Just a few days ago, the worst nightmare
of every open-source maintainer finally
came true. No, they weren't forced to
socialize with the opposite sex.
Instead, in just 6 minutes, which I've
been arguing for years is actually quite
a long time, over 100 packages that
collectively get downloaded more than 50
million times a week were compromised in
a supply chain attack where no one was
fished, no passwords were leaked, and no
tokens were stolen. And to make it even
worse, the poisoned packages were
signed, verified, and shipped through
NPM's trusted publishing feature, which
was built primarily to prevent these
kinds of attacks and has been the
recommended publishing setup for almost
2 years now. In today's video, we'll
break down the clever trick that let an
attacker hijack the release pipeline of
one of the biggest projects in the React
ecosystem. We'll see how the malware
then spread to hundreds of other
packages and learn about the dead man's
switch, which is now on every infected
machine that will nuke your home folder
the second you try to clean it up.
Heaven help us all. It is May 14th,
2026, and you're watching The Code
Report. Life has been extra exciting
lately because every time I wake up, I
wonder which one is going to destroy my
life first, the rodent poop cruise virus
or the mini shai hulud virus.
Thankfully, I'm no poop expert, so I'll
stick with breaking down how the shai
hulud prairie dog bit his little head
again in a fairly sophisticated attack
that no one saw coming, and it all
started with how TanStack's release
process works. Whenever a new pull
request is merged, a GitHub Actions
workflow kicks off, which handles
publishing the new version to the NPM
registry. But to do that, the continuous
integration server needs to get a
publish token from NPM first. To prove
the request is legit, GitHub itself
signs a statement saying which workflow
is running, in which repo, and on which
branch. NPM then checks that signed
statement against the org's allow list
and only hands over a token if
everything matches. The token then lives
for a few minutes in the CI's cache and
then quickly becomes stale, so there's
nothing for traditional fishing attacks
to steal. It sounds bulletproof, but the
problem is that the mini Shai Hulud
attack wasn't traditional. Here's how it
worked. The attacker forked the TanStack
repo, created a pull request, and then
immediately closed it. Even though it
was just a fork, and the pull request
was never seen by anyone, it just
creating the PR was enough to kick off
the publishing workflow. And this is
where the TanStack team went wrong,
because when they configured the trigger
for the workflow, they used the pull
request target option, which meant that
any pull request that came in would run
in the context of the main repository
along with the main repository's
permissions, even if the PR was created
from a fork. And those permissions were
enough to allow the attacker's code to
write a poisoned file into the shared
cache of the CI server, which is used by
GitHub Actions to reuse dependencies
between jobs. A few hours later, an
unrelated pull request was merged into
main, and the poisoned file was
triggered, which grabbed the NPM publish
token from the cache and used it to take
a massive Shai Hulud dump on the 84
brand new compromised TanStack packages.
From there, if you were lucky enough to
NPM install one of those packages, the
malware ran and scanned your system for
anything valuable it could get its
grubby little set tay on. And if it
found any NPM publishing tokens, it used
those to publish new poisoned versions
with the same hack, which is how a
TanStack problem became an everybody
problem. The first wave of victims
included maintainers at Mistral AI,
UiPath, Open Search, Guardrails AI, and
Squawk. Within hours, those companies
pushed compromised packages onto the NPM
registry as well. And through their
Python SDKs, the worm jumped the shark
over to PyPI. By the next morning,
security firm Akamai was tracking 373
poisoned versions across 169 packages,
and the worm was getting even smarter.
It started forging commits signed by the
Claude Code GitHub app, so its malicious
activity blended in with the
AI-generated commits maintainers were
already used to seeing. And on infected
machines, it embedded itself directly
into Claude Code in VS Code, so even
after a developer uninstalled the bad
packages, the worm would just re-execute
itself the next time they open their
editor. And my favorite part, if you
were infected, the malware also
installed a background process that
would quietly check every 60 seconds
whether your stolen GitHub token was
still valid. The moment your token
expires, it activates war crime mode and
nukes your root directory. So, how do we
prevent this in the future? Well, the
reality is that we probably don't, but
there are some things you can do on your
end to help your odds. The best would be
to use pnpm 11 or higher, which comes
with two features turned on by default
that would have stopped this exact worm
from reaching most of you. The first is
minimum release age. It tells pnpm to
refuse any packages published less than
24 hours ago, which is long past when
most malicious packages are detected and
pulled from the registry. The second is
block exotic subdependencies. Normally,
every transitive dependency in your
project comes from the npm registry, but
there's nothing stopping a package from
listing a dependency that points at a
random Git repo or a tarball URL on some
attacker's S3 bucket. Block exotic
subdeps refuses to install anything that
doesn't come through a proper registry,
which closes one of the most elegant
ways for malware to smuggle itself in.
And the third pnpm feature we're using
is approved builds. Most npm malware
does its damage through install scripts
that run automatically when you type npm
install. pnpm 11 blocks all of them by
default and lets you walk through your
dependencies and whitelist a few
packages you actually want to let run
code. But even when you use pnpm, things
can still break in production, and
that's where Sentry, today's sponsor,
can help you out. They just shipped
Sentry agent, an AI agent that
investigates your production issues for
you. So, the next time you get a jump
scare Slack notification about a bunch
of new errors, you can just ask Sentry
agent to investigate the problem instead
of manually digging through dashboards
and logs yourself. The agent uses all
the context Sentry already has on your
system to pull traces, spans, logs, and
replays. Then it walks upstream across
your services to find the actual root
cause. From there, you can work with
Seer to draft a fix and open a pull
request so you can spend less time
staring at error messages and more time
pretending to touch grass. The
developers are calling it a self-healing
software, and you can try it out for
free right now during the open beta at
century.io/fireship.
This has been the Code Report. Thanks
for watching, and I will see you in the
next one.