Last week, Google did something that no
other Fang company has had the balls to
do. They released a large language model
that qualifies as truly free and open
source under the Apache 2.0 license.
That means free as in total freedom, not
openish, not research only, not please
don't make money or we'll sue you. That
model is Gemma 4, and my initial thought
was, "Oh great, another half-baked open
model that's technically free as long as
you also own a small data center to run
it." But the craziest thing about Gemma
4 is that it's small. Like suspiciously
small. The big model is small enough to
run on a consumer GPU, and the edge
model is small enough to run on your
phone or Raspberry Pi while hitting
intelligence levels that are on par with
other open models that would normally
require data center caliber GPUs just to
run. That shouldn't be possible. And in
today's video, we'll find out how it
works and look at some other crazy
compression techniques developed by
Google. It is April 8th, 2026, and
you're watching The Code Report. To be
fair, several other companies in the
game and family have released open
weight models. Like Meta's Llama models
are quasi-free and open, but under a
special license that gives Meta leverage
to any developer that actually starts
printing cash with them. Then we have
OpenAI's GPT-OSS models, which are also
Apache 2.0 licensed, but they're bigger
and dumber than Gemma. Outside of that,
we basically rely on Mistral and the
Chinese models like Qwen, GLM, Kimmi,
and DeepSeek. Gemma 4 hits different
though because it's made in America,
Apache 2.0 licensed, intelligent, and
most importantly, tiny. For comparison,
the 31 billion parameter version of
Gemma 4 is scoring in the same ballpark
as models like Kimmi K 2.5 thinking. But
here's the absurd part. I can run Gemma
4 locally with a 20 GB download getting
roughly 10 tokens per second on a single
RTX 4090. But if I wanted to run Kimmi K
2.5, I'd be looking at a 600-plus GB
download, at least 256 GB of RAM,
aggressive quantization, and multiple
H100s just to get it off the ground. Is
Kimmi still a better model than Gemma?
But there's no way in hell I'm going to
run it locally. So the obvious question
is how did Google achieve this
unbelievable shrinkage? Well, the answer
is they didn't just shrink the model.
They attacked the real bottleneck in AI,
memory. To run a massive large language
model locally, you don't need a better
CPU. You need more memory bandwidth.
Every time a model generates a token, it
has to read through a massive amount of
model weights in VRAM, which is the
video random access memory on your GPU.
It doesn't really matter how big the
model is. It's more about how expensive
it is to read it. And this is where
things get interesting because alongside
Gemma 4, Google quietly dropped a
research note on something called
Turboquant, which sounds like a
marketing buzzword, but it's actually
kind of insane. It's a new approach to
quantization, which is the process of
compressing model weights so they take
up less space. Normally, through this
process, you get a simple tradeoff, a
smaller model but worse performance. But
Turboquant improves this tradeoff with
two steps. First, it compresses data
that's normally in an XYZ Cartesian
coordinate system into polar coordinates
that include a radius and angle. Because
these angles follow a predictable
pattern, the model can skip the typical
normalization steps and store
information more efficiently, thus
reducing memory overhead. Then it uses
this mathematical technique called the
Johnson-Lindenstrauss transform to
shrink high-dimensional data by
compressing it down to single sign bits,
positive one, negative one, while
preserving the distances between these
data points. Frankly, I'm too stupid to
understand how the math actually works,
but Turboquant is actually not the
secret behind Gemma 4's small models.
You'll notice that some of the Gemma 4
models have an E in the model name like
E2B and E4B. And what that stands for is
effective parameters because these
models incorporate something called
per-layer embeddings, which is like
giving every layer in the neural network
its own mini cheat sheet for each token.
In a normal transformer, each token gets
one embedding at the start, and the
model has to carry that information
through every layer. And most of that
information isn't needed. Per-layer
embeddings changes that by giving each
layer its own small custom version of
the token. So information can be
introduced exactly when it's useful
instead of all at once. There's an
incredible visual guide by Martin
Groothuis that I'll link in the
description if you want to dive into
more detail. The end result is a small,
smart, and efficient model. I'm running
it here with Ollama on my RTX 4090, and
my initial impression is that it's a
solid all-around model, and it would
also be a great model for fine-tuning
with your own data using tools like
Unsloth. But if you're a programmer,
it's still not good enough to replace
any high-end coding tools like Code
Rabbit, the sponsor of today's video.
They just launched a CLI update that
lets it review all the code your agent
writes, then tells it exactly how to fix
any bugs it finds. You can enable this
with a new \dash} \dash} agent flag,
which turns Code Rabbit into a tool your
agent can call directly. From there,
it'll give your agent structured JSON
with all of the issues plus instructions
on how to fix them so your agent can go
back and clean everything up before it
opens up a pull request. They also
simplified the setup process and removed
their rate limits so you can get started
with a single terminal command and run
as many reviews as your agents need. Try
it out for free today using the Code
Rabbit off login command and use it free
forever on any open source project. This
has been The Code Report. Thanks for
watching, and I will see you in the next
one.