Before I write a single line of Solana
code, we need to get your machine set up
properly. So, let's go over what we'll
be installing. First, [music] Rust.
Solana programs are written in Rust, so
we need the Rust compiler and Cargo,
which is Rust package manager. If you've
never written with Rust before, don't
worry. We'll cover everything you need
to know, but the tool chain needs to be
there.
Second is the Solana CLI. This is
[music] your command line interface for
interacting with Solana networks. You'll
use it to create wallets, deploy
programs, check balances, [music]
airdrop yourself devnet SOL, and a lot
more. It's essential.
Third is Anchor. Anchor is a framework
that makes Solana development
significantly easier. It handles a lot
of the boilerplate and security checks
that you'd otherwise have to write
manually. Most production Solana
programs today are built with Anchor,
and it's what we'll be using throughout
this bootcamp.
>> [music]
>> And fourth is Surf Pool. This is a local
test validator that's extremely fast.
Instead of waiting for transactions to
confirm on devnet, you can test locally
and get instant feedback on your [music]
code. It's a huge productivity boost
when you are iterating quickly. Now,
I'll be showing this on a Mac, but I'll
include instructions for other operating
systems. The process is pretty similar
across platforms. [music] Now, let's get
started.
So, we're going to go straight to the
Solana docs. So, solana.com/docs,
and there is going to be an installation
section. And this is going to go over
everything you need to set up your
environment. And it's pretty simple
because everything's been wrapped into
this curl command to install all the
dependencies that you need. So, this is
going to cover Rust, the Solana CLI,
Anchor CLI, Surf Pool, Node.js, and
Yarn. One thing to note, though, is if
you are running Windows or Linux, there
are pre-reqs that you're going to have
to meet before actually running this
curl command in your terminal.
I am running a Mac, so I can't show you
how to do it, but um if you just go to
the documentation, everything is very
explicitly stated here for you to follow
along.
And once that's all set up, then we can
get to our install. So, here we're just
going to very simply copy these
commands, and we're going to paste it
into our terminal.
And we'll let this run. It's going to
take some time to run, but what it's
going to do is it's going to make sure
all of the dependencies are installed on
your machine. And once they are, then
it's going to move on to the next one.
If you already have things installed, it
won't reinstall it. So, you can see mine
ran pretty fast just because I already
did have everything installed on my
machine.
Um and then it's also going to check
versions for you. And then once it's all
installed, you'll see that it says
installation complete, please restart
your terminal to apply all changes. So,
I'm just going to close this out, and
then we're going to reopen the terminal.
I'll zoom in a bit for you there.
And then all we're going to do is check
to make sure everything was installed
correctly. So, that command is also
explained here in the docs, and all it
is is checking the version of each
dependency that was installed on your
computer. So, we're just going to copy
that and paste it into our terminal.
And you can see I have Rust, Solana CLI,
Anchor CLI, and Surf Pool all installed.
So, we're all good to go there. Now that
that's set up, if you are curious to
dive deeper into each of these CLIs and
all the basics that go along with it,
there are docs for each of them. So, you
can go into these pages here and just
take a look
and figure everything out on how you can
use these CLIs. These will be used
throughout the rest of the bootcamp, so
you don't have to read through this
documentation. You can follow along with
the rest of our courses, but if you're
curious now, take a look. And then we're
just going to go over a few more basics
for getting your computer ready, so then
you can follow along for the rest of our
projects. So, the next thing I'm going
to look at is setting up your local
wallet on your computer.
So, if I go to terminal, if I type in
Solana address, it's using the CLI to
check what wallet is connected as your
local key pair on your machine. So, I'm
going to type this in, and you can see I
have no signer found right now. Um
most of the time it's going to show that
unless you've already set it up. So, if
you're just installing for the first
time, this is the output that you're
going to get, and you're going to be
able to run Solana keygen new.
And what this is, so the command
actually tells you what to run, which
makes it easy. But what this is doing is
it's generating a new key pair and
storing that on your machine.
Now that's created, you're going to have
your seed phrase displayed on the
screen. Mine's going to be blurred out,
so you can't see it. Um but make sure
you save that. It's going to be how
you're going to access your wallet in
the future. And then you're going to be
able to see what that wallet address is.
So, here this is your public key that's
returned.
Um if I type in Solana address now, it
should return the same public key. So,
you can see that these match up, and
that is my local key pair on my machine.
So, now if I'm going to want to test
anything out locally, it's going to use
this wallet. And for me to be able to
test, I'm going to need some devnet SOL
in my wallet. So, how are we going to
get that? Well, there is a faucet, so I
can take this address, and we're going
to go to the Solana devnet faucet, and
we're just going to paste that in,
choose an amount, and confirm the
airdrop.
And
this does require you to connect your
GitHub. I don't want to connect
[clears throat] mine currently, um just
cuz that'll have all of my login, but
we'll go back. There is another method
that you can use. This is going to have
a rate limit on it, so it's a lot more
efficient to use the faucet. But if you
go straight into the Solana CLI and you
type in Solana airdrop, and I just type
in two, it's [snorts] going to request
two SOL to my wallet.
And you can see that this rate limit was
reached because I'm using Wi-Fi that a
lot of other people are using right now
and probably already requested some SOL.
So, I'm going to
just go to another browser where my
GitHub is actually logged in. So, one
second.
I'm going to open that.
And we're going to go to the devnet
faucet.
Okay.
So, I'll connect my GitHub here,
and then I'll paste in the wallet
address, and then we're going to choose
an amount, and we'll confirm the
airdrop.
So, we'll verify that.
And you can see the airdrop was
successful.
So, now we have funds on our wallet, and
we're going to be able to use it for
testing purposes. Now, we can confirm
that this actually happened by using the
explorer. So, the explorer is Solana's
block explorer, and what this does is it
shows you recent transactions, token
account, mint account, wallet accounts,
um
just activity that happens on chain. And
it's also going to connect to different
clusters. So, here you can see we're
connected to mainnet beta, which is
Solana's mainnet. It's where all of the
actual real traffic happens. There's
other clusters. So, you have localnet
when you're running a validator locally
on your machine. There's testnet where
mainly the network team works on testing
things, and then devnet, which is where
you'll be testing things for um
just when you're building.
So, here you can see I airdropped
devnet SOL to my wallet. So, we're going
to check that. If I paste in my wallet
address here,
and I'm now connected to devnet, we'll
click over, and you can see my balance
on my wallet is now five SOL because I
just requested five SOL from the
airdrop. So, that's an overview of
pretty much all the basics you need to
be set up on your computer. We went over
installing all of the dependencies on
your machine, how to set up your wallet
locally in your terminal, how to request
funds to your wallet, and then how to
use the Solana block explorer. So, now
you're all good to go. You have your
machine set up to start working through
the tutorials in the bootcamp.