Now, another common question people ask
me would be, "Adam, why don't you hedge
your portfolio if you think the market's
in a correction or bear market?" Now,
for those of you who don't understand
what is hedging, hedging means like
buying insurance. Like you think the
market's going to go down, you buy a lot
of put options. So, when the market goes
down, your put options will make you
money. Or you can, of course, short the
market or you can buy inverse ETFs. Now,
I used to do a lot of hedging in the
past. I don't really hedge much anymore.
And the reason is because hedging is not
free. And again, when you hedge, which
means you buy inverse ETFs, you short
the market, you buy put options, yes, I
would say that one out of five times the
market will go a lot lower and you'll
make money on your put options or your
hedges.
But four out of five times, after you
hedge, the market reverses back up very
strongly and your put options lose you
money, your shorts lose you money. And
so, by doing that in the long run, you
find that hedging actually reduces your
return.