Is SpaceX a good business? After doing a
lot of research, I think yes. In fact, I
think it's a phenomenal business with a
wide economic moat, which means it's got
a sustainable competitive advantage that
is way ahead of the competition. So,
what does SpaceX do? Well, they've got
four main businesses. Their most
profitable business is Starlink. I'm
sure you've heard of Starlink, which is
a global high-speed satellite internet
business, which currently has got over 9
million users.
This is high-margin recurring revenue
business. The second business is their
launch services, which is also very
profitable. And this focuses on
commercial and government launch
operations for NASA, for the Department
of Defense, and commercial clients.
Then, you've got Starshield, the third
business, where they focus on secure
satellite network for defense and
national security, military-grade
capabilities. And then, finally, they've
got Starship, where they offer fully
reusable large-capacity rocket systems,
potential for deep space and huge
payloads. There's been a lot of talk
about sending and building data centers
in space. Well, you need these Starships
to launch them into space, all right?
So, out of all these four businesses,
they generate a total sales revenue of
15 to 16 billion dollars as of the end
of last year, 2025. And are they
profitable? Yes, they are profitable not
on a GAAP basis, but EBITDA
positive. EBITDA means earnings before
taxes, before depreciation, and before
amortization profit of 8 billion
dollars. So, that is as of the end of
last year. Now, 5 years from now, in
2030, they're projected to have a
revenue of 50 billion dollars, as well
as an EBITDA of 25 billion dollars. So,
from now to 5 years, the projected
growth rate for For profits is about
25.6%
compounded annual growth rate.
Currently, 60% of their revenue comes
from Starlink, which is their high-speed
satellite internet. And for their launch
services, they control 80% of all
commercial mass to orbit. So, they are a
current monopoly in that business.