When I came to pick up my things from
the office that morning, I came to the
office and they were refusing to let um
anybody that got laid off into um the
building. I think at that moment it kind
of felt like a bit dehumanizing. Dang, I
worked at this company for so long and
like I'm not able to even go to my desk
and like say goodbye to like any of my
co-workers or like pick up my things.
Like this seems pretty messed up to me.
A lot of people were like leaving the
building at that time. So, I ran into
like some of my friends who I don't even
primarily work with. They came out and
then they saw me and then they felt
really bad and like started like
huddling around me and like hugging me.
>> Oh my god. I'm so sorry.
>> No, no, no. It's okay. It's okay.
Dennis, UC Berkeley,
AI generated
by Oracle.
Berkeley CSP.
Hi Dennis, welcome to the channel. Thank
you for coming on the interview. Dennis
is one of my friends back in Berkeley.
Um, do you want to say hi to our
audience first?
>> Hello, my name is Dennis. I'm from UC
Berkeley and um, I'm originally from
Seattle, Washington.
>> Yeah. So, today we wanted to talk about
your experience at Oracle. So, we're
going to start from like at the
beginning like when you decided to join
Oracle because you graduated Berkeley
the same year as me, right? Um, 2022.
and uh what offers did you had in hand
back at that time and also why did you
choose Oracle to be your first job?
>> Yeah, of course. So, when I graduated
from UC Berkeley, I think around March,
I had two offers at the time. It was um
between Oracle and another startup at
the time. Um, and when I applied for
both of these jobs and got the offer, I
think I just kind of like chose Oracle
just because it was like more of an
established company and more of a
reputable um, kind of choice for me and
I think that um, it was really good for
me to like kind of get my foot in the
door as well. So, I kind of wanted to
choose Oracle in that sense.
>> Did you did you think the job search at
the time was hard like back in 2022 or
like compared to now? Cuz I think like
when I did my job search, I already
thought it was really hard and it's it's
definitely harder right now. What how
did you feel about the job search?
>> Yeah, I thought the job search was
pretty difficult at first. I think um
like I said earlier, I got my offer in
March and um I heard other people
getting their offers like earlier than
me. So at the time I kind of felt like
oh I need to get a job secure by the end
of college. So um definitely I thought
that it was a bit difficult um
specifically for me because I did switch
into computer science a bit later a bit
into my um educational journey at
Berkeley right so um I think that I
didn't have as much experience at the
time so um I thought that was a bit
>> of a limiting factor cuz I didn't have
like a return offer from an internship
or anything so I kind of felt like I was
fresh off the boat but um after that I
was able to secure that job so
>> makes sense. I think a lot of our
audience probably don't really know
about what Oracle does probably still
thinks of it as like an old school like
database company and you also worked in
Netswuite which is part of Oracle. Can
you talk about what like Oracle does and
what Netswuite does?
>> Yeah, of course. Um, honestly, I didn't
really know what Oracle did at first
either when I got the job offer. But,
um, besides that, um, I would say that
Oracle is kind of similar to like how,
um, you would say like AWS or Amazon is
like how Amazon generates a lot of their
revenue and money from like cloud
services like handling enterprise
things. Um, Oracle does that in the
sense of like OCI, Oracle infrastructure
where um, they have that cloud and
database um, servers and everything. I
think right now like they're even
planning to like invest a lot of money,
billions of dollars into OpenAI and
building those database and servers for
OpenAI and then they're also storing I
think a majority of Tik Tok data into um
Oracle servers right now. I think
they're part of that like offer when
they um had to um Tik Tok had to like
devest or something like that. Um but
besides that um I think that for um
>> for Netswuite
>> Oh yeah, for Netswuite specifically.
Yeah. Yeah. Sorry. Um, NES, it's like a
more of like an enterprise like
accounting um, software where we work a
lot with businessto business and um,
they mainly handle like all the customer
information, all of the data, the
accounting information for these
companies and um, they kind of aggregate
all of that so then they can know how
much revenue they're making.
>> I see. So before you started at Oracle,
did you have any like how did you
imagine like being an engineer at one of
these big tech companies? And um after
like actually joining, was there
anything that like violated your
expectations or was very different from
what you imagined?
>> Yeah, of course. Um I knew that like if
I were going to work at a company like
Oracle, which is like a really old like
kind of like dinosaur company where like
they were kind of like one of the old
pioneers of like software innovation,
right? Um, I knew that like a lot of the
code that I was going to work with is
going to be like really old or like kind
of like legacy code, right? Um, versus
like if I worked at a startup or like
somewhere new, I can kind of like start
building the code base out, you know,
and like kind of have my own ideas
there. So, in that sense, I was a bit
surprised when I actually started
working where like I didn't really get
to um fully like innovate or like
develop things that I wanted to do. It
was more of like, oh, fix this or like
work on this, like make this product,
but like look at an old existing legacy
code that like as an example and then
just like build off of that, right?
>> Yeah.
>> And probably a lot of tech debts to fix
too.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. A lot of things
to fix. Um definitely like a lot of
customerf facing sides of like um urgent
issues that came up a lot of times like
those things. I think I definitely felt
it could too because um my company it
also scaled from like a smaller company
to like midsize or even like a larger
one. So um a lot of systems that
supported the smalls size um customers
weren't like scalable to like what it is
right now. So there were also like so
much tech that's to fix I definitely
suffered that too.
>> Yeah. And for like the stuff that you
touched dayto day, how much of of it you
think like over overlapped with what you
learned in Berkeley CS or how much of it
like you had to learn from like from a
fresh start after you started working?
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think that like I think a
lot of people mentioned this, but like
you don't necessarily get to apply
everything that you learned when you're
in college to what you're working on. Um
I definitely think that was the case. I
think that like in college you're kind
of like taught like a general sense of
like everything and like it's like you
learn all the material, but like you
don't necessarily have to apply all of
those when you're actually working. Um,
and I think that honestly like
>> I think school prepares me for like le
coding more than actually the job,
right? Um, and I think when you actually
start the job, you get to learn more
about like actually doing the job and
actually like doing the things that
you're going to build because I think
each company kind of like does different
things, has different styles, right? And
you kind of learn have to learn how to
adapt to that style. You have to learn
how to like train yourself to become
like an employee at that company, right?
>> What's your take on like leak coding? Do
you think like being good at leak coding
really means that you're going to be a
good engineer? Um, I think my take on
leak coding is like I think that it's
not a good reflection of like how you
are as an engineer. I think that like
definitely they just want to see how you
solve a problem, right? They want to see
your logic and your workflow. Um,
personally for me, like if I was like an
interviewer at a company, I would be
more concerned about like how they're
approaching the problem. Like if they're
like kind of a good person to work with.
Are they like explaining their workflow?
Like it doesn't 100% necessarily be
correct. like do they seem like they
have that knowledge, right? Because I
don't think everything's like black and
white of oh, can you pass it? Can you
like just get it done, right? I think um
even now with like AI and like all like
the new bots and everything that can
help you with these interview questions,
I think that a lot of times people are
kind of wondering like how do you
approach like solving things using AI,
right? Like how do you prompt things in
the future? I think that's also why a
lot of startups right now like they do
interviews with like you just go in the
office and work with them for a day so
they can know like your working style
and stuff. It's not really about like
solving like algorithm problems or
stuff.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. For sure. For sure.
>> Um and I know um so a lot of audience
might be curious about the compensation
um but this is also a very sensitive
topic. So just share whatever you feel
like you're willing to share. But um can
you give us a sense of what the like the
comp structure as a as a suite too at
Oracle will look like? Like what's the
what's the split or whatever you're
willing to share? Yeah,
>> of course. Um so when I got my first
offer at Oracle, I think the general
gist is like the first four years you
work at a tech company, that's generally
the most you're going to be paid. Um, so
for me, I was paid $120,000 for the
salary. And then for the sign on bonus,
I was paid 20,000 and then relocation
10,000. And then um for the stocks, um,
at the time I did join Oracle at a
pretty good price. I think the stock
price was like about $60 at the time.
>> How much is it right now?
>> It's about 300. Oh, wait, not right now.
Actually, the peak was like 320 in
October. Now it's at 200 sadly. But um
yeah, I did join at a really good time
about like $60 or something. And at that
time it was about like $40,000 my first
year. So my first um year was about like
190,000 and then um my third year it was
about um from the stocks it kind of like
tripled or quadrupled basically. So um
by my third year I made about 280,000. I
also think that like uh when I got
promoted as well, I got um a salary bump
as well and um stock refreshes as well.
>> Uhuh. With like Oracle, it really is
because the stock prices like went up a
lot. So I think the the comp really
varies a lot. It's just like goes up and
down with the SC stocks basically,
right? And also you mentioned
promotions. So you worked at Oracle for
like three and a half years, right? Like
how many times did you get promoted or
how does it work there?
>> Yeah. Um, I would say that the promotion
is pretty slow at Oracle. I know that
it's pretty slow at like a lot of kind
of like old established companies. Um,
and if you wanted to get promoted fast,
it would typically be like a startup,
right? But at Oracle, I think many times
when I was working there, um, I always
heard that there was like, oh, we're
having a hiring freeze or we're having a
promotion freeze, which is also a layoff
indicator.
But basically, I asked my manager like,
oh, what can I do to get promoted? What
can I do to get promoted? And every
single time my manager said like, "Oh,
we're having a promotion freeze. Like
nobody else is getting promoted right
now." Or the other thing was like, "Oh
yeah, I tried submitting like an
application to like get you promoted,
but then it was just rejected by like VP
or whatever." Right. So like sometimes
the manager just doesn't have complete
control over if they can promote people.
I think it's just more of like budgeting
and stuff like that. Even if you have
the performance, you've been at the
company for a long time, sometimes you
just aren't able to get the promotion,
right? So, I did end up getting promoted
actually um actually a couple months
ago. It was pretty bad because like I
got promoted like in January and then
laid off in March. So, um yeah, it was
like um they promoted me and then laid
me off basically.
>> How long do you think on average it
takes now for like a promotion just from
like sweet one to two?
>> Mhm. I think um generally like I know a
lot of people they do get promoted
within like one or two years. Um, three
years is definitely like kind of like on
the longer end of getting promoted on
things, but I think that's just
completely dependent on like company or
like where you work at, not necessarily
like your performance.
>> Yeah, that makes sense. And also from
inside Oracle, uh, now that there's like
the big like AI bloom, uh, what what do
you think is the company's attitude
towards like AI? Is do they want to like
lead um AI or are they more like a a
thing a trend that they need to keep up
with? I'm not 100% sure if they I would
say like they are kind of like leading
the way with AI. I think definitely like
they are trying to keep up with it. Um
when I was working at Oracle, I know
that like we were always being trained
on like what's the newest AI tool that
we can use to integrate towards our
work, right? Um, I found that like we're
pretty good partners or we we were good
partners with um, OpenAI and kind of
like how I was talking earlier, we
invested billions of dollars into like
having these servers for OpenAI and um,
definitely we are trying to like use a
lot of our money into like investing
into it. And I think that when I was
working there, we were also like a lot
of the people on my team were told to
like keep up to date with it, attend
these training workshops. So I think I
did get to use like codecs, use a lot of
other um AI tools that helped expedite
my work.
>> So speaking of the layoff, um in the
last few months before the layoff, do
you think uh there was a shift in the
like company's atmosphere or were there
signals that were hinting towards a
layoff?
>> Yeah, for sure. Um I think like with any
company that you're going to be working
at, there's definitely like work gossip,
right?
>> Rumors around.
>> Yeah, rumors around. And it's always
like, "Oh, did you hear the news? Like
there's going to be a layoff next week
or something like that." And then next
week happens, it doesn't happen. But
like um sometimes it's just like
completely random whenever it happens.
And um I think even with my co-workers,
we were all talking about it and it was
just kind of word of mouth and um even
my managers um they weren't able to talk
about it. They were just like, you know,
we have to just continue working.
There's nothing else we could really do.
It's just completely random, right? And
um I think there are obviously signs as
well kind of like how I said earlier
like promotion freeze, hiring freeze,
those are all pretty big indicators. And
even like restructuring, I think I saw a
lot of people saying like, "Oh,
restructuring is a pretty big sign." But
I didn't realize it until like it
happened here at Oracle. Like I just saw
people getting moved to different teams,
people getting positions that like they
weren't positioned before, right? Like
just different positions that they um
have now. So I think those were all
signs of like kind of like
>> a layoff was coming.
>> Yeah. Did you feel like uh people
knowing that a layoff might be coming um
started like spending more energy on
like interviewing outside or taking like
a a pause on their work or like not
really working. Was that happening?
>> Yeah. Like I think like for some people
it definitely was happening. It was just
like kind of like losing the urgency or
like sense of like having to work
because like oh you might potentially
get laid off like within next week,
right? and everyone is like kind of like
saying like oh like 30,000 people right
it's like pretty daunting and pretty a
lot right so like you're just like oh at
that point like why am I even working
why am I trying to finish this project
like why am I like working on the
weekend to finish this out if I'm might
just get cut like
>> next next week right so I definitely
think a lot of people were pretty
stressed out about it and like just
deciding
>> potentially not to work and finish their
things um and definitely I think a lot
of people were on the mind of like oh
how can I prepare prepare myself for
when I like leave this job, right? Um I
know a lot of people were like kind of
like looking into things of like
preparing their resume, preparing like a
lot of things that they worked on before
backing up things that they were working
on before they leave.
>> I see. Like in hindsight, if you had
known it like more in advance, like six
months in advance that the layoff was
happening, um would there be anything
that you have done differently? You
would have done it differently?
>> I think like maybe like six months in
advance. I don't necessarily think that
there's much I would have done
differently other than the fact that
like I probably would have saved a lot
more money. Um I would have probably
like put more money into like my high
yield savings account and everything
like that. Um for me like I generally
just put all my stuff in stocks and I
think that like being laid off in March
and then having taxes due in April was
like pretty big for me because like I
felt like
>> the market was also not good.
>> Yeah, the market was also not good too.
So, I was like, "Dang, I really need the
money right now to pay off my huge tax
bill, right? But I also have all that
money saved up for like rent and all
those like emergency fundings." So,
like, what can I do now? Should I sell
my stocks? No, the stock is bad right
now. So, it's like kind of you kind of
expect that you should have more money
saved in your high yield savings
account, probably more than you expect,
and not have it locked up in stocks
because you might have that hesitation
of like, you know, selling, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um so the actual day um the
layoff day was March 31st, right? Um how
did that day go for you? Um like what
what happened? What was the first thing
you did and how did you hear about the
news?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Of course. Um so when
I got laid off, I heard the news
actually like two weeks before it
happened. Um it was like more of like
word of mouth all over the news like oh
like Bloomberg released that like oh
Oracle is planning to lay out 30,000
employees, right? So it was always a on
a lot of our minds and I think that like
I just heard the day before like from a
couple of other employees like oh
layoffs are happening tomorrow like
Mexico just got hit or like oh like
Canada just got hit like people are
disappearing on Slack. So I was like
dang okay. And then my friend um told me
like they're going to send out an email
tomorrow morning or something like that
at 6:00 a.m. And I was like okay dang
that's pretty crazy. But then knowing
me, I was like, okay, like if I get laid
off, it's whatever, you know, like I
don't tend to cry over that type of
thing, you know? So like if it just
happens, it happens. But like it was the
fact that I just wanted that
confirmation to know if I got laid off
or not, right? Um so I ended up staying
up until like 3:00 a.m. that night
because I was like
>> I just want to know if I got laid off or
not. So then I got that email at 3:00
a.m. It's like saying like, oh, it was
at 3:00 a.m. Yeah, it was pretty crazy.
I was like, "Dang, 3:00 a.m." But they
sent it at 3:00 a.m. and then they were
like, "Hey, you got laid off, right?"
And then I thought, "Okay, I'll just go
to sleep now." You know, like I got that
confirmation I needed, right? But then
after that, I was like could not sleep
the entire night, right? So I stayed up
the entire night. I pulled an
allnighter. It was like, "Okay, let me
just get my mind off of things now
because now like I should apply for
unemployment benefits now. I should
apply for anything that I need to get
myself financially secure. So then like
I can look for a job in the future,
right? So, that's what I did after I got
laid off. And then, um, I had my morning
meeting with my manager that day. He
texted me at like 8:30 a.m., "Hey, like,
can you hop on for a quick Zoom call?"
>> And I already knew what was happening
cuz I got the email, right? We had that
call and it was him and his upper
manager. And, um, he basically told me
like, "Hey, like, you know, this is
completely random. Like, it's not
performance- based at all. Like, you
know, these things happen. I'm really
sorry to hear that." Blah, blah, blah.
Um I'm not sure if I can reveal too much
about the phone call, but um that's
basically the gist of what happened. We
just had that phone call that morning.
>> Mhm. And then that day did like all of
your stuff got like deactivated and you
lose access immediately or how did how
did that go? Yeah, at 3:00 a.m. on um I
got the email notification for my work
company email. And then um I tried
checking Slack because um I felt like a
lot of people would be posting on Slack,
but then my Slack was immediately
deactivated at 3:00 a.m. And then at
9:00 a.m. when I had that morning
meeting call with my manager, um that's
when I stopped having access to my um
Outlook and my um laptop as well. M so
you basically didn't have much time to
like did were there anything that you
had to do before like everything got
deactivated cuz I know some people try
to like save some like stuff uh for like
future use if you want to show it on
your resume or stuff. Did was there
anything that you had to do before
everything got deactivated? Yeah, I
think um what I did was like I mainly
prepared like things that like that
would help me apply for like job welfare
stuff like kind of like payubs and like
all of the information that I needed so
that I can like apply for things in the
future.
>> I'm not too sure like if you're allowed
to like
>> download all of those other things um
just because they're afraid of
retaliation and stuff like that. But,
uh, for me, I did like kind of just like
look through everything that I've worked
on and kind of like summarize all of
that information just so I had that
information ready in case if I needed to
apply for jobs in the future on my
resume.
>> Yeah.
>> And in terms of like emotionally, what
was your first like emotional reaction
to to all the news or that day?
>> Honestly, like for me, like I'm a pretty
carefree person and like I think that
like oh, if it happens to me, it happens
to me. Like, you know, I'm just going to
look on to bigger and better things,
right? So when I got laid off at first I
was like okay it happened you know like
just got to apply for different thing
got to like move forward with my life
right. I also thought it was like a
really great opportunity for me to like
apply for new new jobs, right? And apply
for new things because a lot of times
people in tech, they tend to like
plateau and like stay at the same job
for too long. And it's always better to
like job hop and like, you know, do
things, right? So, um, at the time I was
I was like, this is a great opportunity.
But then when I came to pick up my
things from the office that morning, I
came to the office and there were
security guards all over the front doors
of each office building and they were
refusing to let um anybody that got laid
off into um the building. Yeah. And um I
called my manager down and I was like,
"Hey, they're not letting me into the
building. You know, they have security
guards here. Like they're not just
letting anyone in." Um and then my
manager like came down and he was like,
"Oh, can I check him in as a guest?"
like, you know, um he just needs to
bring his stuff down. And then the front
desk worker is like, "Sorry, we're not
allowing anybody up to the front desk."
And my manager was like, "Oh, what the
heck?" Um so I think they were just like
really worried about retaliation or
something. But um I think at that moment
it kind of felt like a bit dehumanizing
kind of like, "Dang, I worked at this
company for so long and like I'm not
able to even go to my desk and like say
goodbye to like any of my co-workers or
like pick up my things. Like this this
seems pretty messed up to me." Mhm.
>> So, I had to give my manager like
literally my IKEA bag. I I literally
gave him a bag and he had to go up get
all the things off the desk and like
make sure everything that was used to be
mine is back to me, right? And I think
the saddest and emotional part was like
I was sitting down there like kind of
embarrassed because I was just sitting
down there like in front of the office
for a while and a lot of people who were
working there like just like kept
leaving the office and they just saw the
people waiting outside because they got
laid off, right? So it was a bit awkward
in that sense. But I think the most
emotional part for me was like
>> when I came at a pretty bad time it was
during lunch hours. So like a lot of
people were like leaving the building at
that time. So, I ran into like some of
my friends who I don't even primarily
work with, but like they work on my
floor and I get to like talk to them a
lot. They came out and then they saw me
and then they felt really bad and like
started like huddling around me and like
hugging me. And that made me really
emotional cuz I was like, "Dang, these
people who I don't even necessarily work
with but are friends with care so much
about me and like, you know, this is the
most humanizing thing about like work at
Oracle, right?" So, I think that's what
made me like a bit more emotional than I
thought. So, I started crying and like
being upset. I was like, "Dang, like you
guys are so sweet. You guys are so kind.
Um, I really appreciate you guys like
coming down here and like keeping in
contact with me."
>> Yeah. Oh my god. I feel so sorry.
>> No, no, no. It's okay. It's okay. That
that was just my experience. Yeah.
>> Mhm. Yeah. It's that that sounded kind
of messed up like not not letting you
pick up stuff for from your desk. Um was
good that you still got everything.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. What was another surprising story
was like one of my friends who also got
laid off. She had her entire org laid
off. Like her entire like manager, VP,
everybody on her floor got laid off. And
when she went to the front desk, um they
were like, "Sorry, nobody's allowed up.
Do you have like a manager to bring your
things down?" And she was like, "No, my
whole or got like removed. Like my whole
or got like cut off, so like how am I
supposed to get my things?" And then the
security guard was like, "Sorry, like I
don't know what else to say for you."
And then um she had to like end up
communicating with one of her friends
from a different floor to come to her
floor to get all of her things for her
which was like
>> the messed up thing, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Um so I guess also part for part of the
layoff um what people might be curious
is about is about the the severance
packages and also this might be a
sensitive topic as well.
um just whatever you're willing to
share, but how did it work at Oracle and
like compared to what people know about
like the Fang company severance
packages? Do you think it's on like the
heavier side or lighter side or like
comparable? M I think it's definitely on
the lighter side, but um luckily we live
in California where like I think anybody
that gets laid off from like a
California company, like if you live if
you're based in California, it's
different if you work remotely. But um
if you're based in California, you're
guaranteed 60 days of war notice where
you're technically employed at the
company until like 2 months after the
layoff date. So like for example, March
31st, it would be like June 1st. you
would actually be terminated from the
company.
>> So, you're still technically on payroll
until then. And then, um, as for
severance, I think the general gist was
like, oh, you get two weeks of like bare
minimum severance regardless of how many
you work there. And then I think for
every year you worked after 2 years, you
get only one week of severance. So, I
think like if I had worked at Oracle and
I was like in a remote position, not in
California, I probably would have only
had like 3 weeks of like severance pay
or something like that.
>> I see. Do you think it was offset
because of the the 60 days thing?
>> Yeah. Yeah, it was offset by the 60-day
warrant notice. Um, so basically, um,
yeah, that's why it was like,
>> yeah, I didn't know about those 60 days,
but now that I think of it, it will be
really important for like foreigners
working as well, cuz if they're on like
H-1B, then they need to need to have a
new job within like 90 days, right? But
if they are on payroll, then technically
they have like two more months. So, they
have like five months to search for a
new job.
>> That's very important.
>> It's definitely important for that.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. And so with the layoff that
affected around like 30k people um what
did the collective feeling look like um
among the community if you like talk to
your colleagues and stuff how did people
feel? Yeah, I think um all around it was
pretty like devastating. Like I think
within like specifically Oracle
Netswuite um because Netswuite was like
a company that was like acquired by
Oracle. Uh we were pretty like immune to
layoffs for a while. Like we didn't have
layoffs until the first time in like
August where they laid people off and
that was like already a pretty big
shock. Like the environment was like
quiet the next day and like we just like
felt like the environment was just
really weird. Um, and then when I got
laid off, I think like a couple of other
colleagues and co-workers reached out to
me and like were asking me like how I'm
feeling, blah, blah, blah. Just like the
whole like, you know, general.
>> Yeah. Was it that did a lot of people on
your team got cut or is it just like
some people or did like your whole team
dissolve?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, um, luckily like
my team wasn't hit that hard. I know
that other people within my floor, their
entire team got cut. I think this time
it just appeared to be like they cut off
entire orgs or they cut off entire teams
or they maybe laid off a couple of
engineers on another team that's like
pretty important probably.
>> I see. I see.
>> Um so I think this time um it was like
um me and then another um person on our
team.
>> Um and for that I think that like she
was like a pretty big senior on our team
as well. And um
>> yeah,
>> I see. Um, do you think it mostly hit
like engineering or like what kind of
people or what kind of teams were mostly
hit?
>> Um, I think that like I don't
necessarily think it was mostly
engineering. I think it was mostly just
like
>> Oracle restructuring. I think they um
realized that like hey, we're spending
too much money in these types of areas
that aren't necessarily profitable
>> and they felt like maybe like we need to
budget our resources better. I see. Um,
so I think that's probably also why like
me and the other person got laid off
just because kind of like how I
mentioned earlier like I felt like I
joined at a really good time and in
order to like cut me it would save like
maybe two other engineers on our team,
right? Versus like if they had cut
somebody else then maybe they would have
laid off four people instead of two
people, right?
>> That makes sense. And um so after the
layoff um I saw your LinkedIn post like
uh a few weeks ago. You said that you
deliberately like chose not to touch
like job applications for a while. So um
why did that make why do you make that
call and um or did you like take a few
days to think through like what you
wanted to do next or like what was
happening after it?
>> Yeah, of course. So, I think the reason
why I made that deliberate call was
because um I felt the need to like kind
of have like a clear state of mind and I
wanted to fully prepare myself and make
sure I'm ready to like enter the job
market again just because I think that
like a lot of times people do apply
right away and like they not they're not
necessarily prepared or mentally cleared
to like you know
>> apply for things again. And I thought it
was like a really great opportunity for
me to like pick things back up, like
call my mom again, call my friends
again, reconnect with like things that I
felt like I wasn't able to do before,
right? And um with that, I was able to
like go on vacation more or like do
things that like I I wasn't necessarily
able to do while I was working at
Oracle.
>> Mhm. For the layoff news, who who who
were the first people that you you told
and like what was their reaction? Uh
actually like I was um I messaged my
family the day before and I was like
Oracle layoff news again. Pray for me
tomorrow when I got the email. I
screenshotted the email and I sent it to
my family group chat. I was like I got
hit but um yeah my family was the first
to know.
>> Yeah.
>> I see. So yeah. What what did you
actually do that month like when you
when you were preparing yourself?
>> Yeah. Um what I did that month was I
basically called my mom. I facetimed her
like almost every day for a couple of
hours actually, like just doing my
day-to-day activities. And I called my
friends. I reconnected with people that
I didn't really get to talk to as much
as I wanted to.
>> Um, I went on vacation. I went to
Coachella. I went to LA just to like
have some fun again. And then, um,
hobbies, I got to like pick up cooking
and baking again. I know that in like in
college I was able to like cook a lot
and like do like a lot of recipes that
like I never got to explore. But like
when I started working I kind of like
just made scrap meals every day or meal
prepped every day. But this time like I
got to ate like make really really big
dishes and like I got into baking again
and I yeah it was just like a really fun
experience.
>> So back in college I'm actually close
with like one of um Dennis's
sweetitemates or like housemates. So
I've seen him cooking like a lot of good
Vietnamese food.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> But after working, how will you say like
the work life balance is like are you
like drained every day after work that
you just don't have energy to cook?
>> I would say like the work life balance
was pretty good actually at Oracle. I
wouldn't necessarily say like I was
absolutely drained and didn't have
enough time to cook. I think it's just
more of the fact that like you are like
in this routine schedule of like having
to go to work every day and like you
know like do these things and you also
want to stay healthy. You want to go to
the gym. You want to have all these
things, right? So, like if you go into
the office at like 10:00 a.m. or
something, right? And then you get out
of the office at 5:00 p.m. and then you
go to the gym until 7:00 p.m.
>> You have no time to cook anything,
right? Um I would wouldn't say I was
necessarily drained. It's just like that
routine schedule of not being able to
have enough time to do the things that
you necessarily love.
>> I see. And um so after that period um at
what point did you think that okay
you're ready to like get into like
building stuff or like um lead coding or
um going back into job search um what
point that happened and uh what you
actually did after that.
>> Yeah for sure. Um I think like within
like that month of period I did kind of
feel like I wanted to like start
building again and start doing things.
So I thought it would be a great
opportunity for me to like do cloud
coding because I felt like oh I already
learned codec so might as well learn
cloud as well right. So I decided to
vibe code for the first time and just
like try building my own product.
>> What did you vibe code?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, like, um,
basically I kind of like just solved an
issue for myself, which is like, oh, you
know how like you take so many photos at
like vacation or something and then you
have like hundreds of photos of yourself
and you're like, oh, I have to delete
all those like bad photos of me and then
choose the best one. Um, I kind of just
created like this app where like it
basically uses an AI bot to help you
sort through all your photos, like pick
out all the bad ones, delete all of
those, and then also you can import like
your Instagram photos, like reference
photos for the AI bot to learn basically
like what your style is, like what kind
of like, you know, theme you would want,
right? So, that's the app that I built.
And then also like I paid for that
subscription as well, just to like get
my app out there. So, it's like kind of
like just in the testing phase, but I
thought it was a pretty great
opportunity for me to like just do
something for fun.
>> Yeah, that's very very helpful. I really
need that cuz my phone I have like 1 TB
storage for my phone, but like it's
running out.
>> It's crazy. I like I'm going through my
album like what is taking up so much
space.
>> Exactly. For sure.
>> It's cuz I I store so much like videos
on my on my phone too.
>> But yeah, what are what what else other
than like vibe coding?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Um, so then after Vibe
coding, I decided to like get back into
League coding again, obviously, cuz
that's definitely like a must to get
done. Um, and with my Claude
subscription, I was able to um use it to
learn le coding again. So, I asked
Claude to like, you know, hey, build me
like this um Le code study guide or like
help me um relearn all this information,
right? and it was able to really help me
break down like things that were like a
bit unclear before. I would say now that
like even though like it's been years
since I le coded or like years since I
graduated from college, I think that now
I'm kind of better off when I freshly
graduated because there's just so many
tools that can help me learn how to like
le code again.
>> And then um for resume building, I did
that before I was laid off. Actually, I
I heard the layoff news. So, I was like,
"Okay, I got to put down all this
information that I know before I get
laid off as well."
>> Makes sense. Um, with like the job
search now that you're like um applying
or interviewing with different
companies, do you think like the
importance of leak code changed or like
>> what is the the primary thing that
you're preparing for for the job search
right now?
>> I think definitely le coding will
probably always be a part of um software
engineering coding like interview
question styles. Um that's unfortunate,
but it's just like kind of like a must.
Um I think it's just like kind of like
the basic knowledge check of like can
you do like a basic coding problem,
right? Um even if it's like a tricky
problem, but um I think nowadays it's
more of like oh like I heard that like a
lot of times they'll give you like a
broken code system like kind of like a
fully developed thing but like they want
to see you how you fix it with using AI
like how are you prompting these AI
tools to fix your problem you know? Um,
so, so looking back at the layoff, um,
what was the company's like official
reason for the layoff and like now that
like uh it's it's over, do you think
there's a different real reason for it?
>> Yeah, I don't necessarily think I know
that like a lot of companies these days
they're um specifically the fang
companies or like any other big company.
I think that a lot of times they're
saying like oh like AI is the one reason
why we're replacing these jobs. But I
think it's more so like for Oracle case,
we had to like
>> invest so much money into like building
these data centers that are going to be
like pioneering for like OpenAI's
future, right? So they had so much debt
and so much like billions of dollars
that they had to make and the only way
they could like
>> get that money is to lay off lay off
people. So there was like this whole um
Oracle restructuring plan that was like
announced during like um during an all
hands meeting stuff like that where like
we're restructuring like Oracle to like
be so it like we save more money and
we're able to like you know be
profitable. So uh I definitely think
that like it was just more of like a
restructuring thing.
>> I see. And regarding the AI impact um
now that you're in the job market again
do you do you think that AI is replacing
engineers? Do you do you see like some
kind of roles getting cut or what kind
of roles are actually like growing with
with AI?
>> Yeah, I think that like um I don't think
that like AI will fully replace
engineers just because like with any
like LLM um there's going to be
hallucinations. There's going to be like
small errors, right? And you have to
have that expertise of like building
things in order to fix those and prompt
them to like be able to build them,
right? So I think that like AI is more
so like removing the redundancy of like
having engineers like maybe we don't
need 10 engineers for this project.
Maybe we only need five engineers, you
know, because when I was using these AI
tools at work, things that would take me
like maybe 5 days to do would only take
me like a day or two to do, right? Like
we're being more efficient as engineers.
So like I think it's more so like
removing you know how many engineers are
on a team and um I wouldn't say that
necessarily people are fully getting
replaced by AI. It's more of like we
want to keep some people but not
everyone.
>> Makes sense. And with your own career
planned, do you have like anything
that's different planned for yourself?
Like what types of companies are you
trying to switch into or what what kind
of field?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. For sure. I think
working at Oracle, specifically
Netswuite, um even just Oracle in
general, it's like a businessto business
company. It's strictly like me
personally, I don't like interact with
Oracle at all. Like even you, you don't
really know what Oracle is, right? Um I
think that's like the fact of life with
like any businessto business software
company, right? And I think that like
for me, I would definitely want to
prefer working at like a userfacing
company, right? when I build things in
Oracle and as I was like a software
engineer there, I didn't necessarily get
to see my product being like used on a
day-to-day basis, right? Versus like
let's say I worked at Door Dash, I could
see like, oh, maybe I got I got to
engrave this button, you know, like I
get to like see my feature actually
being implemented, right?
>> That's kind of like the area that I
would love to work in. Kind of like a
more fast-paced environment where I can
actually build things and see it being
used.
>> Yeah. And that's also how I feel about
like uh engineering jobs, too. I feel
like um I've worked in both like more
info spaces and more product spaces and
I think like with product you get to see
what you're building and you get to see
people using it. It feels you get the
sense of like accomplishment.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. For sure. You get a
sense of accomplishment.
>> Yeah. And also for like uh the engineers
that are in like probably Bay Area in in
big tech right now watching these
layoffs and are anxious. Do you have any
advice that you will say to them?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. For sure. I definitely
do think that like it is something to
worry about. Like not inevitable, but
like it might happen, but I wouldn't
like be too anxious about it. Like at
the end of the day, you can't control
it. Your managers can control it. It's
kind of like a higher org thing. Like
it's nothing you can really control. If
it happens, it happens. The only thing
that you can do is like kind of like
prepare yourself, right? Like
>> make sure you polish up that resume.
Make sure you like get everything ready
that you need before you might
potentially get laid off, right? don't
necessarily think that you're fully
secure because it might just happen to
anyone, right?
>> Um and I think that like you should
definitely um not be too anxious about
it if you can. Um try not to think about
it just because it's random and there's
no point in being anxious about it.
>> Yeah. And for the people that haven't
yet entered um the tech space um but are
thinking about it uh like what would you
say now? like do you think it's still
good to like join um big tech companies
or should people just pivot away from
CS?
>> Yeah, I think like if you definitely
have the drive and the grit to like do
CS and like you are passionate about it,
I definitely think it's the place to be,
right? Like just because you're afraid
of not being able to get a job, it's
like job insecurity, I don't necessarily
think that like you should pivot away
from it, right? Um, if you do think that
like, oh, you can get away with like
getting a decent job and like you don't
really you aren't passionate about it,
then probably go away from it. But like,
I don't think that you should be going
away from it just because the job market
is a little bit shaky right now.
>> And from the layoff to today, if you had
to say like one most valuable thing that
you learned, what would it be?
>> The most valuable thing that I learned
from after being laid off, kind of like
what I talked about earlier, right? Like
you want to have that plan for when you
get laid off. You want to have like that
security of like can you pay for things
when as soon as you get laid off like
there are things that like come up and
you might not be able to like handle it
with the money that you currently have
in your savings account, right? So you
want to make sure that you are able to
like fully support yourself.
>> And for the last last question for this
interview, um because our series is
called what's next? So always like at
the end of the video I ask this question
of like um what do you think what's next
for you like in the next year or um
couple years? Do you think there's
anything that you want to accomplish?
>> Mhm. Yeah. For I think what's next for
me is like definitely get a job. But I
think that like um besides getting a
job, I want to be able to do things that
I fully love and um kind of do things
that like make me more fulfilled and
more happy. Whether that be a job that
is like something I'm more like into or
like you know have fulfillment from. I
want to be able to do like side hustles
or side projects that I also think that
like I want to be able to like fully
create, right? So like for me like I
think I'm really into baking these days
and I feel like I always wanted to like
do a side hustle like opening like a
small bakery, right?
>> Oh, that's so cute.
>> Yeah. And then also like I think just
traveling a lot like when I was working
at Oracle I always did travel a lot. a
lot of my friends for like how do you
work so much but also travel at the same
time but I definitely think like paying
it forward like I want to be able to
take my mom to like travel the world
with me and like see these places that
she hasn't seen before so I definitely
think um those are like my goals in mind
for the next future.
>> Yeah,
>> makes sense. Yeah, thank you for sharing
so much about the stories. I think like
right now there definitely are a lot of
people that are curious about what's
happening in the bay and curious about
these layoffs. So yeah.
>> Yeah. Thank you for for sharing all
this.
>> Yeah, of course. Thank you for having
me.
>> And I'll see you guys in the next video.
Bye.
Next step.
Bye-bye.