we can actually be traditional finance.
>> This is one of the people quietly
rewriting how global finance works. Meet
Anatoly Yakovenko, one of the founders
of Solana. It's completely open finance.
See a full control over the entire
stack. This network processed over a
trillion dollars last year. It runs 24/7
and every line of code is open for
anyone to read. My dream is that it's
like Linux. And today, [music] he's
sharing his entire vision for where
markets are heading. Why the biggest
trading firms are now building on Solana
instead of competing against it. [music]
His bold prediction for the next 10
years. There's not going to be a
difference between DeFi and finance.
We'll just call it all finance. And what
every trader needs to understand right
now. Because in this game, the only
enemy left isn't a competitor. You are
fighting physics. And what what better
thing can you possibly work on?