Some of my students, in fact, what
happened was when the market went wave
up, wave down, wave up, wave down, wave
up, they said, "Hey Adam, you know, why
don't we sell here? You know, because,
you know, after wave up could be wave
down." And I said, "No, I'll just stay
invested. I've been doing this for many,
many years." And now it came down, they
said, "See, I told you so. I told you
should have sold there."
Now, the problem with thinking this way
is that once you have this belief that
after wave up I'm going to sell,
there'll be many instances in the future
and in the past that if you did that,
you would have missed the biggest runs
in the market. So, let me give you an
example, right? So, if you guys have
this fear that oh, every time the market
goes down, I'm going to get out, then
imagine the person here, right? It waves
up and it's going to go down. Oh my god,
it's going to go down. And they get out
here. What happens? They miss this big
run over there. Or it drops here, they
panic, they think it's going to go
lower, they sell, they miss that big
run. Go back further in history over
here, same thing, right? It goes up here
and then it drops, then they think, "Oh
my god, I'm going to get out after a
wave up." And they sell here and they
miss the big run. So, the reason I can
tell you that is because I used to do
this many, many years ago. Every time
the market waves up, I will anticipate a
wave down, so I will get out attempting
to buy it back lower. And I can tell you
that four out of five times after I get
out, it does come down, but before I can
get back in, it zooms back up and then
I'm left without having the stock. And
it goes up three, four, 500% and I'm
sucking my thumb with just a 30% return.
So, in the past I used to jump in, jump
out, jump in, jump out of great
companies and I made money along the
way, but I found that again, if I just
held on to the great companies through
the big ups and downs over the years,
you know, today I'll probably already be
a billionaire.