Last week, Anthropic officially became
the Apex Alpha company of the artificial
intelligence race with a valuation
exceeding OpenAI as they filed to go
public with their trillion dollar IPO
later this year. If you're a software
engineer, this comes as no surprise
because Claude has been the best AI
programmer for years now. But despite
the billions of dollars flowing into
this company right now, they also just
proposed something that sounds insane.
Maybe we should wait a second and pause
all AI development because AI is getting
dangerously close to recursive
self-improvement. And when that happens,
the last thing humanity ever builds is
the thing that realizes it doesn't need
humanity. Even if AI is benevolent and
doesn't go rogue and kill us all, a new
paper just dropped that believes all
rational firms will automate each other
into a death spiral anyway. It looks
like we're screwed no matter what we do.
But not everybody out there is a doomer.
And I found some compelling evidence
that AI might actually kind of suck. It
is June 9th, 2026, and you're watching
the code report. Anthropic's in-house
think tank just dropped a report, and
this is the thesis. AI is getting
dangerously close to recursive
self-improvement. In other words,
they're smart enough to rewrite their
code and upgrade themselves in a loop
with no humans necessary. The entire
industry is all gas and no breaks, and
they want everybody to come together and
hold hands and create a brake pedal. The
problem is that Anthropic can't pause
alone. While OpenAI, Deep Mind, and XAI
keep sprinting. So, unilateral pausing
is off the table. It's either everybody
or nobody. And that includes China, by
the way. And nobody's really worried
about the EU. However, a global pause is
a very convenient thing for the market
leader to advocate for. Because it
doesn't erase Anthropic's lead, it
freezes it right as they're about to
make billions of dollars with an IPO. If
all this sounds familiar, it's not
because you're crazy. It's because in
2019, OpenAI did the same thing before
the release of GPT2. At first, they said
it was too dangerous to release it, just
like Anthropic is doing right now with
Claude Mythos. But then they released
GPT2 and it was totally fine. That was 7
years ago, and now it looks like ancient
technology. Today, if we are to trust
these Trust Me Bro benchmarks, the
modern Claude models are far better at
research than humans. Like 64% of the
time, a Claude mythos is better than a
human every time. On top of that, AI
researchers are now solving problems
that humans haven't been able to. Like
OpenAI recently disproved a central
conjecture and discrete geometry, which
mathematicians have failed to do for the
last 80 years. The scary thing is that
we're already giving AI access to data
centers, robots, and weapons to blow
people up. And thanks to predictive
programming in Hollywood movies, we all
know how that story ends. It's either
enslavement like the Matrix or
extermination like Terminator. I'd
prefer the latter, but there's a
possibility for an even dumber outcome.
as predicted by economists from Boston
University in their paper, the AI layoff
trap. At this point, there's been tens
of thousands of layoffs in tech thanks
to AI. But these economists did some
math, and it doesn't look good. Because
when a firm automates away a worker with
AI, it pockets 100% of the savings. But
the laid-off worker is also a customer.
And their loss spending doesn't just
hurt the firm that fired them, it hurts
everyone selling anything. Demand goes
down. So the endgame is that firms
automate their way to infinite
productivity and zero demand. They also
argue that things like UBI and
upskilling aren't going to work and the
only solution is to put a tax on
automation. It kind of like the same way
we tax pollution, making it cost more to
fire people. So the math stops rewarding
the AI race. But if there's one thing
I've learned about economists, it's that
they're wrong pretty much every time. A
third possibility is that AI just isn't
nearly as good as people think and never
will be. This is the Wall-E situation
where we keep chasing more and more
automation and ultimately destroy the
planet by building more and more data
centers. One piece of evidence that
supports that outcome is that over the
last couple years with the rise of
Agentic AI, the number of new app
releases on the iOS app store is nearly
doubled. However, it appears nobody's
actually using these apps because app
reviews and apps with significant usage
are declining. In addition, this 2025
report from MIT analyzed over 300
enterprises implementing AI. And even
though they spent over $30 billion
collectively, the end result was that
95% of their projects delivered zero
measurable revenue impact or return on
investment. That doesn't look good. But
luckily, there are tools that can help
you avoid failure, like Pioneer, the
sponsor of today's video. If you're
calling a Frontier model for every LLM
request in your app, it's probably
burning through a bonfire of tokens just
to return generic results. But Pioneer
solves this by giving you an inference
API that you can plug into your existing
LLM setup to handle all model routing
and optimization for you. And it will
cluster your app's traffic by use case
to discover where your current model is
being too slow, too expensive, or too
stupid. Then it trains a fleet of
smaller open- source models in the
background and alerts you when it finds
one that's cheaper and better so you can
easily swap it under the hood. But
Pioneer works great with Claude Code,
Codeex, Cursor, Hermes, or anything else
hitting an LLM endpoint. And you can get
$30 of inference for just $5 today. But
this has been the code report. Thanks
for watching and I will see you in the
next one.