Again, SpaceX is targeting a 1.75 to 2
trillion valuation, but Amazon is
currently selling in the public markets
at about 2 trillion valuation. But look
at the mean difference, right? So
imagine if you had $2 right now,
would you buy SpaceX or would you buy
Amazon? Imagine you could buy the whole
company. If you buy SpaceX for $2, you'd
be getting 16 billion in revenue right
now. Of course, it could grow over time
and you're getting 8 billion in earnings
before taxation, depreciation, and
amortization. Or would you rather spend
your $2 buying Amazon, where right now
you're already getting 716 billion of
revenue existing, which again will grow
as well, as well as 146 billion in
current profits?
Right? So that's a question you have got
to ask yourself. So for Amazon, you can
see the price-to-sales ratio is three
times versus SpaceX 109 times.
Price-to-EBITDA for SpaceX, 218 times,
and for Amazon, the price-to-EBITDA is
16 times.