Hey everyone, it's Bree and we're back
with the Solana blockchain developer
roadmap. In this video, we'll learn how
to handle data on chain. We'll be
building out a CRUD app, which stands
for create, read, update, and delete,
which should cover all the basic logic
for storing and managing data on chain.
We'll get started by using the Anchor
CLI to build your workspace. [music]
Anchor is a framework for building
Solana smart contracts and that's what
we'll be using to build out our CRUD
app. [music] So, let's navigate over to
our terminal and we're just going to
type into the terminal. Actually, I'll
zoom in a bit so you can see better.
Okay. So, we'll type in anchor init and
that's going to initialize a workspace
for writing an Anchor smart contract.
So,
we'll name that CRUD app.
And you can see it's now initializing my
workspace for me.
And then we'll just CD into the
directory that it created.
And we'll open that code.
Okay.
So, I'll zoom in a bit and this is what
was created in your workspace. We're
going to go straight into the programs
directory, which is where your actual
smart contract is going to live. Now,
this generated a file structure that is
a little bit
overkill for just a CRUD app. Um, this
is best practices for when you have a
lot of instructions and a lot of code to
manage. Um, for simplicity, what I'm
going to do is just delete everything
besides the lib.rs file. And as we
progress through this roadmap and get to
more complex applications, you'll be
using all the files that were generated
here, but for now, we really just need
the lib.rs. We don't need to extract
this into several files because it's
just a short amount of code to be able
to create a CRUD app. Since we deleted
all of those files, we can delete the
mods here.
Okay.
And we can delete this. And now we're
left with just the basic outline of a
Solana program.
So, this is using the Anchor framework.
You can see that the Anchor link crate
has been imported into this file. This
declare ID section,
this is what is going to generate the
public key for your smart contract. So,
when you search a contract on chain,
it's going to be found by its public
key, which is this address right here.
So, this is generated when you run
Anchor build in your Anchor directory in
your terminal and it's going to generate
the public key and once it's deployed on
chain, that is going to be how you find
the smart contract on chain. I like to
think of it kind of like a key value
store, so the key is your public key and
then the value is all of the code for
your smart contract on the chain. So,
now I have this macro right here,
program. And that is part of Anchor and
what it's doing is it's handling your
entry point for the smart contract. So,
it's saying, "Hey, all of these
functions that live inside of this
program macro are going to be
instructions for your smart contract."
And it's going to create the entry point
for that smart contract. So, Anchor is
handling all of the complexities here
and really all you have to worry about
is writing your functions and defining
the logic within them.
So, you can see here we have this
initialize function already written for
you. We're going to be updating this to
be our create function for our CRUD app.
So, one example that I like to use for a
CRUD app is a journal. Um, a journal is
a good way where you want to create and
store data. Sometimes you want to update
it, sometimes you want to delete it. Um,
so each journal entry is going to be a
new data set that we're going to be
either storing, updating, or deleting on
chain.
Now, one thing to know with Solana smart
contracts, all smart contracts are
stateless. So, if you came from other
ecosystems like Ethereum or Cosmos,
you're probably used to having all of
your state stored in the smart contract
itself. On Solana, it's stored in
accounts. So, here we're going to be
generating data that needs to be stored
somewhere. And to do that, we're going
to have to create a new account on
chain. So,
when you're writing smart contracts on
Solana,
you always have to think of this account
model first. So, I always like to start
with what data I need and how I need to
store it. So, here let's start with
exactly that. I'm going to define a new
account that I need to create on chain
and we can do that by using the account
macro from Anchor. And all I'm going to
do is write out a data structure that's
going to hold all of my data that I need
for that account. So, I'll make this my
journal struct.
And let's see, if I'm writing a journal,
well, first I want to know that it's my
journal and it needs to be only
accessible to me. So, the first field
that I'm going to store here is who the
owner is and we can know that by the
public key. So, whenever you have your
wallet connected to the front end of the
application, we're going to be able to
pull that public key of your wallet and
use that to identify what data you can
access. So, we'll make this owner a
pubkey type. And if you're new to Rust,
um, think of it kind of like TypeScript.
Everything is type safe here, so every
field that you define, you're going to
have to define its corresponding type.
So,
now when I'm writing a journal, now I
know that it's mine, what else am I
going to want to store? Well, I think
I'll store the title and then I'll store
the message and that should cover
everything for my journal on a basic
sense. So, we'll add two more fields
here.
I'll do title
and that'll be a string type.
And then I'll do message.
And that'll also be a string type.
Okay, so that's pretty much all the data
that I want to store for my smart
contract.
Now, when you store data on chain, you
have to pay rent for that account.
Meaning, you're paying for how much
space you are taking up on chain to
store the data that you need to store.
So,
the amount that you pay for rent
corresponds to how much space you're
taking up. So, we have to calculate
that. Um, back when I first started
writing smart contracts on Solana, you
had to manually calculate this and it's
quite annoying. So, Anchor actually has
a macro now that automatically does it
for you. So, you can do that by adding
this derive init space macro.
Okay.
And when I do that, I'm going to get an
error and you can see that the error is
with these two fields that are string
types. And the reason we're getting an
error there is because a string can be
infinitely long, really. So, we need to
have a max length here to be able to
accurately calculate the space it's
going to take up on chain. So, I'm going
to add one constraint here that just has
the max length for each of these fields.
So, we'll set the first to 50.
And let's set the second to like 200.
Okay, now you can see that error went
away.
Now,
now we defined what our account is, but
we haven't actually created that account
yet. We've just defined what data that's
storing. So, we're going to actually
create the account with this initialize
function.
We'll update the name to create.
And then
the first parameter that's passed
through an instruction in an Anchor
smart contract is always going to be
your context. So, this context is
actually a data structure of all the
accounts that need to be passed through
the instruction to accurately execute
the logic. So, we're going to need to
create a data structure that holds all
of the accounts and then defines what
actions need to be done on each account
for this instruction. So, it'll make a
little bit more sense as we actually
write it out. So, let's update this to
create.
And we'll go down here to create our
struct for that.
So, here we're going to use the derive
accounts macro from Anchor.
Um,
this may seem like a lot in the
beginning, but it does get very
repetitive. So, the more you do this,
it'll start to stick.
Okay.
So, we'll do derive accounts and we'll
define this.
Now, for here, we'll be using a lifetime
specifier and that's really just
a Rust thing that says, "Hey, I need to
make sure that all of these variables
stay alive throughout the entire
lifetime of this instruction." Now, we
just need to define every account that
needs to be passed through in our create
instruction. So, the first one, pretty
obvious, is we're creating a journal
account. So, that's going to be an
account that we're going to have to pass
through.
We can define each account with this
account macro. And then whatever actions
need to be done with this account, we
can define within a constraint on that
account, which I'll show you what that
is in just 1 second. But first, let's
write the account. So, this will be my
journal.
And it's going to be an account type
with our lifetime specifier.
And it's going to contain the type of
this data structure down here.
Okay.
So,
now we defined the account that we have
to pass through, but this account, it
hasn't been created yet. So, the way
that we're going to create this account
is just by using the init constraint on
the account.
So, now whenever we initialize an
account,
we're going to have to have a payer
because that payer is going to be paying
the rent to have the account on chain.
So, we have to define that whenever
we're initializing. Now, who is that
payer going to be? Well, it's going to
be the owner of the journal because
that's who is going to be signing the
instruction to create the account. So,
the owner is actually going to be
another account that we're going to have
to pass through.
So, we can define that here.
And the owner will be a signer type
because that is who is signing the
instruction.
Okay.
So, now I can define the payer as my
owner.
And since I'm initializing, I have to
calculate how much space this account is
going to take up on chain. So, to do
that
I can define the discriminator.
And then I can define the discriminator.
So, we're going to use eight, which is
just the basic discriminator for Anchor.
Um with this new Anchor version, you can
customize your discriminator for more
efficiency, but since we're just going
over
how to make a crowd app at a base level,
um we're just going to stick with
eight as our discriminator, and then
we're going to add in the init space
calculation. Um which we can do
by typing in our struct down here.
And then init space.
Okay.
So, that will auto calculate the space
for us since we used this derive init
space macro when we defined our journal
struct.
Okay.
Now that that's done,
um
I'm going to want to create my journal
as a PDA. They're going to define the
account and be able to generate the
account address. So,
first I'll define what the seeds are.
Now,
whenever you create an account that has
a PDA, um you can optimize how you use
that PDA. So, here I'm going to be
defining
my title and my owner as the seeds for
the PDA. If I let's say I defined my PDA
as just the owner, and that was the only
value I use as a seeds. Well, if that
was the case, then my wallet could only
have one account. So, I could only make
one journal entry for my journal because
I have one wallet. So, putting the same
input value in is going to generate the
same PDA out. So, here I'm going to also
define the title of my journal entry as
part of the PDA generation. Now,
this does kind of cause some confusion
cuz now I can only have that title used
once. Um so, there's further
optimizations that you can do here with
your PDA, but at a baseline this works.
So, we're going to stick to this for
now.
Now, the concept of a PDA um is pretty
confusing in the beginning. So, I do
have a video just explaining what PDAs
are, which I'll link here. And then as
you start to write more smart contracts,
you'll start to see ways to use PDAs to
optimize your programs. Um it just comes
with time. But for now, we're just going
to understand that it's a seed and a
bump to generate your PDA.
So, my input values for my seed are the
title
and the owner.
And this will be the key. So, it'll be
the public key of my wallet that's
connected to the front end.
Now, every time I define my seeds, I
also have to define the bump.
If you're still confused on what a bump
is, check out the PDA explanation video
that I linked here.
Um
Okay. Now that that's done,
I have my signer. Now, there's one
constraint I'm going to have to add to
this account, and that's mute.
So, in Rust, all variables are immutable
by default. So, if any part of your
state is going to be changing in the
instruction logic, you have to mark that
account as mutable. So,
since the owner is going to have the
account balance change to pay rent,
we're going to have to mark the signer
here as mutable.
Okay.
And then the last account that we have
to pass through is our system program.
So, anytime we're creating a new
account, we're going to have to pass
through the system program.
Okay. And sorry, I had a typo here. It's
actually accounts with an S, not just
account. So, we're going to fix that and
then get our errors to go away.
Okay. So, now that our errors are gone,
actually a new error was just generated.
And the reason why is because
in this struct, it doesn't know what a
title is. So, you can see here it's able
to access the owner field because we're
passing through the owner account down
here as an account. So, it can access
that. But title, it doesn't know what
that is. The title is actually going to
be a user input value coming from that
create instruction. So, let's go up here
and define
everything that the user is going to
have to input on the front end of our
application. So, the first is going to
be the title.
And then the second is going to be the
message.
Now, I can use another macro down here
to say, "Hey, you're going to find what
this title value is from the
corresponding instruction." So,
if I just do
instruction
and then I type in title,
now it knows to pull the title field
from the
instruction up here. So, now the error
went away.
Okay.
Now, I'm just going to remove that
handler field because that came from our
scaffold. Um we don't need that. We're
going to write our own logic here.
So,
now that we've finished our derive
account struct that has all of the
accounts that are going to be passed
through and how they need to be updated,
now we just finish the logic in our
actual create function.
>> [snorts]
>> So,
all we're doing here is just saving
title and message and owner into the
field of our new
journal entry account that's being
created on chain.
So,
we can easily do that by loading in the
context. So, we'll do let journal.
And we're going to take a mutable
reference
to our account. And the reason it has to
be mutable is because we're now changing
the data that exists with in that
account. So,
we're adding the title, the message, and
the owner into the account state.
So, we can load that in by calling
ctx.accounts.
And then I'm going to call journal
entry.
Okay.
Now, all I do is just update that state.
So, we can do journal entry
dot
owner.
And that is going to be equal to
And that's going to be equal to the
signer, which is being passed through
our account struct. So, we can just call
ctx again
dot accounts
dot
owner.
And then we just want to take the public
key of that to save.
Okay.
Now, we'll also update the title and the
message field, which is going to just be
setting the title equal to the title.
And then the message equal to the
message.
And then the last thing we have to do is
just return our okay.
And we're good to go.
So, that was our first instruction for
our crowd app.
Now that we got that done, um the rest
of the instructions are going to fly by
because a lot of this is repetitive, so
we can do a lot of copy and pasting now,
which makes everything a lot easier. So,
we finished create. Read actually
happens from our RPCs. We're going to
read directly from the blockchain. So,
we don't have to create a read function
here. So, we can skip that. The next
thing we're going to do is update. So,
how can we update
data that already exists on chain in an
account? That's going to be our next
instruction.
>> [clears throat]
>> So, I'll copy our create instruction
and paste it.
And we'll rename this to update.
Okay.
And then I'm going to again copy our
derive account struct, and I'll rename
this to update.
Okay.
So, let's talk about what's going to
change here. So, I already initialized
the account, so I don't need this
constraint anymore.
But a constraint that I do need is mute
because I now need this account to be
mutable so I can change the state that
exists within the account.
Whenever I'm handling an account that's
a PDA, I'm always going to have to pass
through the seeds and the bump because
it needs to be able to know how to
generate the PDA address. So, that is
going to stay the same as well.
Now,
because I'm not creating a new account,
I don't need the payer. But I do kind of
need a payer. You'll see in a second.
But I can delete that.
And I also don't need the space because
I'm again not creating a new account.
However, if I do change the fields,
let's say my first message was just one
word, and then I updated it to have a
thousand words in my message. Well, now
I'm going to have to pay for that
additional space that I'm now taking up
on chain.
So,
we're going to use this constraint
called realloc.
And what that's doing is reallocating
the space for our account.
So, the first thing I'm going to do is
calculate my space.
And then once I've calculated it,
I'm going to define who the payer is.
So,
in this case, I'm either going to be
paying additional rent for the
additional space I'm taking up, or I'm
going to be refunded rent because now
I'm taking up less space on chain.
So, that again is going to be the
signer, which is the owner.
And then the last thing I'm going to do
is set realloc to
Sorry. Realloc zero to true. And what
that means is
the previous space that was being taken
up, it's going to zero that out before
recalculating the space. So, what that
means is the previous space that was
being taken up, it's going to zero that
out before recalculating the space up
here. Okay. So, now that's good to go.
Our signer is going to stay the same,
and then the system program will stay
the same. So, now we'll go back up to
the logic. Well, I'm still going to load
in my journal entry. However,
I want to make sure my journal says
private to me, and no one else can
access it, and I can't change ownership.
So, I'm not going to allow anyone to be
able to update the owner. So, I'm not
going to change that.
Now, the title is part of the PDA. So,
we're not going to allow for updates for
that, either. We're just going to allow
for updates for the message. So, the
only field that is going to be updated
here is the message.
Now, when I deleted title, you get this
error here. It's actually not an error,
it's a warning. Um but, this is coming
from my Rust analyzer.
Um if you're following along and don't
get these same errors that are being
generated, I do have Rust analyzer down
here as an add-on in my VS Code, so get
that added, um and then you'll be able
to follow along with the same error
messages that I'm getting.
Um but, you can see this warning here.
And that's because I'm passing through a
parameter in my instruction, but I'm not
actually using it anywhere in the logic.
And this is going to happen sometimes
when you're writing Solana smart
contracts, because you still do
technically need this title field, and
I'm going [clears throat] to have to
continue to pass it through the
instructions parameters,
because I'm using it to calculate my
PDA down here.
So, the way we're going to get rid of
this warning is just add a little
underscore here. And that's basically
telling Rust, like, "Hey, I know I'm not
actually using it in the logic of this
instruction, but I do still need to
gather that information for something
else."
Okay.
So, now
quick and easy, we already finished
create, read, and update. The last one
we have is delete, and that's going to
complete out our CRUD app. So,
let's copy one more time the same
layout.
And I'm going to copy again my derived
accounts.
Now, we'll rename this to delete.
Okay. So, now I'm going to update my
delete struct. So, we still need to keep
it mutable, because the account is going
to be changing, it's going to be
deleted. Now, we also still need the
seeds in the bump, because it is a PDA,
and we have to calculate that PDA.
We don't need realloc, because we're not
reallocating anything.
And then, to delete an account on chain,
you can just simply use the close
constraint for Anchor. Now, I'm going to
set close equal to a signer. So, this is
adding additional permissions by only
allowing a specific account to be able
to close that account. So, I want the
owner of this journal entry to be the
only person that's allowed to delete
their own journal entry. So, we want to
make sure that the signer of this
instruction
is the same as the owner of this
account.
So,
we'll set that to owner.
Okay.
And then, owner and system program will
stay the same.
And then, because all we're doing in
this instruction is deleting the account
itself, and the deletion of the account
is actually handled right here in this
constraint on my journal entry account
macro,
I actually don't need anything in this
function. I can just make the function
return an okay.
And because I'm not using any of this
information,
I can just add an underscore here,
and then we're good to go. So, this is
all the code that you need to have a
fully functioning CRUD app on Solana.
So, my camera stopped recording, and I
have now spawned to a new office, and
we'll finish this project here. But,
don't worry, I promise we're almost
done. We finished writing out all of our
smart contract code already, so all we
have left is to build and deploy the
program. So, we can actually do this
very easily using the Anchor CLI. I'm
going to open up my terminal, and then
navigate to the CRUD app directory, and
all I'm going to do is run Anchor build.
And this command is taking all of our
Rust code and compiling it. So, mine
compiled really quickly, because I
actually already compiled this program
earlier. Yours is going to take a little
bit longer. And then, once everything is
compiled, you're going to have this
target directory generated. And then, if
you go into the deploy folder, there is
this CRUD app.so file. This is what was
compiled, and what is going to actually
be deployed onto the Solana blockchain.
>> [snorts]
>> So, now that we have this file, we can
again use the Anchor CLI and deploy it
on chain. So, to deploy, all you have to
do is run Anchor
program deploy,
and then specify which cluster you want
to deploy to. So, we're going to be
deploying to devnet. So, I'm going to
add a flag that says provider.cluster
is devnet.
Now, before you run this,
you do have to have your local keypair
set up in your CLI and have it funded.
If you don't, I have that in the setup
video, but I can also go over it really
quickly after I enter this command.
So, here you can see it's deploying my
program.
I actually already deployed this
earlier, so it says program already
exists, but it's upgrading. If I had any
code changes when I recompiled the
program, it would upgrade the file
that's on chain to this new file. So,
this program ID field is the ID for the
program that you just deployed, and
we'll be able to query that on chain.
So, if this didn't work,
I want you to check to make sure that
you have a local keypair set up in your
CLI. So, if you type in Solana address,
it's going to return your public key of
that wallet.
If it returns an error, it's also going
to return a CLI command to run to
generate a new
wallet for you. So, you can just copy
and paste that, run it in your terminal,
it's going to return your new public key
for that wallet, as well as the seed
phrase. So, save that somewhere.
And then, once you have that, all you
have to do is airdrop some devnet SOL to
yourself. So, if I copy this, and I go
over to faucet.solana.com,
I can paste in my wallet address and
choose how much SOL I want to airdrop to
myself, and then airdrop it. I've
already airdropped the maximum amount of
SOL for the day to my wallet, so I can't
actually show you, but all you do is
click this button, and then
you'll be good to go, you'll be able to
deploy.
And then, after that, the last thing I
want to do is show you how to
verify that this was deployed on chain.
So, if I copy the program ID,
and I go back over to my explorer,
>> [snorts]
>> update the cluster to devnet, and then I
paste in that program ID, it's going to
be able to look up my program. So, think
of it like a key-value pair. Your value
is that .so file that you deployed, and
the key is your program ID. So, [snorts]
I'm just going to search this, and now
you can see there's a program account,
and here was when I originally deployed
it on chain 15 minutes ago, uh when I
first tried to record this video, and
then
3 minutes ago, when I just executed the
last deployment for upgrading this
program.
And there you go. So,
>> [music]
>> we've learned how to handle data on
chain and build and deploy your program
to Solana devnet. Up next, we're going
to be learning about tokens, and then
how to handle those in Solana programs.
[music] So, check that out next.