Ubuntu, SUSE, Amazon Linux, and Red Hat
walked into a bar that only Linux
distros can get into. And they sat
around talking about the bulletproof
kernel code they all shared, but then
out of nowhere, a 732-byte Python script
penetrated the back door and beat them
all to death with a baseball bat. Last
week, a 100% reliable logic flaw was
discovered in the heart of the Linux
kernel. It had been sitting there
quietly since 2017 until an AI scanning
tool surfaced the issue, wrote an
exploit, and even designed a fancy
website for it. And it affects basically
every Linux machine on planet Earth, or
at least every machine updated since
2017. That means if you run a Linux
server, or you're one of the top 3% of
absolute units who run Linux on desktop,
you need to update your stuff like
yesterday. Any script kitty who watched
this video I made a few weeks ago, it
can easily take control of your machine
with tools like Metasploit. It's no
joke. CrowdStrike has already confirmed
that attackers are using this script in
the wild, and CISA has already put it on
the notorious Kev list of known
exploited vulnerabilities. In today's
video, we'll look at the technical
details behind copy-fail,
CVE-2026-31431, and find out why Linux
sucks and you should only ever use
Microsoft
Windows. It is May 4th, 2026, and you're
watching The Code Report. Personally, I
love Linux, but my private equity
Illuminati handlers want me to tell you
it sucks in order to control the
narrative and sell more copies of
Windows. What's kind of crazy though is
that the going rate for a universal
Linux privilege escalation on the gray
market is somewhere between 10,000 and 7
million US dollars. And that's based on
Crowd Fund's bounty pricing. But a few
days ago, an AI agent found one in about
an hour of scan time, and Theory, the
company behind this AI-powered hacker,
dropped the proof of concept on the
public internet for free. The exploit
targets the Linux kernel directly, and
it's such a big deal they gave it its
own fancy website. At first, people were
skeptical that it was just some
overblown AI slop, but it was later
confirmed by the Linux kernel team and
was traced back to a few normal-looking
commits from 2015 and 2017. But the
scariest thing is that every Linux
distro is affected. Debian, Arch, Red
Hat, you name it. If it has kernel code
after 2017, it needs to be updated right
now. But now let's find out how it
actually works. Well, to understand it,
let's take a look at the raw exploit
code in this tiny Python script. What
this code can do is allow an
unprivileged local user to write four
uncontrolled bytes into the page cache
of any readable file on a Linux system
and use it to gain root access. What
you'll notice is that the code relies on
something in Linux called auth ink ESN,
which means authentication encryption
extended sequence numbers. We don't need
to understand what this thing does, but
the important part is that it lives
behind Linux's AF_ALG
interface, which exposes kernel crypto
algorithms to user space. But auth ink
ESN has this weird internal behavior
where it writes four bytes of scratch
data into what it thinks is a crypto
output buffer. But because of a bug in
the AF_ALG splice function, that output
buffer can accidentally point into the
page cache of a read-only file. Like in
this Python script, it points to the
read-only SU file. And that's really bad
because SU is on every Linux distro and
allows you to run a command as a root
user. The good news though is that copy
fail is not remotely exploitable, which
means to run it, you would have to be a
regular user on a Linux machine or the
attacker would have to gain a foothold
on the system through SSH or some other
compromised application. That means your
Arch-based laptop is probably safe, but
it'd still be a good idea to patch it
anyway. What's crazier than the exploit
itself though is how it was discovered.
Like I mentioned, it was discovered by
an AI agent and basically they just gave
it a prompt that said splice can deliver
page cache references of read-only files
to crypto TX scatter lists, go look. And
it only took 1 hour of scan time to
completely borg every Linux machine on
planet Earth. These AI hackers are
teaching us that now more than ever our
AI coding agents need to be writing the
best quality Slack possible. And one
tool that can help you do that is Code
Rabbit, the sponsor of today's video.
They just launched a Code Rabbit agent
for Slack, which gives your team an
agent for managing your entire
development workflow right inside your
Slack channels. You start by connecting
your team's tools like GitHub and
Sentry, then bundle them into a scope to
provide operating context for your
agent. Then you can @mention Code Rabbit
in any Slack channel whenever something
comes up, and it'll pull the relevant
traces to find the issue, open a pull
request with the fix, and notify you
when it's finished without you ever
needing to leave Slack. It also adds
every decision and pull request to your
team's knowledge base, and so the agent
can get smarter about your team's
workflow over time. You try it out for
free at the link below, and you'll get
an extra $50 in free credits. This has
been the Code Report. Thanks for
watching, and I will see you in the next
one.