Hey everyone, it's Bree and in this
video we're going to talk about how you
can monetize an API. So, most APIs need
the same things before they can charge
money like authentication, accounts,
billing, metering, payment collection,
and usage enforcement. But, Pay is a new
tool that gives you a whole different
model. Instead of building a full
billing system first, your API can just
return a standard 402 payment required
[music] and Pay handles the payment
challenge, verification, and retry flow.
So, let's see what that looks like. By
the end of this video, you'll have a
local Pay gateway that returns a 402
payment required [music] for metered
endpoints, verifies payment, and
forwards the request. Now, one thing to
note, Pay does have two sides. [music]
One is for consumers to use Pay curl,
Pay cloud, or Pay codex to access paid
APIs.
>> [music]
>> And then, the other is for providers to
use the Pay server to run a payment
gateway in front of their own API. In
this tutorial, we're focused just on the
provider side. So, if you're also
interested in the consumer side, I'll
link a separate video [music] in the
description. Now, let's get started with
this demo.
So, I already have the Pay CLI installed
on my machine. If you don't, you can
just install it with brew install Pay
and I will link the GitHub in the
description of this video. But, once you
have the CLI installed, you can start
out with just building out your config
for the endpoints. And the Pay CLI
actually has a scaffold to help you out
with this. So, I'm in a temporary
directory. I'm going to type in Pay
So, Pay server scaffold and that is
going to generate a file for my server.
And you can see it created it. And I'm
just going to open that so you can see
what it looks like.
Here is the scaffold. Now, I have my own
config that I created for this video.
So, I'm just going to update this to
exactly what I want with the specific
endpoints that I want.
Okay.
So, this file, it's essentially the
contract for the gateway.
You can see here there's a health
endpoint, and that's free because it
doesn't have a metering block. But then,
if you look down here, you can see V1
report.
>> [snorts]
>> That's a paid endpoint because it has a
price, and here's the price to be able
to call that endpoint.
And anything that's not listed here is
blocked with 404. So, this is important
because this file basically acts as an
allow list as well.
Now, once you have this file, you're
going to be able to start the gateway.
So, we'll go back to our terminal, and
I'm going to run pay server start, and
I'm going to point that to the file that
we just created.
And I want to run this locally, so I
specified the bind flag for that.
Okay. And now, once I run that command,
you can see that we now have a server
running.
And I'm going to open up a new tab here,
and now we can actually test out these
endpoints. So, the first thing I'm going
to test out is the health endpoint. So,
now that the server's running, we can
actually test out these endpoints, and
I'm just going to split my screen here
so you can see the config while we are
making these API calls. So, the first
thing we're going to do is call a free
endpoint just how you regularly would
with curl. So, I'm going to call this
free health
>> [snorts]
>> endpoint.
And you can see that it returned an okay
here.
So, that worked. Server's running,
endpoint's accessible. Now, let's test
out calling the health endpoint, which
is payment gated, and we're going to do
that first with a curl command,
um just how you normally would call an
endpoint here.
You can see we get an error. So, if we
scroll up, you see 402 payment required.
And now you can see this endpoint is
accessible, however, it aired out
because it is gated with a payment and
we were not able to complete that
payment.
And you can also see here that the
response includes the payment challenge
that the client needs to satisfy. So, it
hasn't been completed yet. Now, let's
try out the same exact thing, but we're
going to be using pay.
So, I'll paste in the command for pay
here, making that same API call. And one
thing that I forgot to point out
earlier, we are using the sandbox flag
when we make these calls. And the reason
is when we're working in sandbox mode,
this uses a local net style of test
funds through the sandbox. So, we don't
have to be using any mainnet funds to be
able to test things out or demo it.
Okay.
>> [clears throat]
>> Now, I'll run that.
Again, this is the same endpoint we
tried to hit earlier that returned a 402
payment required. And here we ran the
same thing with pay. And you can see
that it returned a status okay and it
was able to complete our request.
So, what's happening here is pay reads
the challenge, it creates the payment
proof, retries the request, and then the
gateway verifies it before returning the
response. Okay. So, that was like a
high-level overview um of just how pay
works. One other feature that I do want
to show is that
you can have a split endpoint. So, let's
add recipients and have a split endpoint
here.
Now, this is where pay becomes more than
just a simple paywall. The paywall can
include split rules. So, one API call
can distribute revenue across the API
operator, partners, affiliates,
processors, and other recipients.
Now, let's test out this and make sure
that it works.
So, I'm just going to clear out my
terminal and
let's talk about another feature with
pay. And that is the proxy mode. So, so
far, if you go into this file, you can
see for our routing, the only type that
we've used is respond. And this is
perfect for demos. But in production, a
lot of providers would want their
routing type to be proxy. So, then they
can forward pay requests to an upstream
API. So, if we update the file, this is
what it would look like to have a proxy
type routing. And the gateway keeps your
upstream API
So, [snorts] the pay gateway,
the gateway verifies the payment, and
then it injects the upstream credential
and forwards the request. So, the
customer never receives your provider
API key. And then another feature that I
want to go over is if your upstream has
an open API or Google discovery
document, pay can serve a filtered
version of the open AI JSON file.
So, that would work with this command.
You're going to start your server with
an open API JSON.
And the important detail here is that
pay filters the open API document, so it
only the endpoints that are listed. So,
all of your endpoints that are listed in
this file, it's going to filter to only
access those. So, this means that agents
discover the paid surface that you
actually want to expose and not your
entire upstream API.
And once the gateway works, you can
publish a provider listing to the pay
skills registry. And that's what lets
pay skills search Claude and Codex
discover your API without having to
guess URLs. Now, that's everything that
I wanted to go over for the provider
side of pay. You define your routes,
prices, and routing rules, and then pay
turns those routes into an HTTP 402 paid
endpoints. So, the clients and the
agents use pay to satisfy the challenge,
and the gateway verifies the payment
before delivering the API response.
>> [music]
>> So, for API providers, this is the way
to start monetizing endpoints directly
without having to build [music] a
traditional billing stack first.
Check out the Pay repo in the
description of this video,
>> [music]
>> and to check out the consumer side of
Pay, check out the other video that's
linked in the description. Thanks,
everyone.