My other hero that I've emulated for so
many years of course Peter Lynch. He's
been retired for many many years, but
he's known as the greatest fund manager
of all time. So during his stint as a
fund manager of Magellan fund, this was
for 13 years, he grew the fund 604%
versus the S&P 500 of 223%.
His compounded annual growth rate was
29% a year. Now again, does that mean
that his portfolio went up 29% exactly
every single year? No. Does it mean he
went up in a straight line? No. In fact,
his portfolio had drawdowns every single
year. And every time the S&P 500
dropped, his portfolio would drop a lot
more than the S&P 500. So for example,
you can see major drawdown 56%
here, and then 27% here, 42% here, 32%
here. So again, his drawdowns were
bigger than the S&P 500. Why?
Because you find that to be a great
investor, you've got to be a contrarian.
You have to buy things that no one dares
to buy. That's how you get in when
they're very undervalued. And the
problem is that when you are a
contrarian and you buy things that are
very undervalued,
it's normally on a downtrend. And
normally on a downtrend, even though
it's cheap, cheap can get even cheaper
in the short term. And that's why many
of these great investors, in the short
term, they may drop even more than the
market, but that's the price they pay to
buy undervalued. That's the price they
pay for being a contrarian. But by doing
that, it sets them to way outperform and
beat the market over the long run.