A lot of people don't know this, but
Alphabet is kind of like the Berkshire
Hathaway of the tech world. So, many of
the great tech companies are actually
owned by Alphabet, both the public
companies and the private companies. So,
in fact, in their private venture
portfolio, you can see that Alphabet
owns
a 7% of SpaceX, which they initially
invested $900 million in 2015. And now,
the current valuation before IPO is 87
to 140 billion dollars. So, again, this
is not factored into Alphabet's share
price. When you buy Alphabet, you're
actually getting this for free. You're
getting 7% of SpaceX for free in that
way. Oh, by the way, as you know,
Anthropic is now becoming one of the
most popular frontier AI models, and
Alphabet owns 14% of Anthropic as well,
which, of course, runs the Claude LLM
that's creating havoc in the SaaS
enterprise software world. Alphabet also
owns Stripe, and they also own Waymo,
which is the leading autonomous driving
provider in the world right now, which,
of course, Tesla is trying to catch up.
Alphabet also owns AST Space Mobile and
Planet Labs, which are other dominant
players in the space economy.