Pay is a new developer tool on Solana
that turns HTTP 402 into a wallet
approved API. It's a payment layer that
lets CLIs and AI agents access paid APIs
without juggling API keys. So, when an
API returns a 402 payment required, Pay
detects a payment protocol, prepares a
stablecoin payment, asks for a local
wallet approval, and then retries the
request automatically. In this video,
I'll show you the difference between a
normal curl request that gets blocked
and a Pay powered request that completes
successfully. Then, I'll show the
payment debugger to get a full
challenge, payment, and response flow in
real time.
And finally, I'll show how this works
for developers who are building with
paid APIs and agents using tools like
Codex or Claude. So, let's get started.
So, we're just going to start with the
installation and setup. Here, you can
see the GitHub repo for Pay, which I
will link in the description of this
video. If we scroll down in the readme,
you can see the installation section.
We're going to use brew. You can also
build from source if you would prefer.
And I'm just going to brew install Pay.
Once that's set up, I'm going to check
the version to make sure it's installed
correctly.
And we're good to go. So, up next is
just setting up Pay. And when you do
that, you can just follow the setup
instructions here. So, do I want to
install Pay for my skills? I'm going to
do that. So, now when I'm using Claude,
it's going to know about Pay and be able
to use it when answering my questions or
working with any code base that I have.
And now, the next question is how should
you store your accounts? I'm going to
use the Touch ID in my keychain, so I'm
just going to verify that.
And then, we're good to go.
Then next, it's going to prompt you to
top up the wallet. So, this is the
wallet that Pay is going to be using to
make any payments needed. You can see
here it says QR code unavailable. If I
just expand it, it's going to show up. I
just have my terminal shrunk a bit, but
this gives you the QR code that you can
scan from your mobile wallet and then
send funds directly to this wallet that
Pay is using. And that is going to allow
it to make on-chain payments. And once
that's done, I already have my wallet
funded, so I'm going to skip that.
Now, we're all set up and we can start
actually using Pay. So, first I'm going
to spin up a demo server so I can demo
on local. And you can actually do this
directly with the Pay CLI.
So, I'll just call Pay server demo and
specify the bind, and this is now going
to run our demo server. Now, this server
was set up so that all of the local
endpoints here are payment gated. So,
let's see what endpoints are available
and then we can test them out.
So, let's use this first endpoint here
that's returned, which is for the usage
report. And let's first test it out just
running a curl command. So, this is how
you would normally call an API endpoint.
So, we're going to scroll up and you see
this error here that says 402 payment
required. So, this is what a normal
client sees. The API is reachable, but
the resource is gated. So, the server
responds with a 402 payment required
error. And that's the part that Pay is
actually designed to handle. So, let's
test this out again using Pay. And I'm
going to call the same command, but
we're going to wrap that in the Pay CLI.
So, if we have Pay, curl, and then the
same local API we're going to be
calling.
And here you can see the API was
successfully called. It returned the
usage report and a okay status. Now,
here I'm making the same request through
pay and pay reads the payment challenge,
builds the payment proof, signs it with
the local wallet, and then retries the
request. But, from the user's
perspective, it feels like you're just
running a normal curl command, but the
payment handshake actually happens
automatically here.
Now, let's see what pay looks like in a
UI with a debugger. So, it's a little
bit easier to conceptually understand
when we're looking at the UI and able to
analyze the debugger. I'm going to open
up that site here in my browser, and I'm
just going to execute a payment gated
API request one more time. Here, I'm
going to use this gated endpoint that is
shown on the payments debugger UI. So,
let me just copy this and then paste it
in my terminal.
And now you can see what's happening in
real time.
Okay. So, you can see the resource was
delivered. I'm going to expand my
browser so you can see everything. We'll
zoom in a bit. So, this debugger, it's
one of the best ways to understand
what's actually happening behind the
hood with pay.
It groups the raw HTTP request into a
single payment flow. So, instead of
staring at headers, so now I'm going to
show basically the same thing, but just
all of these different ways to do it so
you can see the full process from
different perspectives. If I go back to
the server that I'm running, I'm going
to click onto this request. And now you
can see a UI that comes up with it. And
this is now pay, but pay running in a UI
with a clickable button. So, if I adjust
click on the continuous Solana button,
it will now execute my payment and
return an okay status. So, here's
multiple ways to have your payments be
executed with the pay CLI. Now, I'm
going to show one more way to use pay
for payments. And
that is directly with your Cloud Code.
So, if I type in pay Cloud,
it's now going to open up my Cloud Code,
and I can interact with Cloud Code, and
it's going to be using pay. So, let me
ask it a question that's going to need
an API request that does require a
payment. So, we can use the Google API.
I can ask it,
"What are the What
is the best
restaurant in Philly
for Italian food?"
So, here you can see it returned some
response. It says, "It can get an
updated list with current hours, current
reservations, and reviews using a live
search via pay." And it's able to do a
live search by calling the Google API
endpoint, which is payment gated, so
it's going to be able to use pay, so
then make that payment for the API
request, and then make a live search
directly in my Cloud Code terminal. So,
let me say, "Yes, do a live
search with pay."
So, here you can see it's using the
Google Places API. It costs $0.001
for a text search. And now, my wallet
has not been funded yet on mainnet. Um
for all of the other requests, we were
using local, which does automatically
fund your wallet with devnet sold to be
able to execute the request. And this is
actually a mainnet call. So, it's now
prompting me to top up my wallet, and
it's giving me the wallet address that I
need to send funds to and then telling
me how to send those funds. So, if I
update that with the funds, it's going
to be able to execute a request for me.
So, now I went and funded my wallet and
it has USDC on it now. So, I'm going to
go one more time back into Claude. So,
if we do pay Claude,
it's going to open my Claude code and
I'm going to ask one more time
So, here you can see it found the API
request that was needed to search for
the top Italian restaurants in
Philadelphia with up-to-date live
information. And that one call was
$0.001
and it took the wallet that I just
funded and made that payment, but before
actually executing that payment, it came
up on screen with a pop-up that I had to
approve it and I had to use my touch ID
on my Mac to be able to approve that
request. And once I approved the
request, it made the request and then
returned all of this information.
So, just a recap of everything we went
over today. Pay is basically the missing
payment layer for HTTP. Instead of every
paid API needing its own account system,
API key flow, dashboard, and billing
setup, the server can return a standard
402 challenge. So, Pay understands
protocols like MPP and X402, pays with
the supported stablecoins on Solana, and
then sends the proof back to the API.
And the important part is that this
works with tools developers already use.
So you can wrap curl, cloud, codex, or
any agent workflow. And the API gets
paid, the user stays in control, and the
agent doesn't need to hold private keys
or API secrets.