So, this is my portfolio for the last 7
years from January 2019 to January of
this year. And you can see that my
portfolio in blue gained a total of 267%
versus the S&P 500, which is in green,
that gained 175%. But again, you can see
along the journey there were quite a
number of drawdowns. So, for example, in
2020, during the COVID pandemic, in the
bear market, my portfolio dropped 36%.
In fact, my portfolio dropped slightly
even more than the S&P 500. And then in
2022, when we had the bear market, as
the Fed raised interest rates
aggressively, my portfolio dropped 26%.
And then more recently in 2015, last
year, when Trump came out and imposed
tariffs on the whole world, is the
liberation day. Market panic, right? And
my portfolio went down 19% as well,
okay? So, having double-digit drops in
your portfolio, it's not uncommon, even
if you're holding very, very good
companies
like me, okay? It will happen, yeah?