Now, again, if you look at the S&P 500,
you can see that the drawdown is
actually about 9%. So, why is my
portfolio down more than 9%? The reason
is very simple. It's because you don't
own any energy stocks. You can see that
year-to-date, a lot of stocks, in fact,
are down more than 9%. A lot of them are
down 20%, 30%,
and many of them are very good
companies. Your Microsoft, your Nvidia,
your Meta, they are down double digits.
Your Palo Alto, great companies are down
a lot. And I own all these companies,
right? But why is it the S&P is only
down 9%? Because it's being held up by
the energy stocks. Why? Because oil. Oil
goes up, energy companies make a lot of
money. As you know, the majority of
stocks that I buy in my portfolio are in
these sectors like healthcare,
technology, financial stocks,
communication services stocks, and
consumer discretionary, also known as
consumer cyclicals. Why? Because stocks
within these sectors, they have much
higher growth rates, higher profit
margins, stronger economic moat, higher
return on capital compared to the S&P
500. So, in the long run, these sectors
over here, they way outperform the S&P
500 over the long run. But this year is
what we call a bizarro period.