It's 2009. You're at a Hannah Montana
movie, and your phone won't stop buzzing
with notifications from a new dating app
you just downloaded. Your favorite
artist is supposed to be releasing a new
album next year. Your favorite TV show
is currently being made into a movie,
and you're still riding high from
arguing how many days are in a week on
the bodybuilding.com forums. Life is
good, at least on the weekends. Because
during the week, you have to spend all
day using the worst programming language
ever invented. A language that was
famously designed in 10 days, but after
using it, it had you wondering what
Brendan did after day two. A language
that every browser interpreted
differently, had no standard library,
modules, or classes. And if your primary
job was to write it, I'm told you were a
massive loser who didn't deserve to feel
love. At least that's how things were in
2009. But over the next decade, that
sentiment changed. JavaScript went from
being a language that you'd never touch
directly without putting on a jQuery
hazmat suit first, it to arguably the
most popular programming language in the
world. While JavaScript developers,
despite all the stupid stickers on their
MacBooks, went from being considered
script kiddies to real programmers with
actual feelings and emotions. So, how
exactly did this mass psychosis happen?
There's a bunch of different reasons,
but in my opinion, I think the most
underrated was all led by a single
person who has since been forgotten to
time. Jeremy Ashkenas. In 2009, Jeremy
was a developer at Document Cloud, where
he had the unfortunate task of working
on a heavy client-side JavaScript
application, which was rare at that
time. Having a background in Ruby, but
being forced to write JavaScript, I
assume every morning he'd wake up and
think to himself, "Wow, today might be a
good day to jump myself off the Golden
Gate Bridge." But unlike everyone else
who had JavaScript Stockholm Syndrome,
Jeremy had the audacity to think he
could fix it. And so he did. His first
act was dealing with the fact that
JavaScript had no standard library.
Again, this was 2009. Although Firefox
had shipped support for some array
helper methods like map, reduce, and for
each, Internet Explorer hadn't yet,
which meant you couldn't use them unless
you polyfilled them. So, to fix this,
Jeremy released underscore.js, a utility
belt library that contained about 60
helper functions that made it easier to
work with arrays and objects. Now, I
know that doesn't sound exciting today,
but building for the web was so bad back
then that underscore likely did save a
few people from throwing themselves off
the Golden Gate Bridge.
Underscore got so popular that many of
its features were adopted into the
JavaScript language itself, which
eventually made it obsolete. But,
underscore was only Jeremy's first act.
Next,
instead of augmenting Fishhead
JavaScript with a new library, he'd have
more freedom if he just created an
entirely new language with large
cannons. Again, I can't stress this
enough, the JavaScript in 2009 was very
different than it is today. There were
no classes, so inheritance was done
through a pattern where you'd manually
attach properties to a hidden object
called prototype that every function had
access to. The only way to declare a
variable had bizarre scoping rules that
hoisted declarations to the top of a
function whether you were aware of it or
not. No one really understood or cared
about the difference between the
equality operator and the identity
operator. And so, you'd have a bunch of
type coercion happening without even
realizing it. And to define even a
simple function, you had to literally
type out the word function every single
time, which led to some pretty ugly
code. By building a new language that
compiled to JavaScript, Jeremy could fix
it without having to wait for the
standards committee or browser vendors
to do it themselves. And even better, he
could leave JavaScript, the bad parts,
in that musty room Brendan spent 10 days
in. And CoffeeScript was huge. The
father DHH adopted it almost overnight,
and in 2011, it shipped as the default
JavaScript preprocessor in Rails 3.1.
Meaning, the front end for every new
Rails app in the world was suddenly
written in CoffeeScript. GitHub,
Dropbox, and a long list of early 2010
startups adopted it, and for a few
years, it was the default choice for
anyone who took JavaScript seriously.
Today, CoffeeScript is basically dead
after its best features were absorbed
into JavaScript itself, but every time
your agent writes a class, arrow
function, default parameters, a spread
operator, does string interpolation, or
destructures a value, you can thank
CoffeeScript. But, Jeremy still wasn't
done yet. By 2010, he had given
JavaScript a standard library with
underscore and a better syntax with
CoffeeScript. But, there was still one
massive problem left. There was no good
way to actually structure a JavaScript
application. If you wanted to build a
large client-side heavy app, you would
still end up with thousands of lines of
spaghetti where your data, DOM
manipulation, and event handlers were
all tangled together. So, in 2010,
Jeremy released Backbone.js, a tiny
library of less than 2,000 lines of code
that gave JavaScript developers their
first real taste of MVC on the front
end. It introduced models for your data,
collections for groups of models, views
for rendering, and an event system that
let everything stay in sync without the
need to wire it up by hand. For the
first time, you could build a serious
client-side app without it collapsing
under its own weight. And with Jeremy's
track record, it quickly caught on,
powering the early versions of Trello,
Airbnb, Hulu, Pinterest, and basically
every other startup that needed a real
front end between 2011 and 2014. If you
were a JavaScript developer during that
window, you almost certainly wrote
Backbone, and you probably thought it
was the future. But, as it turns out, it
wasn't. Angular, Ember, and eventually
React would make Backbone obsolete by
taking its core ideas and pushing them
further. But, Backbone was the library
that proved you could actually build
client-side heavy applications. It's
easy to forget how bad JavaScript used
to be, and even easier to forget the
people who fixed it. But, the modern web
was built on top of ideas that Jeremy
Ashkenas pioneered, even if no one
remembers him. But, speaking of things
you no longer have to build yourself,
Auth is another one, thanks to Clerk,
the sponsor of today's video. They just
launched the Clerk CLI, which comes with
commands that are even more powerful
than the ones I I at that human dog
show. Just run clerk and knit in any
directory and it'll set up end-to-end
authentication for your entire project
with custom middleware, auth pages, and
environment variables. It even detects
if you're migrating from next auth or
auth0 and walks you through the entire
process. And since they know you're
using agents to do all your dirty work,
they also created clerk skills, which
ships framework specific patterns pinned
to the CLI version. So your coding agent
knows exactly how to use it. And the
clerk API command lets your agent hit
the entire clerk back-end API from the
terminal without copy and pasting
credentials. Try it out for free today
at the link below or just run clerk and
knit to get started. Thanks for watching
and I will see you in the next one.