SpaceX is being valued at 1.75 trillion.
That's what they want to sell the
business for to retail investors. The
current annual revenue is $16 billion.
Current profit before tax and
depreciation and amortization is $8
billion.
So, if you take the total valuation
divided by the revenue, you get a price
to sales ratio of 109 times. If you take
the total value divide by the profits,
which is the EBITDA profits, you're
getting a price to EBITDA ratio of 218
times. Now, this is based on last year's
revenue and profits. But, how about we
calculate the forward price to sales,
the forward price to earnings? Well,
depends on the projections. So, let's be
very optimistic and let's take the
aggressive projection. If the company is
looking to double its revenue in 1 year
to 32 billion and double its profits to
16 billion. Let's take the most
aggressive projection. At a current
valuation of 1.75 trillion, that is
still a forward price to sales ratio of
54 times and a forward price to EBITDA
ratio of 109 times.
So, is that expensive or cheap?