The next application we're going to
build introduces how to handle data on
chain. Specifically, for this project,
we'll be covering one of the most
fundamental challenges in modern
democracy, voting.
Think about traditional elections for a
moment. Whether it's a government
election or a doubt proposal or a
community poll, we face the same core
problems. How do we ensure every vote is
counted accurately? How do we prevent
fraud? How do we maintain transparency
while protecting voter privacy? And
perhaps most frustratingly, why does it
take hours or even days to get results?
This is where blockchain technology
shines. Let me break down why blockchain
is uniquely suited for voting. First,
immutability. Once a vote is cast on
chain, it cannot be altered or deleted.
The ledger is permanent and
tamper-proof. Second, transparency with
privacy. Every vote is publicly
verifiable on the blockchain, meaning
anyone can audit the results in real
time. But here's the key. Voters are
identified by their wallet addresses,
not their personal identity. So, you can
prove your vote was counted without
revealing how you voted. Third, instant
verification and results. Traditional
elections require manual counting,
recounts, and verification processes
that take days. On blockchain, votes are
tallied automatically as they're cast.
Results are available the moment the
voting period closes and every
participant can independently verify the
count. Fourth is accessibility.
Blockchain voting can happen from
anywhere with an internet connection. No
need for physical polling places, no
issues with mail-in ballots getting
lost, just your wallet and a few clicks.
In this project, we'll build a complete
on-chain voting system on Solana. Here's
what makes our implementation powerful.
We'll use program derived addresses, or
PDAs, to create deterministic voting
accounts. This means each poll gets its
own unique account derived from the
poll's parameters, and each voter's
ballot is stored [music] in an account
derived from their wallet and the poll
ID. This architecture prevents double
voting while maintaining a clean,
scalable structure. You'll learn how to
manage state efficiently on chain,
handling vote tallying in real time as
transactions come in. We'll implement
proper access controls to ensure only
authorized users can create polls, and
only eligible voters can cast ballots.
The code you write here scales from a
small Discord community poll to
governance systems managing millions in
treasury funds. The principles are the
same. Trustless verification,
transparent execution, [music] and
immutable results. Let's get started and
build the future of voting together.
So, for this project, we are coding the
voting application, and this is actually
the very first Anchor program that
you're going to be writing throughout
the bootcamp. So, for this one, we're
going to do it from scratch. Um the rest
will be more high-level understanding
concepts, but here we're going to show
exactly how to get started for writing
an Anchor program.
>> [snorts]
>> So, now I already have my voting
directory open in my terminal, and all
I'm going to do is type in anchor init,
and this is going to initialize my
workspace, but I should probably name
it. So, we'll do anchor init voting.
Okay.
And now it's generating a workspace for
me set up for Anchor smart contract
development on Solana. And this is able
to be generated because you have already
downloaded Anchor onto your machine
earlier in the install video, and with
that comes the Anchor CLI. Okay,
[snorts] so you can see it initialized
an empty Git repo for me with this
anchor init command. So, I'm going to CD
into voting,
and I'm going to open up that code, and
we're going to talk through what anchor
init generated for you, and then
actually start writing our program.
And this will be pretty quick because
creating a voting app on chain is
actually very simple. So, let's zoom in
a bit so you can see it. Now,
here you can see I have a lot of folders
generated. Um this app folder is for
when you're ready to build your front
end. Um this is not going to cover the
front end, but it will go into this
directory. And we have migrations as
well, and then your node modules. All of
this is really for the front end
TypeScript side of things. So, we're
going to focus on this programs folder.
And inside programs, you have voting and
source, and you have your cargo.toml.
Now,
this is actually set up
for a lot more complex of a program than
what we need. You can see that there's
an instructions folder, and that's going
to hold all of the separate instructions
for your project. There's constants,
error, instructions, lib.rs, and state.
And this is the most common best
practice for writing smart contracts. As
you see when we get to more advanced
concepts throughout the bootcamp like
the stable swap AMM, it's going to be
structured this way. But just for
simplicity here, I'm actually going to
delete all of this besides the lib.rs.
So, your main code with the entry point
for the program always lives in your
lib.rs file. So,
just going to delete this as well.
Okay. Now we just have our lib.rs.
And we'll get rid of the mods because we
don't need them. There's no other files.
Okay.
Great.
Now, let's start actually writing the
program. So, you can see there's already
some boilerplate code here, and it's
importing Anchor Lang, which is the
crate for the Anchor framework. There's
this declare ID, and what this is, it
just defines the program's ID, and the
program ID is this that you see right
here. So, this is your public key for
the program. And once you deploy the
program on chain, you're going to be
able to identify that program based on
this public key. So, we'll be able to
see that later when we connect to an
explorer and we're able to
search the explorer with the public key,
it's going to show us this program.
Now,
here you have a program macro, and all
this is doing is basically saying, "Hey,
all of the functions that exist within
here are going to be my instructions for
the smart contract that I'm writing."
And that is how Anchor kind of helps
simplify a lot of the smart contract
writing because it's going to cover your
entry point and deserializing and
serializing data for you, all within
this macro. So, all you have to worry
about is the function and the logic
behind it.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay. So,
now let's figure out what do we actually
want to write for voting. So, if we
think about voting, essentially, it's
not going to handle tokens on chain.
It's going to be like your most simple
smart contracts, and it's really just
handling data. And for voting, you're
keeping score of accounts between
different candidates. So, how does data
work on chain? Well,
one thing that we know is that smart
contracts on Solana are stateless,
meaning that
no data is stored within the smart
contract itself. If you're coming from a
different chain like Ethereum or Cosmos,
this is going to be a very new concept
for writing smart contract architecture.
Now, [snorts] where is the state stored?
It's stored in accounts. So, what we're
going to have to do is define what we
want our state to be and how those
accounts are going to look like. So,
whenever I'm designing a smart contract,
I always like to start with the state
and then move on to the logic after. So,
how do we actually do that? Well, we're
going to define an account because
that's where state is stored. Whenever
we want to create an account with
Anchor, all we're going to do is just
use the account macro that Anchor has.
So, I'll type out account here,
and that is doing all of the hard
behind-the-scenes work of generating
account and storing data. Now,
all I have to do is define what data
structure I want to store what fields
into my account state. So, I'm going to
name this struct poll account,
and
I'm going to enter all of the fields
that I want. So, let's think. If I'm
creating a poll on chain, what do I want
to store? Well, I'll probably want the
name of what the poll is and a
description. So, let's add that first.
So, we'll do poll
We'll do pub poll name,
and we'll just define that. It's going
to be a string. Now, there's something
that you're going to have to know with
Anchor is whenever you have a string
variable,
you're going to have to define a max
length, and the reason is it is
calculating the space that it needs to
take up on chain to be able to pay rent
for that account. So,
when you calculate the space, if you
have a string, you want to know about
how long the string will be to be able
to accurately calculate space. So, I'm
going to have to define here the max
length macro.
And for the name, we'll just do like 32.
It doesn't need to be that long. It's
just a name.
And back to where I was saying we need
to be able to calculate how much space
is on chain, there's actually a fun
Anchor macro that automatically does
this. So, I remember when I first
started building on Solana, you had to
manually calculate how much space was on
chain,
and it took forever.
So, [snorts] now you can just do a
derive init space as the macro
underneath your account macro, and it's
going to automatically calculate that
value for you. So,
now I'm going to define the next
variable, and that's just going to be
the description. And I'll need the max
length
for this one to be a little bit larger
because in a description, it's usually
longer than the title. And let's make
that like 280.
Okay.
And we'll name that as poll description,
and also going to be a string.
I used the wrong brackets. Little typo.
I'm like, "Why is there an error?"
That's why. Okay.
Cool.
So, now we have those fields. Now,
the other thing that's important when
you're creating a poll is when is it
going to start and when is it going to
end because you don't want the poll to
go on forever. So, let's add in those
fields as well. Now, this is going to
introduce the concept of
having time in your smart contract. So,
we'll talk about how you're actually
able to get time as we're writing the
logic. But for now, we just need to be
able to keep those values in our state.
And time is going to be a U64 type
because we're using a Unix timestamp
here.
Okay. So, we're going to have the poll
voting start and poll voting ends.
And that will also be a U64. Okay.
And then
the last thing is how many options do I
want in the poll? So, we'll just have an
index here that we're going to keep
count of. So, poll option index.
Okay.
Great.
So, that's everything for the poll
accounts. Um
now let's think about if we're creating
a poll, what other information do you
need to store? Not just the information
for the poll itself, but for what are we
actually voting on? So, we have
different candidates in a poll and we're
going to need to store that information.
So, that's another account that we're
going to have to create. And after that,
I think that's all of the data
that we really have to store for this
project. So, same thing, we're going to
follow adding account and derive and
init space cuz that's what you're going
to do whenever you're generating an
account. And now we're just going to
define what data we want to save for the
candidate. So, pub struct
can
did accounts.
I'll use the correct curly brackets this
time.
And now
let's just see what do we want to store?
Well, we need to keep track of the votes
and then what the actual thing is that
we're voting for, so the name.
So, let's save the candidate name.
And that's going to be a string and once
again for the string we'll have to
define the max length. So, you can
actually see here it's generating an
error. The Rust analyzer is pretty good
with this.
Um so, it's saying expected max length
attribute. So, if you ever forget,
you're just reminded because it's going
to be bright red and you don't like
that. So.
max length
And for the name we'll do the same as
the poll name, we'll do 32.
Okay. And if I save that again and the
Rust analyzer regenerates, now the error
went away.
And the last thing we're saving is just
the votes. So, pub candidate
votes and that's a number, so we're just
going to do U64 there.
And we're good to go. So, now we have
our two states. And usually whenever I'm
writing smart contracts, I always start
with the state to make sure that I know
where my data is being stored and what
data I have to work with throughout the
logic. So, throughout the rest of the
boot camp videos, um whenever we're
explaining a concept, I'm always going
to be starting with explaining what the
state looks like. But, this is the only
time I'm actually manually typing out
how to write the account state in your
smart contracts. So, if in the future
you ever get confused, come back to this
video and go over this section.
Now
now that I have the account, how do I
actually create it? Because all I've
done so far is defined what the data
looks like that's going to be stored
within that account state.
But, I haven't actually generated the
account. So, let's figure out how that
works. Um
well, there's this one concept with
Anchor.
And that's this context. So, let me
rewrite what I want this to actually
look like. And this is going to be
initializing my poll.
And if I initialize the poll,
I'm going to basically just be storing
all of these data fields into the
account and initializing it on chain.
So, every time you write an Anchor
program,
this first parameter of your function is
always going to be your context field.
And what this context field does is it
maps you to a custom data structure that
you write within your Anchor program
that's using this derive accounts macro.
And it's basically telling the function,
these are all of the accounts that
you're going to interact with when
executing this function and how you're
going to interact with those accounts.
So, we're going to write the data
structure for our derive accounts struct
to tell this function that it's going to
need to initialize a new account on
chain. So, let me name that. I'm going
to name it init poll.
And we're just going to write
we're going to write out our derive
accounts macro.
And now all you're doing is writing a
struct that's going to hold every single
account that you want to interact with
for its corresponding instruction. So,
for this instruction, all we're doing is
initializing a poll account. So, all we
have to worry about right now is three
accounts. So, the first account is
always going to be the signer. Whenever
you execute an instruction, you need to
have a signer that's signing for that
transaction. So, we're going to do pub
signer.
And that's going to be a signer type
with a lifetime.
And I forgot to name my struct, so this
is init poll.
Okay.
There we go.
I love how errors just show up right
away and then you know how to fix it.
Okay. Now, the next thing that we're
missing is whenever we have what the
account is, we also need to use the
account macro to just declare that it's
an account.
Now that we have that,
it's going to be showing that the signer
is an account.
And one thing that we're going to have
to add here is we're going to have to
add a constraint called mute. And what
that does is it makes this variable
mutable. So, in Rust all variables are
mutable by default. So, whenever you are
defining an account here and you know
that the account is going to change in
some manner, you're going to have to
mark that account as mutable. So,
whether the data in the account is going
to change, here for the signer, the
signer is going to have their balance
change because they're going to be
paying for the transaction. So, we do
have to mark that as mutable.
Okay.
Now, that's the first account. The
second account is the poll account cuz
we know that we're initializing that.
So, let me define an account again.
And we're going to add some constraints
on this as well, but we'll come back to
that. Let first let's just type out I
want this to be a poll account.
And this is going to be an account type.
And we'll need the lifetime specifier
and
this is going to be
the poll account data. So, this is just
mapping back to this poll account here
that we've defined.
Now, I left the constraints blank. So,
whenever you mark this account function,
there's several constraints in Anchor
that are telling you what you want to do
to that account during the logic of the
corresponding instruction. So, here what
I want to do, this account doesn't exist
yet. So, I'm going to initialize it.
So, let's type in init.
That's our first instruction.
Now, whenever you initialize a new
account, there's going to have to be a
payer and the reason is accounts have to
pay to store data on chain. You're
paying rent. And that's what we talked
about earlier where you have to
calculate how much space an account
takes up based on its data. Um the
reason you have to calculate that space
is the amount of money that you're
paying for rent correlates to how much
space you're taking up on chain. And
because of that, we do have to have a
payer assigned to the account that's
going to be paying for that rent.
So, the payer is the signer and then
we're you're just going to define the
space. So,
we have eight, which is the Anchor
discriminator, and we're going to add in
this fun little function we talked about
earlier that just automatically
calculates the space for us and that's
this init space.
Okay.
And then the next thing, so we're going
to make this poll account a PDA and a
PDA is a program derived address. It's
essentially a
address that doesn't have a public key
and it is created based on seeds and a
bump. And the seeds are input fields
that we're going to specify as we're
creating the accounts. And later when
you sign a transaction based on a PDA,
you're using those seeds rather than a
private key. So, you can pick whatever
seeds you want, whatever you think is
the most efficient for
the program that you're creating. So,
here we're just going to name it, we'll
do poll.
And then as ref.
And then I'm also going to want to store
the poll ID.
Just so I'm able to identify each of the
polls.
And we'll just do as ref there as well.
And now you can see again getting an
error. And the reason we're getting an
error is because every time you have
seeds, you're going to need a bump
because a PDA is generated based on your
input of seeds and a bump. So, all we
have to do here is specify a bump, which
I think if I delete this, it should
instruct you. Yeah, bump must be
provided with seeds. So again, if you
forget,
it'll just remind you.
Okay.
So, there is everything we need to
generate this poll account.
And you can see we're still getting some
errors and the reason is whenever you
are creating a new account on chain or
interacting with an account, you're
going to also need to interact with the
system program.
>> [snorts]
>> And
as we know, we're going to need to
specify every single account that this
instruction is going to have to interact
with. So, we're just going to add in the
system program.
And there we go.
So, we're getting some errors with the
lifetime, but that'll go away in a
second once we finish the logic. But,
another error that is now generated is
this poll ID. So,
you can see here if I hover over it,
says it can't find the value of the poll
ID. And what I'm doing is I'm pulling a
value from the poll accounts state. Um
however,
this poll ID
has not been stored yet in the state
because the account hasn't been created
and it's not able to find that value
anywhere.
So, [snorts] where we're going to need
to get the poll ID is going to be as an
input parameter in the instruction. And
whenever we're pulling variables from
the instruction, we have to tell Anchor
that so it knows where to look for it.
So, all we're doing here is just adding
another instruction and that's going to
be the instruction macro and inside
you're just going to specify what
variable you're pulling from the
instruction. So, we'll just do the poll
ID as well. I'm going to be taking
from that instruction.
And that's going to be a U64 variable
because it's
a number.
Okay.
So, that's good to go. Now we have all
of the accounts that are associated with
the instruction. So, the very last thing
to do is just write the instruction
logic. So, if I'm initializing the poll,
all I'm doing here is just saving all of
the data that I need to the poll
account. And a lot of this is just going
to be user input information because I'm
generating the poll and I want to be
able to specify all of the fields to be
able to create it.
>> [snorts]
>> So, as always, context is your first
field and then we're just going to add
all the other input parameters. So, we
have poll ID.
And I could store the poll ID in the
poll account state, but I don't really
need to because it's already stored in
my PDA and I wanted to introduce another
Rust concept here. So, I'll explain in 1
second. But, this is going to be the
only field that's not actually being
stored into the state.
So,
poll ID we're using for our PDA.
And then the rest of these input
parameters are going to be everything
that we need here that's being stored.
>> [snorts]
>> So,
we have poll ID, we have start time, end
time, name, and description.
So, start
is a U64.
End is also a U64.
And then name is a string.
And then description will also be a
string.
So, those are all of our input
parameters and all we have to do is
store that to our state. And it's very
easy with Anchor because I can just take
this context and load it in. So, I can
do context.accounts.
And that's going to be able to access
all of these accounts that I've
specified here. So, context.accounts
.poll_account.
And now I'm just going to access every
field. But, I can make this a variable
just so it's easier to write out. So,
we'll make this poll is equal to our
context poll account.
Okay.
Now, I can just do poll. s.
Poll description is our description.
And we're just going to fill in all of
these fields. And what it's doing is
taking each field in the account state
and saving the
>> [snorts]
>> information that's been an input to the
function into our account state.
So,
poll description, we have poll name.
And then we have poll voting start and
voting end.
And I've used the wrong comma for all of
these cuz I can't see that far. Okay.
Cool.
So, now that this was generated,
all that we have to do here is return an
okay value because our result is an
empty value here.
So, okay.
And now we're good to go.
And now, two Rust concepts that I wanted
to introduce here. One is you can see
we're getting an error here for poll.
And that's because I created a variable
and I didn't make it mutable because
Rust, all variables are immutable by
default. So, if I add this mute keyword,
now all of those errors go away. Okay.
So, one other thing that I wanted to
talk about, which it should be showing a
little yellow squiggly line here, but
sometimes Rust analyzer is a bit funky.
Um if ever you pass a variable as a
parameter into a function, but that
variable is not actually used in the
logic of the function, you're going to
get a warning because
why are you passing the variable if
you're not actually using it? So,
whenever that happens, because it does
happen quite a lot when you're writing
smart contracts because as you can see
here, we're needing the poll ID for our
PDA, but we don't actually need it in
the logic because I'm not storing it to
my poll account
account state.
So, basically, what you're doing is
you're telling Rust, "Hey, I know this
isn't being used in the logic of the
function, but I do actually need to
accept it as an input parameter."
>> [snorts]
>> Okay.
So, that's your first instruction.
Now, the second one is pretty much
identical to what I just explained
because all you're doing is creating an
account, initializing it, pulling in
input data, and storing it to that
account.
So, we've already initialized the poll
and now we're going to initialize the
candidate account. Since both of these
functions are really just initializing a
new account on chain and saving data to
it, it is very repetitive. So, what I'm
going to do is just copy and paste this
section of code so I'm not repeating
everything that I just explained. So,
we're just going to copy in our struct.
So, again, whenever we start a function,
we always start with the derive accounts
because we want to define every single
account that that logic for the
instruction is going to interact with.
So,
I'm just going to copy this over. Um
pre-wrote this section so you don't have
to
watch me type it all out.
And
we'll just paste that in. So, this is
our initialized candidate section and it
basically looks identical to the
initialized poll except for one
difference. And that difference is I'm
passing through a fourth account. And
that fourth account that I'm passing
through is actually the poll account
that we just created. The reason that
I'm passing this through is because
I need to access and update data from
the poll account. Whenever we have a new
candidate, we do have that field in the
poll account called poll index. And what
that index is keeping track of is how
many candidates are actually in the
poll. So, every time we do initialize a
new candidate, it's going to increment
that value. So, because of that, we do
have to make the account mutable to be
able to update the account state in the
poll.
And as you can see here, I'm once again
passing through the seeds in the bump.
And the reason that I'm doing this is
because the poll account is a PDA
account. And to be able to access the
correct PDA, you're always going to have
to pass through its seeds and bump.
Okay. So, now that we have that, um we
can just go over to the actual logic for
writing the initialized candidate
function. Now we have both of our
accounts initialized on chain and we
have an instruction for each. So, the
very last thing that we have to do here
is have an instruction that's actually
doing the vote. So, let's start with
that. But, before we
actually write the logic there, there's
one thing that I want to point out. Back
to a few fun little Rust things. So, you
can see earlier we wrote our poll here
and we made it mutable. But, now we're
getting an error and it's saying it
cannot move
because it's behind a mutable reference.
And the reason here is because now we
have this mutable reference for the poll
account.
So, the way to fix this, I'm going to
remove this and make a reference to it.
And do make it mutable.
And now we have our error go away.
Okay. So, if that ever comes up, that's
how you'll fix it. So, two different
ways to write variables with Rust.
Okay. Now, the very last function is
just our vote. So, we have pub fn
vote.
And we're going to pass through
our context. I'm just going to copy this
over so I'm not writing
everything out completely. Okay. And
we'll update it.
Okay. Now we have our outline of our
function.
And [snorts]
first thing is creating that derive
account struct. So, I'm going to name
this vote.
And I'll go down here and make the
actual struct. So, I can copy this. I do
a lot of copy and pasting here with um
Anchor cuz again, it does get
repetitive. And then we'll just edit it
as we need to.
So,
here is now going to be our vote.
Always going to have the signer as our
first account. We still do need the poll
account to access all of the information
for the poll that we're voting on. And
then we also need the candidate
accounts. And we're going to need to
update this. So, I copied this over from
the candidate accounts derive account
struct. And that was when we were
initializing the account, but now it's
already initialized. So, we can get rid
of that.
And everything you need for initializing
are these three constraints. And now
Now, just going to make it mutable
because we will be updating the account
state by adding a vote to that
candidate.
Okay, and that is good to go.
And we can actually get rid of this
system program for this one because
we're not initializing any new accounts
on chain. So, there you go. These are
the three accounts we're going to
interact with for voting. Now, we can
just write the logic and then we're good
to go.
So, everything that we need to pass
through for this vote instruction, there
are
few different fields.
One is going to be the poll ID and the
other is going to be the candidate. And
these are actually not using in the
logic, but the reason we need to pass
them through is because we're using them
for our PDAs down here. So, if we look
back again at this vote struct, we have
a poll ID that we're using for our poll
account PDA and we have a candidate that
we're using for our candidate PDA.
So, the way this actually works is if
I'm voting for candidate A
and there's A, B, and C as my
candidates. Every PDA is going to be
generated based on the candidate's name.
So, there'll be a PDA generated based on
A, B, and C.
And when I'm passing through what
candidate I want to vote for, I'm going
to be passing through A as my candidate
parameter. And it's going to pull that
value from the input of the instruction
and it's going to use it here when it's
calculating the PDA. So, then it's
generating the account that corresponds
with candidate A.
So, [snorts]
that's where we're not actually using
candidate in our logic for the
instruction. It's all mapping back to
the PDA. So, it's always best to
optimize how you're using PDAs and this
is one example for that.
Okay.
So, now that we have that taken care of,
let's add those two sections.
We'll do the poll ID
and the candidate.
Now, the logic. Okay. So, what am I
doing? Well, I'm going to be saving
the vote to the candidate account. So,
let's load in the candidate account. Let
So, we're going to load in let candidate
equal and mute. We're going to load in
our context and pull in that candidate
account.
CTX accounts
dot candidate account.
Now, we have all of the information
related to the account and we can update
it in our logic. Now,
first check. We want to make sure that
someone is voting while the poll is
actually active. So, we need to check
the current time and make sure that it
falls in between the start time and the
end time for the poll. So, let's load in
what the current time is. So, let
current time
equal to
and we're actually going to be able to
use clock. And clock is from
a Solana crate that you can import and
it represents the network time from the
blockchain.
So, clock is we're going to do get
and we'll unwrap that and one field
within clock is the Unix timestamp and
that's where what we're going to be
using to keep track of what time
it currently is when someone processes a
vote.
Okay. So, now we have that and again,
Unix timestamp is a U64 type, which is
why we saved our start time and end time
as U64s.
Okay. Now that we have that, we can do
if we'll just use some very basic if
statements here. So, if the current time
is greater than
the voting end, so we'll do
the context and we'll grab the voting
end time from the poll account, which is
why we needed to pass that poll account
through here. So, poll account dot
poll voting end.
And I'm going to have to cast this as an
I64 because actually Unix timestamps
can't be negative.
Um so, it's an I64, not a U64.
And
we'll put this in brackets because I'm
in parentheses because I'm casting it.
Okay.
So, if that happens, we're going to
return an error.
And I can make uh errors by using the
And I can write errors in Anchor by
using the error code macro. So, I'm just
pasting this in so I don't have to type
it all out, but um we have an error code
macro and you're able to write all of
the errors that you want for your
instruction and then a message that you
want to admit whenever that error does
occur. So,
let's go back and then specify our
error.
So, it's just the error code and then
we're going to do voting end ended.
Now, we need another if statement for
essentially the opposite. So, let me
copy this, paste it in.
And now if the current time is
less than or equal to
the poll voting
start.
Okay. Once again, casting as an I64.
And then we're going to return a
different error, which is voting not
started.
So, so far in our vote instruction, we
have checked the current time and made
sure that the current time falls within
the voting start and end time, so it's
actually an active poll. We've loaded in
the candidate information. So, the very
last thing we have to do is just save
the vote to the corresponding candidate
account. So, since we already know the
right candidate account is being loaded
in because it's taking this input
parameter and generating the PDA based
off of it,
all we have to do is take candidate
and then
set the candidate votes field to
increment by one.
Okay.
And we're good to go.
Now,
back to the Rust warning for having
variables that are unused in your logic,
that we'll just put our little
underscore here because we are using it
in the account struct. Okay.
And that is everything that you need for
your program and we can just build it to
make sure everything runs. But just a
quick overview, we have our program
macro here. All of our instructions live
within that program macro. So, we have
initializing our poll. Our poll accounts
is the account that's holding all of the
data for the new poll that we're
generating. It's also keeping an index
of how many candidates are corresponding
to that poll.
We have initialize candidate, which is
the instruction that will be ran every
single time you want a new candidate
added to the poll. And then we have vote
and vote is when anyone wants to come in
and make a vote. They're going to
specify the candidate they're voting for
and it's going to update the candidate's
account state with a another vote in
their state.
And that's everything. So,
whenever you're writing smart contracts,
start with your account.
What state do I want to store?
Then you write out your instruction.
You're going to write all of the
corresponding accounts that the
instruction needs to interact with and
then you can finish out your instruction
logic.
So, the last thing we're going to do
here is just build our instruction.
And if I go to my terminal
and I'm going to
see.
Okay.
Making sure I'm in the right directory
here. I'm just going to type in anchor
build.
And once again, we're using that Anchor
CLI that we've installed earlier. It's
going to compile my program and make
sure everything works. And the great
thing about Rust code is if your code
compiles, you're pretty much good to go.
It has a really great compiler. Um it
just takes a long time to compile. So,
we'll let this load, probably speed it
up for the video, and um make sure
everything looks good.
All right. So, our code compiled.
Everything's good to go.
Now, one more thing that I want to show
you is just deploying because I did
mention earlier that this
public key maps back to your address and
I just want to showcase that. So, in our
install script, we already created our
Solana wallet address and we funded it
with devnet SOL.
Um so, I should just be able to deploy.
So, if you run the command anchor deploy
and you have the flag provider
dot cluster
and then I type in devnet, it's going to
deploy my compiled program onto devnet
with that local keypair that we
generated earlier.
And I spelled it wrong. So, one second.
Provider.
So, you can see it's deploying to the
Solana devnet cluster. The upgrade
authority is my keypair that's saved on
my local machine. It's deploying the
program. Here is the path. So, this path
is taking you to the SO file that was
generated when you ran anchor build. So,
that is over here. If we go to target
and deploy,
you have this voting.SO.
This file is what is being deployed onto
the Solana blockchain. In our case, the
devnet chain.
Um
great.
So, it's saying I need to install a
package. So, seems like I'm a bit out of
date in my CLI. We'll just let this
install and then let it finish
deploying. Then we're going to go to the
Solana Explorer and then just check out
our program.
Okay, great. So we're good to go.
Now I'm going to
open up a browser, [sighs]
type in explorer.solana.com.
So explorer, that's our block explorer.
Currently connected to the main net
cluster, I'm going to switch over to dev
net.
And let's go back over to our VS code
and we're going to go back to that
declare ID function that I talked about
in the very beginning. So copying this
public key,
I'll go back to Firefox and I'm going to
paste this in.
There we go.
So here's my program that was deployed
on chain.
And you can see my deployment happened
just a few minutes ago.
And this is how you're able to access
all of the information that's actually
running on the network for what you're
building.
Now we finished writing our first Solana
smart contract and now we're going to
talk about how to actually test it. So
contract is written, but when you're
testing a program, you want to be able
to actually test against the Solana
virtual machine.
So how can we do that? Well, there is a
framework called light SVM. So light
SVM, it's a lightweight library for
testing Solana programs. It works by
creating an in-process Solana virtual
machine that's optimized specifically
for program developers. So we're going
to be writing rust tests that correspond
with our rust smart contract that we
just wrote. Here is all of the latest VM
documentation. So there's several
different helper crates that are
available. Um and then if we click into
the documentation, it talks about how to
get started, why you would want to use
light SVM for your testing, how to test
your program, some examples.
So examples, this is just some very
common copy and paste test for certain
ways that you would want to set up your
environment.
And then we have our API reference and
then just additional documentation for
each helper crate that's available for
you.
Now
great reference as you're writing custom
light SVM tests for the programs that
you're writing, but we're going to go to
the voting app that we just wrote.
>> [snorts]
>> Now
I don't want to take the time to
actually manually write out all of this
code on on the video. So I already wrote
it beforehand and we're just going to go
over all of the important concepts that
you need to know to be able to write
light SVM tests. So
this is for an anchor program that we
wrote. So we're going to be using some
additional helper crates for light SVM.
So we import anchor and then we also
import the anchor light SVM helper
crate.
And by doing that, it's going to help
generate clients from the IDL that you
generated when you ran anchor built. So
whenever you're writing your light SVM
tests, you want to make sure that you
ran anchor built beforehand and you have
your target directory generated and
within your target directory, you do
have an IDL here because it's going to
be accessing this IDL to generate
clients for you.
And this keeps all of your tests type
safe in rust.
Now
going back to this file
here are all the important concepts that
you need to understand to be able to
write your own light SVM tests. First is
declare program. You're going to be
using this and calling in what your IDL
is for the application. And this is
going to be able to generate the types
for you.
So here are the paths to be able to grab
each type that you have. So you can see
it when I hover over this, I have the
type that we wrote for our candidate
account data structure and then the type
that we wrote for our poll account. So
now we can easily access all of the data
for each of these types.
And then
this is pulling in the .so file that was
generated when you ran the anchor built
command.
Now
when you're writing light SVM test, you
do have a little bit of a setup before
you can actually [clears throat] test
your program and the reason is you're
generating an in-process VM. So you're
going to have to create all of the token
accounts or deploy the program and get
everything set up to be able to actually
use it. So how we're setting this up
when you use the anchor context from
your anchor light SVM test, you'll be
able to now set up your VM. And because
we're using the Solana clock, which you
can see here
we're using this for testing because we
do have to get accurate timestamps to
know if the poll is a valid time or not.
And all of that is just setting up your
environment.
Now we have a few helper functions and
this is just for generating PDAs. So we
know when we're writing a PDA, we have
to define our seeds and then we define
our bump. And the PDA is generated by
running your input seeds and the bump
through a SHA-256 hash function and it
returns your public key for your PDA.
>> [snorts]
>> Um so
how do we
now get that? Um we're going to need to
get the PDA account for each of these
addresses to be able to accurately test
it. So you can do that with this helper
function that's find program address.
And all you have to do here is just
write out all of the seeds that are
associated with the PDA.
>> [snorts]
>> So we have these two helper functions to
be able to get the PDA for our poll
account and the PDA for our candidate
account.
Now that all that setup is done
um typically it's a bit more setup
because you'll have to initialize tokens
on chain, create mint accounts, create
token accounts, things like that, but
here we're just handling data. We didn't
introduce tokens yet. Um that will come
with our escrow program, which is the
next project. So here we're just
worrying about data. That's all of our
setup. Now we can write our first test.
So to write the test, we're just using
our setup function.
Now we do need to fund an account and
the reason we need to fund an account is
because we need to have an account
that's going to be the signer for
processing the transactions. So this is
creating an account for us. We're
funding it with lamports and then we're
going to unwrap it.
>> [snorts]
>> Now we have all of these values defined
because these are all of our input
parameters for our instructions that
we're testing. So a little bit more
setup there.
Now all you have to do is call the
instruction
from your anchor context because the
anchor light SVM crate is now generating
this anchor context for you.
So when I call this, I can now call the
program and I can call the accounts that
are associated with the instruction that
I want to execute. And then all of the
arguments that
have to be passed through for the
instruction. So here you can see for
initializing the poll, we did specify
three accounts in our derive account
struct, which was the signer, the poll
account and the system program. All of
that we do have to specify in the
accounts section when we're calling this
instruction for testing. Then the next
section is your arguments and for
initialize poll, the arguments that we
accept are the poll ID, the start time,
the end time, the name and the
description. So this is just pulling in
those parameters for the function. Now
all you do after that is specify that
it's an instruction and then unwrap it.
Then you're able to get the result by
running the execute instruction function
from light SVM. So you can see this
execute instruction here.
So what that's going to do is execute
the instruction through the in-process
Solana VM that's running with light SVM.
And
it's going to basically be like you're
testing it on chain. So here we're just
making sure that the result actually was
successful and then we are asserting
that the result is the accurate answer
that we want. So here we're asserting
that the result is actually the answer
that we want. We're pulling in the poll
account data after the transaction took
place and then we're asserting that each
field in the poll account has been
correctly updated to the input
parameters that we've already defined in
our argument section here.
So that's pretty much it. Now what this
function does is if I run it
it's going to test the initialize poll
instruction.
And you can see down here one test
passed, so we're good to go.
Now you can take on your own time when
you clone this code to look through the
other instructions, but when you want a
100% test coverage on your code, you
just want to go through all of the
instructions and then potential edge
cases that you can think of. So here we
have testing the initialize candidate,
testing a successful vote.
We have testing multiple votes.
And we have multiple candidates as well.
So here we're testing some of our error
cases. So we had two errors. One was
voting before the vote actually started
and one was voting after the voting
window ended. So this is testing to make
sure it returns the correct error. So
you can see here the result, we want to
assert that it returned an anchor error
of voting not started. And this anchor
error is from that error code macro that
you generated when you were writing the
program.
So
here's the other error case and then
testing multiple polls as well. And that
covers pretty much 100% test coverage
for our voting program. So if I just
want to go through and run all of the
tests, I can
open my terminal and I'm just going to
run cargo test and that's going to pull
all the light SVM tests and run them.
And you can see here it ran eight tests,
all the eight that we just went over and
all of them passed. So we're good to go.
And that is how you're going to be
testing all of the programs that you
write. So light SVM is an efficient way
to test [music] your programs. So here's
an example with the voting program
that's just handling data and then as
you progress the rest of the projects
[music] in the boot camp, it will show
the progression of using light SVM for
more advanced use cases.
And that is testing your voting program.