Just a few days ago, during the
Berkshire Hathaway annual meeting,
Warren Buffett once again said that
prices in the stock market were too high
and he didn't see anything to buy. And
right now, his company has accumulated
over 397 billion dollars in cash without
having anything to buy. So, is this a
signal for you as an investor to get off
the markets? Do not buy anything
because, you know, the markets are too
expensive. Well, let's explore that in
this video.
I know quite a number of people who have
been staying out of the stock markets
for quite a while and they've missed out
on the huge rally in the markets and by
staying in cash, they're seeing their
purchasing power erode because of
inflation. And then, the reason they
give is because they say, "Oh, the stock
market is too expensive." And it's not
something new. They've been saying this
for the last two, three, some people
even four years. And when you ask them,
"Why is the market too expensive?" They
say, "Look at Warren Buffett. He's one
of the greatest investors in the world."
Which I don't agree with, right? I'm a
loyal Buffett disciple. And Buffett, for
quite a while, I think now for over 1
year, he's been a net seller of stocks
and not a net buyer of stocks. And he's
also said for quite a while that, you
know, there's there's nothing to buy.
There's nothing to buy. There's nothing
to buy. And again, just a few days ago,
he reiterated that by saying that stock
prices are too high and the stock market
now is looking more like a casino than
than a church, right? He likes it to be
like a church where people stay and they
are loyal, but you know, casino, they
they go in and out. And as a result, his
company has now accumulated 397 billion
in cash. So, there are a lot of people
who read it as a very bearish sign that
that he's giving. That he's saying that,
you know, things are too expensive and
he's waiting for the market to crash.
And people think that Buffett's
predicting a crash and that's why he's
holding so much cash. Now, for someone
who's a loyal Buffett devotee and
someone who has read everything he's
written, I've watched all his videos
many, many times, I've followed Buffett
now for 30 years and one of the things I
can tell you about understanding
Buffett's philosophies, he doesn't
attempt to predict the market at all.
You know, he keeps saying that I've got
no idea where the market's going to be
next week, next month, next year. He's
got no idea, right? But what he does is
that he only buys companies
that he understands, that are
high-quality companies when they are
undervalued. So, the reason he's not
been buying anything, he's holding so
much cash, is because, frankly, yeah, he
can't find anything that's undervalued,
you know? But on the other hand, people
look at me say, "Adam, but why are you
buying?" All right? For those of you who
are in my community, my ultimate
investors playbook, you get my alerts
every day. You know that I'm buying
stock almost every single day. I'm
trading options every single day. So, I
see quite a number of quality companies
in the market right now. So, why is
there this difference? You You know,
people say, "Aren't you a value
investor? Aren't you following Buffett's
style?" Yes, but why do I have things to
buy and he doesn't have anything to buy?
And there are three reasons why I'd like
to explain to you. And three reasons why
people who watch Buffett and think that
they should be bearish, why they may be
misreading the situation, okay?
So, reason number one, if you understand
Warren Buffett, you would know that
Buffett's discipline, his rule, is to
only invest in businesses that he
understands, that are within his circle
of competence. So, he has said many
times that he doesn't understand
technology, you know, because he doesn't
use it. And he he famously for years
only used a flip phone. And when he
bought Apple, he was given an iPhone by
Tim Cook. But till today, he only uses
his iPhone to make phone calls. He
doesn't even know how to use
messaging. He doesn't use like Messenger
or or or social media. He doesn't use
any of those things, right? Because he's
not interested. He doesn't even have a
computer on his desk for the last 60
years. So, he doesn't understand
technology and he's admitted himself.
You know? And in fact, the only
technology company he bought was IBM
years ago and he lost money on that,
right? Because he admitted, "I bought
something I didn't understand." So, he's
since then followed that rule. Now, some
of you may say, "How about Apple? He
made so much money on Apple, right?"
Now, if you think about it, and in his
mindset, Apple to me is not a technology
company. Apple is a consumer products
company that people are addicted to. And
the reason he bought Apple was because
his grandchild, I think his
granddaughter, said to him one day that,
"I can't live without my iPhone. I can't
live without [laughter] my iPad." Right?
So, he realized that Apple has become a
utility company that people can't live
without, you know? And that's why he
bought Apple. So, to him, Apple is not a
a tech company, right? But like Google
and Microsoft and and Nvidia, these are
tech companies that he doesn't
understand, yeah?
So,
he strictly only invests in certain kind
of companies, which are large cap, large
companies, mature companies and most of
them are old economy companies like
railroads, industrial companies,
insurance. That is his niche, all right?
And if you look at many of the companies
in his niche, I agree with him, they are
crazily overpriced right now. In fact,
they've been very overpriced for the
last few years. For example, take a look
at Coca-Cola, one of the companies that
he owns and is within his niche, right?
Coca-Cola is now selling at a PE ratio
of 25 times, you know? That's really
expensive for a
soft drink company, okay? Walmart, one
company that fits his criteria, is
selling at 48 times PE. Costco is
selling at 52 times PE. Crazy. By the
way, these are great companies. I would
love to buy them as well, but to me it's
like, "You're mad. It's too expensive,
right? It's way overvalued." Uh Moody's,
uh
financial company at 33 times PE. Crazy
expensive, right? How about banks? Now,
for banks, we don't use PE ratio, we use
price to book ratio. And if you look at
JP Morgan, for example, the price to
book ratio is at 2.43 times. Again, it's
crazy. I would love to own JP Morgan,
but it's so expensive, yeah? So,
understand that
it's kind of like the ocean.
Buffett only fishes at certain parts of
the ocean and I fish at certain parts.
So, if you look at ocean, is the ocean
deep or shallow? Depends. Certain parts
of the ocean are shallow
and certain parts are deep. So, when he
says that the market is too expensive,
he's saying that, "Oh, the ocean is too
shallow." He's right in certain areas,
okay? But he avoids the areas which
Ironically, right now, a lot of the tech
companies, well, I wouldn't say all of
them, but many of the very undervalued
companies are actually in tech. And
that's why he doesn't see them because
it's not within his core competence. Of
course, as I said many times, PE ratio
by itself can be very misleading. We
have to look at the growth of the
earnings and the growth of of the cash
flow. So, we look at things like forward
PE and discounted cash flow to get a
bigger a better picture, right? So, if
you look at Stock Oracle, it can give
you a more detailed picture. And again,
let's take a look at the stocks that
Buffett would buy, you know, Costco.
Great company. I would love to own
Costco, but look at the again, the the
PE ratio, 52 times. Again, it's
meaningless. But look at the forward PE
at 44 times. And this company is growing
at about 8 to 7%. So, a company that
grows 7, 8%, but the PE is like 40 to
50, that's that's pretty expensive. And
if you look at the intrinsic value, you
know, if you look at discounted cash
flow,
yeah, discounted free cash flow, you can
see that
it's only worth about 488, but the share
price is now at a thousand dollars,
right? So, it's a big gap between what
the market is paying for and the
discounted
cash flow that you'd be receiving over
the next 20 years. Let's take a look at
Walmart. Same thing. Walmart is growing
at about 8.9 to 8% long term. That's the
growth, but selling at 48 times PE,
forward PE, 40 times. If you look at the
discounted free cash flow, that's only
$39, whereas the share price is $131,
okay?
Big gap, you know? So, he's right. The
market is crazy expensive for these kind
of companies. And look at Coca-Cola,
again, something he's held for many
years. Coke is growing at 6.9% to 4.5%
long term, selling at, you know, 24
times PE, forward PE, 22 times. If you
do a discounted cash flow, free cash
flow, it's worth like, you know, 49, 50
bucks, right? 49, 58 bucks at the most,
but share price is now at $78. But
again, are all companies expensive? No,
there are some great companies that are
actually undervalued. These are just
simply the companies that Buffett is not
interested in. It's outside his circle
of competence. And of course, one of
them is a company whose products I use
every single day. My company spends
millions on advertising on this product
every single day. 3.6 billion people use
this product every single day and
growing. It's Meta Platforms that owns
Facebook, WhatsApp, Messenger, Threads
and uh In- Instagram, right? So, if you
look at Meta Platforms, for example,
and if you look at the discounted
free cash flow, you can see that it is
worth $749.
The current share price is at $608. So,
it is undervalued. Now, bear in mind
that this discounted free cash flow
that calculates 749
if I show you the actual calculation,
you can actually see it here.
All right? Uh it's based on
the recent free cash flow
after accounting for huge amount of
capital expenditure. As you know, uh
Meta has increased their CapEx
uh because spending on the AI data
centers. Let me just show you where that
is.
Uh that's over here.
Yeah. So, you can see their CapEx has
recently gone up a lot, right? Because
of the All right? So, that is causing
the free cash flow. Let me just show you
this uh free cash flow.
Easier to see here. Yeah. So, look at
the free cash flow. The free cash flow
has actually dropped, right? It's
actually dropped because of the extra uh
CapEx. But even with that free cash flow
decline,
uh the valuation
based on that recent free cash flow
is at 749.
Now, you may be wondering, why is there
the Oracle value? By the way, the Oracle
value is stock Oracle's AI that
calculates what it thinks is the fair
intrinsic value. Now, the Oracle value
is $900. So, why is that higher? Why is
that $900 higher than the normal
discounted free cash flow? Because
Oracle value, what it does is that it
normalizes
the CapEx. So, it takes the average
CapEx of the last 5 years to normalize
it, take the current cash from
operations minus the 5-year average
CapEx to get a normalized free cash
flow.
So,
personally for me, I look at the
valuation as $900. And so, it is quite
undervalued. If you look at Meta, you
can see Meta is projected to grow at 19%
for the next 5 years and beyond that
grow at about 14% by selling at a
forward PE of only 17 times earnings.
So, yeah, I would say that Meta
Platforms is one of the great companies
that are dirt cheap right now. And of
course, it's not the only one. There are
a couple of others which I'll show you a
chart in a short while. But let's get
back to this, right? So, first reason,
bear in mind that, you know, Buffett and
me or you, we can all be right, you
know? He can say it's expensive, he's
right in his part of the ocean. I can
say that it's cheap in my part of the
ocean, yeah? The ocean is really, really
big, yeah? Now, the other thing to bear
in mind when you see that he's holding
so much cash is that remember that his
company, Berkshire, is fundamentally an
insurance company.
In fact, many insurance company to one.
And he's also a reinsurance company,
which means he insures other insurance
companies. And as a huge one of the
biggest insurers in the world, he has
got to have enough cash all the time to
ensure that if there are hurricanes,
there are wars, and and and third three
sigma events, he's got enough cash to
pay off all those claims. So, a big part
of the cash is not a technical move
only, but it's a structural thing that
he has to always keep um with him,
right? The third thing to bear in mind
is that, you know, if you had blindly
just followed you know what he's doing
without understanding the reason why,
you would have missed out a lot of gains
in your wealth building process.
And in 2020, think about in 2020 when uh
during COVID when the market dropped
uh I think about over 35%
you know, Buffett didn't buy anything
significant, right? And since then, the
market is up 250% from that level. And
as you guys know, I was buying
significantly. And so were many of you
guys who were actually watching my
videos.
And in 2022, there was another bear
market where the market fell again about
25%, he didn't buy anything as well.
And since then, the market is up 100%
from that level. You could have doubled
your money. Over here, you could have
almost tripled your money, right? And
even more recently in 2025 when Trump
came up with his
uh tariff for the world liberation day,
again the market dropped 20%. He didn't
do anything, right? But if you had again
bought stocks when you were cheap, I
mean, again the right stocks when they
were cheap, you know, the market's up
51% from there, you know? So, you have
to be very careful about just, you know,
blindly following what other people are
doing. Now, again, let me reiterate that
I'm a very loyal Buffett disciple. He is
my guru, all right? So, uh no disrespect
to him at all. But what I'm saying is
that I follow him very closely in terms
of philosophy.
And the philosophy is to stick within
your circle of competence, buy things
that you understand, buy companies whose
products and services you use yourself,
and calculate your own intrinsic value
or you can use stock Oracle that helps
you a lot, buy only when it's
undervalued,
and have the patience to let it compound
over time. That is the philosophy that I
follow, not necessarily what he buys or
sells, all right? Simply by following
his philosophy, but overlaying my own uh
core competence, I've been able to
significantly outperform the market. In
fact, outperform Berkshire in the last,
you know, couple of years. You can see
this the last uh over 7 years since
January 2019, my portfolio is up uh 249%
uh which is above the S&P 500 in green
and above Berkshire Hathaway, which is
in yellow. As I shared with you guys
before, in January this year, I actually
withdrew 99% of my funds from my joint
account. And you see the big drop in the
net asset value. Why? Because I
transferred everything to a new private
limited corporate account in order to
avoid estate tax, right? So, this is the
old account where I withdrew 99%. I left
1% to continue the returns.
Uh and this my new account, which I just
again uh put in in January this year.
And this new account, my new private
limited company, is up 10.76%
uh year to date, way outperforming the
market. Now, the best thing is that it's
not just me. My students are
outperforming the market as well simply
by following all these strategies of
buying great companies when they're
undervalued and overlaying the right
technical analysis as well. And you
know, hundreds and hundreds of my
students share their testimonials all
the time. These are the recent two of
them. One of them is Mo, who is in my
Whale Investor course and also in UIP,
which is the Ultimate Investor's
Playbook. He said, "You know, on a side
note, I took your course back in 2022,
opened a new account, and followed most
of your teachings. And in 3 years, this
is the result." What's the result? It's
up 106%
over the last 3 years.
And
up 29%
in the last 1 year.
And then we've got people like Cam who
said, "3 years this month since my
portfolio inception, I'm up 307%
uh despite a modest start to 2026. Um
It's been a great
It's been great being part of your
wonderful community and continuing to
grow and learn and watching the monthly
updates and deep dives. Huge thanks to
uh myself and the entire Piranha Profits
team for all the hard work and long may
it continue." So, again, the reason I
publish my results every single year,
the reason my students willingly show
their results is not to impress you, not
to show off to you, but to inspire you
that if we can do it,
you can do it. Why not? In fact, many of
my students, when they first joined my
program, they had zero financial
background, zero investment experience.
But they had open mind, they were
disciplined, they followed the rules,
and they consistently beat the market,
not just in the short term, but in the
long term as well.
So, like I like I promised, the last
thing I'm going to show you is what
other stocks are undervalued in the
market today. So, again, I just got um
Richard, who is um one of my
researchers, right? To do this uh recent
update.
And so, this was updated just yesterday,
right? So, you can see that within the
S&P 500 uh yes, there are stocks that
are really expensive. In fact, there are
about 24% of stocks that are very
overvalued, which means they are selling
30% above their intrinsic value. To be
specific, 123 stocks out of 500, right?
And 81 stocks or 16% are overvalued. So,
these are the ones where right now, you
know, we don't want to buy them. Even
though could be great companies. Wait
for them
to drop from
uh very overvalued or overvalued to
fairly valued where it's within a buy
range or better still when it's
undervalued. That gives us a bigger
margin of safety. So, in the S&P right
now, we have got 111 stocks that are
fairly priced, which means they're
selling
um within plus minus 10% of their
intrinsic value. So, this is where we
can go fishing. We look for fishes
within our circle of competence.
And
we've got uh 88 stocks that are
undervalued and 99 stocks that are very
undervalued. So, again, there's always
opportunities. There's always fish in
the ocean. You just have to know where
to look, yeah? So, to be specific, here
it is, okay? So, these are the stocks
that are very expensive right now.
By the way, TJX is a stock that I really
want to own. I've been watching it for
quite a while. It's a very simple
business. It's a retail business, but
it's a great It's a great business. But
right now it's too expensive, so I'm
watching that so that when it gets, you
know, fairly priced under priced, I'm
going to start buying it. When's it
going to happen? I don't know. I can't
predict, right? But one day it will
become undervalued, you know?
What else is overvalued? We've got
Yeah, Tesla is still very overvalued.
Even though it's dropped a lot, it's
still too expensive to me.
We've got Exxon, which I like as well,
but that's very expensive.
And a few others, right? You can go down
the list and check it out yourself.
And then we've got stocks that are
overvalued like Apple's overvalued.
I have a stake in Apple. I want to buy
more, but I can't buy more because it's
overvalued, especially after earnings it
popped up. And we have got now Amazon
that is slightly overvalued, which is
not my big my second biggest position,
in fact. But of course, I bought Amazon
when it was undervalued. But now I can't
buy any more because it is now
overvalued, all right? Then stocks that
are fairly priced you can see over here.
And stocks that are undervalued
over here, and stocks that are very
undervalued over here. And again, as
I've said many times before,
don't just buy a stock because it is
cheap. Because cheap crap
is still crap, okay? Cheap can become
even cheaper, all right? So going to
make sure that not only is it
undervalued, it must be a high-quality
business that meets the right investment
criteria of having a high return on
equity, high ROIC, strong economic moat,
consistent growth in revenue and
profits, blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah, you know, these are the stuff that
I run through with my students you know,
all the time that we share in our
community deep dive research. And of
course, with Stock Oracle you can check
the fundamentals of a business pretty
easily.
And if you look at a chart, for example,
another stock that is very undervalued
right now is ServiceNow. And why is it
undervalued? Because of this prediction
that AI will disrupt all the software
companies, but the facts don't show
that. The facts still show that the
company's compounding
at a significant rate. And if you look
at ServiceNow, for example, let's take a
look at ServiceNow.
Yep, corrected down a lot. But if you
look at the fundamentals,
straight away you can see that in terms
of predictability, it's high.
Profitability, it's medium. It's not too
bad. Growth, high growth. Economic moat,
strong moat. Financial strength, medium.
And valuation is high, which means that
it is undervalued right now. You want to
be more specific, you can take a look.
It's projected to grow at 19.77%
for the next 5 years and beyond that,
19.41%.
And this is These are all the
projections taking into account the
potential disruption from a gigantic AI,
which again, so far there's no real
evidence. If you look at the financials
over here,
you can see again, they just announced
great earnings, great profits, you know,
revenue growing very consistently. You
have got operating cash flow growing
very consistently, free cash flow
growing very consistently, but the price
is down. Why? Again, because of the
sentiment of the market, the emotions of
the market. If you look at the intrinsic
value over here,
you can see that using, you know,
discounted free cash flow,
the stock is worth $234.
And right now it's selling at $91. It's
selling, you know, more than half below
the discounted free cash flow. And even
when Stock Oracle
is more conservative and normalizes some
of the numbers, the Oracle values at 205
and that's again way below that, right?
So again, there are opportunities out
there. Take a look at it and of course,
remember, it's all about position sizing
as well. Make sure that you size your
position correctly, buy great companies,
and let it compound. Thank you for
listening and as always, may the markets
be with you. If you want to catch my
latest videos, click on the subscribe
button right now. Click on the bell so
you get instant notifications once I
upload my latest video. If you want to
check out my online courses, go to
piranaprofits.com.
We're going to learn how to invest and
how to trade the financial markets and
create an income from all around the
world.
If you want to join my live Wealth
Academy program, go on to
wealthacademylocal.com
and find out more about how you can
learn investing and trading live online.
This is Adam Khoo and may the markets be
with you.