So this is guy called Wes Gray and he
wrote another article with a very cute
title. His article is called even God
would get fired and you can go and
Google and read that article. It's
pretty interesting. And in that article
he did a research and he found that even
if you build a portfolio with perfect
knowledge like God and you knew exactly
the next five years which would be the
best performing stocks, your portfolio
would still go through a 76%
drawdown and five separate 30% drawdowns
on the way of beating the market. Think
about that, right? So the implication is
that drawdowns aren't evidence that
you're wrong. They are a structural
feature of equity ownership. So in other
words,