we can actually be traditional finance.
>> This is one of the people quietly
rewriting how global finance works. Meet
Anatoly Yakovenko, one of the founders
of Solana. It's completely open finance.
See a full control over the entire
stack. This network processed over a
trillion dollars last year. It runs 24/7
and every line of code is open for
anyone to read. My dream is that it's
like Linux. And today he's sharing his
entire vision for where markets are
heading. Why the biggest trading [music]
firms are now building on Solana instead
of competing against it. His bold
prediction for the next 10 years.
>> There's not going to be a difference
between DeFi and finance. We'll just
call it all finance. And what every
trader needs to understand right now.
Because in this game the only enemy left
isn't a competitor. You are fighting
physics. And what what better thing can
you possibly work on?
Hey everyone. Today we have a very
special guest, Anatoly Yakovenko, one of
the founders of Solana. So thanks for
joining us today.
Thanks for having me.
Yeah. Happy that you're here. So in this
video we're going to be kicking off an
education series that's teaching market
infrastructure on Solana and how to
build on it. So before we get into any
of the deep questions, what is your
elevator pitch to get someone interested
in using Solana or building on it?
I think
what got me really interested in
building Solana in the first place was
that it's completely open finance. See a
full control over the entire stack.
Um how finance happens and um you know
like this is 15 to 20 years ago before
Solana was even an idea, I was
having fun trying to build trading
systems, trading bots, trading on like
interactive brokers on traditional
finance rails.
And um you're kind of when you do that
you learn that you're kind of trading
with a black box. You don't know how any
of the stuff actually works. What
happens to your order, how it actually
ends up from when you submit it to a
broker to being filled on an exchange in
an order book.
And the cool thing about Solana is you
have
all the validator source code. You can
run your own validator. You can get
stakes. You can even participate in the
block creation process. And you have
full control over that entire pipeline.
So you know exactly
why things can go wrong. And many things
can go wrong, but it's important to me
as an engineer to understand
why stuff can break and then have the
ability to fix it or you know adjust my
strategy.
Yeah, I think that was kind of one of
the reasons I got into crypto too. It's
just you have everything that's
permissionless and borderless and you
have the ability to see the code and
interact directly with it. And that kind
of jumps into one of the other questions
that I had and that was that you have
talked a lot about your own frustrations
in traditional markets. Like watching
large institutions always have edge. You
have co-location and order flow and just
knowing the right people it puts you
ahead of just anyone else that's
trading. So you made a bet early on that
a single global state machine was the
answer. You have like on-chain
borderless permissionless with full
transparency. But one thing that has
kind of been a topic of discussion was
on Solana you have the block leader that
has a temporary monopoly and that means
the playing field isn't super even. But
now we have constellation or multiple
concurrent proposers that just came out
and I wanted to hear your thoughts more
on that. So you're removing the last
unfair advantage here. To me it's more
than that. We can actually beat
traditional finance. So if you kind of
get into the the last mile of how this
stuff happens and you think of it from a
physics as a physics problem, you have a
bunch of information that's happen
that's happening around the world that's
relevant to markets. And the example
that I always use is like you're sitting
in Singapore in your high-rise, you
know, hotel room
and you see like a ship full of iPhones
sink out of the harbor. That information
is really important to markets and it's
important to the company Apple.
And that that app but that Apple stock
is trading in New York. And there's a
physical latency to get that information
from when you see it to the stock market
in New York. So that news wire has to
propagate as fast as possible, speed of
light or fiber even go through like
lower earth orbit to get to the New York
Stock Exchange for trader to then add it
to their risk engine, to their model to
produce a trade to get into the order
book.
If you have multiple concurrent
proposers, um
the idea there is that we don't have to
be located in New York. We could
actually be at the same time located in
New York and Singapore and have at the
same time exceptions actions that are
accepted in the same we call it economic
tick. So in the same short kind of batch
of time that is universally applied
around the around the world.
So by the time that news wire eventually
ends up in New York and a trader's
looking at Bloomberg terminal, the price
on Solana is already reflected it.
Because somebody placed that order
immediately in Singapore. It didn't have
to go all the way to New York first to
place the order. So
decentralized systems actually can
completely beat traditional finance.
This is I think the cool part about
this. This is this isn't us just trying
to work around
problem with Byzantine fault tolerance
and kind of all the all the stuff that's
been holding us back building these open
systems where nobody controls anything.
Which make it much more difficult. You
have to solve a lot more problems than a
centralized provider. But I think
because we have to innovate and think of
these problems from first principles, we
have a chance to really solve them
in a way that's even better than
traditional finance could ever
accomplish.
Yeah, definitely. And
I'm curious what mark mixed with
multiple concurrent proposers and then
you have the updates with Fire Dancer
going live and Alpenglow also coming
live. All three of those, do you think
that's going to bring Solana to the
vision that you have or do you think
there's still more work to do to get to
this kind of NASDAQ on-chain vision that
you have for the future? I think for
my vision has been that Solana never is
frozen. Is that it's like Linux. Yeah.
>> Is is hardware changes,
things change, you know, the internet's
switching from fiber to lower earth
orbit is going to have impact on how
Solana should be constructed and
that means that I want people to go
change the code and make it better. And
always think about how do we reshape the
network to fit the best possible
hardware. The joke that I always had was
that we care so much about latency that
eventually we'll build neutrino-based
internet that goes through the center of
the earth. If we have to do that, we'll
do it, you know, and that's maybe like
maybe that'll happen after we have
quantum computers designing materials
for this.
But uh
that's the dream is like build a system
that is so fast that we actually change
the internet.
Yeah, that would be really cool. Um
and I'm curious too cuz you're talking
about where the future of finance now.
Um one thing just to give some
background for people that are watching
that are are new to crypto. Just in
traditional finance you have stock
markets that close at 4:00 p.m.
Settlements take two days and your
capital sits idle on the nights,
weekends and holidays, but Solana runs
24/7, near instant finality. For a
traditional trader that's
a fundamental change in how capital
efficiency works. So
where do you see this heading and what
do you think the actual mechanics of a
trading desk is going to look like in 10
years? I think um
a lot of trading desks probably have
already adopted because they trade
across a bunch of different venues. Mhm.
But this where you know, people trade in
Japan and London and New York and all of
those overlap effectively a full day.
But even those traditional financial
firms are now going to 24/7.
And crypto's always been 24/7. I think
you basically have the rest of the world
coming online into like what what crypto
is disrupting I think isn't so much
traditional finance. It's that it's
bringing
online the rest of the world into the
same level as TradFi has had over the
last 20 20 years.
And the rest of the world is bigger and
growing faster and will eventually I
think
become finance. Like we're going to stop
calling it there's not going to be a
difference between DeFi and finance.
We'll just call it all finance. Yeah.
I see that. So do you think
do you see that mathematically changing
like the return profile of a trading
strategy with all of that combining into
just 24/7 markets? None of my strategies
ever made any money.
>> [laughter]
>> Neither.
So I'm an engineer. I can tell I can
analyze and and give you like
performance numbers and make something
faster, but I think
uh it takes a very different skill set.
You probably need a team, a combination
of maybe engineers like me and and
quants and stuff to to make it to be
successful in that space.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Now I kind of want to dive more into
like the technical side of things. Um So
we briefly touched on Fire Dancer and
Alpenglow. But those are two pretty
important advancements for Solana today.
And Alpenglow is built by very
professional researchers from Esoteric
and then Fire Dancer by Jump Trading. So
you have this renowned HFT firm deciding
to build infrastructure for Solana
rather than competing against it. And
you have some of the brightest minds in
cryptography writing a new consensus
that brings your block finality to about
150 milliseconds. So, what does that
signal to you about where traditional
finance is moving?
Well,
I think again, Solana
my my dream is that it's like Linux,
that it's open source, open
uh protocols for anyone to participate.
And a lot of adoption in Linux gained
from big tech companies, Intel, Google,
Qualcomm, um because they saw not the
need to build a competitive operating
system and to compete with Linux, but
the benefit of using a common standard
and get it all collaborating and working
together and eliminating a lot of the
pitfalls and attack factors and security
threats um from doing that work
separately, like all all on their own.
And I think if you're going to have a a
global financial layer, you kind of need
that requirement. You need to be able to
allow everyone in finance to participate
in the system and to understand
how
um things that matter to them
financially, um how those work on a
technical level. So, they can have the
trust to know that they're not getting a
bad price or a bad fill or uh somebody
has an unfair advantage over them. A lot
of finance is really all about fairness.
And you know, a lot of law in finance is
about encoding that fairness and
eliminating, you know, fraud and things
like that. And open source protocols
just increase transparency and improve
fairness. Um so, I think this is our
advantage over
like a centralized system where they
built their own internal stack and they,
you know, invite Jump to trade there and
everything, but
the difference here is that Jump and
their competitors all can share the same
source code and all trust the markets
that they're operating in and
all can verify that Jump does not have a
fair advantage over Citadel or whoever
else.
Yeah.
>> I think that's that's ultimately kind of
our
our biggest advantage is
that we're
don't have any
any way to really control any part of
the stack and cause one entity to have
an advantage over another one.
Yeah. So, just leveling the playing
field. And you mentioned two things that
I want to talk more on. The first thing
was um this global financial
infrastructure. So, one thing that a lot
of people new to crypto and Solana in
general, um don't realize is that there
are tokenized funds, equities, and
commodities on Solana. And just in the
last quarter, I believe Solana processed
$1.1 trillion in volume. So, there is a
lot of liquidity depth as well as
tokenizing real-world assets. Um so,
I guess
what do you think still needs to be
built to
fully get this
working? Um to have
everyone be able to use this and and
understand that it's available.
I mean, the like we're already there.
The the thing is like the
what needs to happen is
um
I would say more like of a mental change
in people's behaviors. Like a lot of
technology shifts are happen faster on
the engineering or technology side than
it takes the human mind to adopt. Like
people had to learn how to use a
keyboard. That was not a a thing. And I
don't know if you remember
going to school if you had like typing
class, like because it's just not a
skill that everyone grew up with.
Um people didn't understand web links.
The idea of the web was a whole new idea
that took time for people to like
actually adopt and form. And people that
grew up with in the in a
environment now after AI exists
are going to just assume that it was
always there and like naturally be able
to interact with it versus somebody that
is experiencing as a new technology. So,
adoption curves are all kind of limited
by I would say the human human's
understanding what they're dealing with.
Um
I think with finance, there's such a
incentive to make money that people are
willing to overcome the adoption
barriers and go learn it and and figure
out how to use it. Um so, that's the
advantage. Um
and
the pace of how it's happening, I think,
is both
like surprised me how fast some things
happen, like getting the genius act and
I don't know, we're getting to what,
close to 400 billion of stable coins
issued, and how slow in in terms of like
getting the regulators to kind of
understand that
a lot of the intermediaries that they
created to deal with problems, you know,
from the 19th century railroad stock
boom,
just no longer apply in crypto because
we have cryptography to fully validate,
you know, ownership and just go apply
trust and all these other things. Um so,
it takes time and regulators are
typically
uh
the silver-haired professionals. They,
you know, they go through the industry,
they become best in class in their
industry,
and they're almost on the verge of
retiring before they become a regulator.
Yeah.
>> the industry at that at that state and
they have so much experience that
adopting new technologies is they're
usually the last to do it. Um so, it's
going to take time for us to get through
that like hump um across all the major
regulatory environments in the world.
And and it's not just United States,
it's like everywhere in the world.
Yeah, definitely adopting new technology
like takes time. Um but for people that
are learning and trying to make that
like mental model shift, like what
advice would you have for them to just
kind of speed it up and and understand
things a bit quicker?
Um get a set up self-custody wallet.
Like I think truly try to understand the
risks.
Lose lose a
uh lose a custody wallet. And lose it.
Oh, [laughter] no.
Yeah.
Set one up with uh
enough to where the loss hurts, but not
that it like hurts too much to where
you'll remember the mistakes that you
made. So, take a little bit of of risk
to learn this technology. And geek out
and understand like on how to actually
make it secure. Like you would on like
coffee or sourdough or whatever. I think
that that's kind of become the expert of
this. I think that that's really kind of
what I would recommend. Um and you can
do it as a hobbyist, you can take a lot
more risk actually than a bank or a
professional, but
um
once you understand that, I think you'll
both see the power of it and
kind of the the scary parts of
like
trusting cryptography only and not
having like intermediaries that you rely
on. Um
both of those, I think, are, you know,
empowering and and sobering.
You see hacks and things like that
happen because
even professionals make mistakes. And if
you really really like try to understand
all the attack factors,
you'll understand both the power and the
and how hard it is to get this this
technology fully adopted globally.
Yeah, I love that advice. I actually
accidentally pushed my private keys to
GitHub once and there was a bot that
immediately drained my wallet the second
I pushed it and I've now learned my
lesson and and have done all the
research on security. [laughter]
And when somebody tells you you should
have a separate dedicated computer only
for signing, you can understand why,
right? You immediately understand, "Oh,
this solves all these possible
risks that I that could I I could
accidentally screw up, right?" Yeah,
exactly. [laughter]
Realized the hard way. Yep.
Yeah. Now, you mentioned earlier
fairness, um and I just want to go back
to that. So, I had one question that's a
bit controversial, but that's around
MEV. So, some people see it as
predatory, others see it as legitimate
arbitrage that improves market
efficiency. So, for people coming from
traditional finance, the equivalent
exists, but it's either regulated away
or it's reserved for the largest
institutions. So, do you think MEV is
good or bad for Solana?
So, these are just kind of inherent
parts of the system and it's neither
good or bad.
Um because the the function that these
systems provide is like a fair market.
And it's easy to say that, but if you
think of it like
you have an auction house,
like a physical auction house, it can
physically fit only so many people.
So, if you want to place a bid, if you
want to call it a fair auction house, it
would have to be infinitely sized to
allow everybody to be able to go in and
place a bid. And the time that it takes
to place a bid would have to be
infinitely long because that would be
unfair to block somebody, right? Like a
second before they actually went in. So,
as soon as you start thinking about the
real world,
it is impossible to build a system that
is
fair from without any kind of limits.
So, as soon as you start adding limits,
somebody's excluded, somebody's
included. And you have to design these
systems in a way that it's transparent
why somebody's included or excluded. And
everyone has a shot of being included.
And in a regulated environment, they try
to do this with um regulation and laws
and stuff like that, but ultimately
you end up with uh a lot of captured
systems where you have exchanges that
make a certain amount of money, but not
too much. You have big market makers
that make a certain amount of money, but
if they make too much, the regulators
start like, "Oh, what are you doing?
This is probably something not right."
>> [laughter]
>> And
uh in a open permissionless system, you
have protocols and people find exploits
or corner cases in the protocol and then
they start exploiting them.
And this is where an open system can
self-correct because everything's
observable. You can observe MEV, and we
can as an industry decide what is good
MEV and what is bad MEV. I don't know
that, but businesses do. They see where
their users are getting hurt to the
point that they turn away, but they can
also sometimes see that there's more
liquidity on chain that allows their
users to trade at at a better price.
And
that could be because somebody that is
doing MEV is bringing more liquidity
simply because they want their market to
be accessed more. Um so, again, all
these things are dynamic, and it's up to
that business and front end to be able
to decide what is a good market, what is
a bad market, and the job of the
protocol is to simply allow that
business to be selective. We want
ultimately like where the protocol fails
is if you run a company on Solana and
you have no choice but to be forced to
use a particular market where you know
you're going to get a bad price.
So, to me, that means that the protocol
has failed. If the protocol gives you
optionality, use this market or another
one or this proposer or another
proposer, and you can go and look at the
data and decide this is the best one
that I'm getting, and I can exclude the
bad one, that's great. That means we
have a contestable market. People can go
and decide which auction house to go
into, and we will effectively converge
on better pricing than the regulated
path where you don't have contestable
markets, and things kind of get
entrenched, and you have to kind of the
feedback loop is basically much, much
slower in the regulated side. Um
what we want is
to identify places where somebody
somehow has a
uncontestable monopoly, and then we I
see that as a protocol failure.
If somebody has an edge, and I don't
have to use them, that's great. Like,
let them have that edge, let them figure
out how to make it or break it, you
know, in in this open environment. But
if I don't have to use them, then it's
not my problem, right? Like, I think ev-
everyone that's building an application
can kind of make that choice on their
own.
So, would you say that like MEV would
give
a unique opportunity to traders that
like you don't really have in
traditional finance?
Where MEV hurts users is
if they don't understand like the cost
of it. Like, they they
their applic- like, usually um
users are rarely interacting with it
directly. You have applications and
wallets that set the slippage uh and all
these other things, and they surface
like this is the price that is being
offered, and you're very likely to get
this price, but the worst-case price
you're going to get is is this.
And when that's not surfaced to the user
when the application fails to do a good
job doing that, you end up with bad
outcomes. Because then the user like is
accidentally like sets their slippage to
20%, and they submit to a market that
takes max slippage, and then they get uh
they're surprised, "Why am I getting
this 20% or something like that?" Um
So,
finance is complicated, and when people
like try to like, "Why doesn't it just
all work perfectly?" Think of it as an
auction house, and you have something
that is so hot that there's a line to
get into the auction house that is now
packed, and now you're trying to get
into it.
And what happens if somebody just starts
beating up everyone in line to get
>> [laughter]
>> to get to the front of the door.
Right?
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah.
So, as a the protocol's job is to make
it obvious that there's a line, that the
house is packed, and to prevent anyone
from beating up to get ahead in the
line, and to make that a fair the the
whole process fair. This is like the the
really, really hard part.
Um
Yeah, that's a great analogy. I love
that.
Um [laughter]
so, we're almost at time, so I have one
more question left. Um you're an
engineer, and I think a lot of people
that are engineers that are a little
curious on crypto and blockchain,
there's this misconception that there
isn't a lot of cool tech happening. Um
so, what advice do you have for
developers, and what do you think is the
most
interesting thing to get them interested
in wanting to dive into the land of
crypto and Solana?
So, to me, this is one of the most
fascinating and interesting problems to
work on because
all the fun technology problems like
just butt into physics.
So, the problems we're dealing with in
terms of like how fast can you
synchronize the these like auction
parameters and the state all around the
world is a physics problem. And how do
you do it in a way that we can guarantee
that nobody can attack the system like
for Byzantine fault tolerance is like
one of the hardest problems in computer
science. So, if you really, really get
into it and get into markets and
microstructure and MEV, uh you are
fighting physics, and what what better
thing can you possibly work on? I think
this is why like
AI is fascinating because you're
fighting physics there, too. So,
um the uh
between finance and AI, I don't I mean,
these are the the top two things to work
on.
Yeah, I agree. Um I've been in the space
for a while now, and the more I'm here,
the more I realize there's so much to
learn, and we're just at the forefront
of just innovation and technology. So,
it's really cool.
Yeah, it never ends. I mean, it's it's
>> [laughter]
>> The more you learn, the more you realize
you don't know anything.
>> Yeah.
So, [laughter]
awesome. Well, thanks so much for coming
to chat, and I all of this is amazing
insight, and I hope it helps a lot of
people want to start learning. So, I
appreciate it. Thank you.
>> Thanks for having me. Yeah, thank you.