In a shocking turn of events, that
absolutely nobody saw coming, except for
literally everyone, Anthropic just
dropped what might be their most
game-changing tool since Claude Code,
Claude Design, a new Opus 4.7 powered
platform that turns your half-baked
Figma designs into actual prototypes,
pitch decks, and production-ready UIs
without the need to ever open a single
design tool. The Figma stock dropped 7%
within hours of the announcement.
Longtime Adobe executives are just
giving up and jumping out of high-rise
windows. Every AI design startup just
lost funding, and LinkedIn could barely
keep its servers running because every
junior UI designer was forced to do what
every programmer had to do in 2023,
update their job title to prompt
engineer. In today's video, we'll look
at all the crazy things Claude Design
can do and find out if this is the final
nail in the coffin for human-led UI/UX
design. It is April 21st, 2026, and
you're watching The Code Report. Claude
Design is built on Anthropic's brand-new
flagship model, Opus 4.7, which was just
released last week, and is allegedly
more tasteful and creative than its
predecessor, which is just corporate
speak for we finally taught it that not
everything needs a purple gradient. The
new model can now see images at 3.75
megapixels, which is huge for design
work because it can now understand
images up to 2,576
pixels on the long edge. Then, for
programming, it hit 87.6%
on the software engineering benchmark,
which crushes Opus 4.6, but still falls
behind the mysterious Mythos model.
Despite these impressive trust-me-bro
benchmark results, a pretty loud group
of people on the internet are not happy
and say Opus 4.7 is actually a
regression. There's even a conspiracy
theory that they intentionally nerfed
4.6 over the last few months to make 4.7
feel smarter on the release date. Now,
even though I believe in every
conspiracy I've ever heard, I'm not so
sure about this one because these demos
are straight-up off the chain. As
similar to Google Stitch, which I made a
a about a few weeks ago, The design can
easily put together a basic UI for you,
but when it comes to interactivity,
Claude pulls way ahead. You notice all
these demos are fully interactive.
They've got working animations out of
the box, and we can tweak all these
sliders to get different results. In
addition, it can give you a bunch of
variations about how an animation should
actually look. Like you might try out a
bunch of different animations for a chat
app, or you could have it slop out 100
different loading spinners to choose the
one that fits best for your next failed
side project. It can also produce these
crazy futuristic animations by doing
something that terrifies every web
developer. And that, of course, is
working with shaders. And this thing
might even make video editors obsolete
because it can even produce full-length
video animations over a minute long.
Impressive, but the problem is that
these are all cherry-picked pre-built
demos. Let's find out if Claude design
is actually good by building something
ourselves. Before you start building
something, though, you might already
have your own design system in place.
And like Google Stitch, you can upload a
design system, which will force it to
maintain consistency between designs.
The cool thing about Claude is that you
can upload that design system by linking
a GitHub repo, or you can even upload a
Figma file directly. And that's actually
awesome if you're a designer because in
theory, it means you only have to design
a couple screens, then give Claude your
Figma file, and it designs the other 100
screens for you. Now, I actually have my
design system already set up as a PDF
file, which I'll go ahead and upload.
Then I'll prompt Claude to build us an
iOS onboarding flow for Horse Tinder.
And now we just wait, and wait, and
wait, and wait. Opus 4.7 is a lot slower
than Google Stitch, Code X, or Cursor
Composer, but at least it's still a
thousand times faster than a human. But
eventually, it brings us to this canvas
with five beautifully designed screens.
Now, beautiful might be a bit of an
exaggeration here, but it is a good
starting point. One issue, though, is
that it didn't use my design system,
even though it's recognized here in the
chat output. It looks a lot more
Claude-y than Fire Ship-y. We can just
ignore that, though, because another
issue is that the Horse Tinder logo is
all washed out. Well, another nice
feature in Claude design is that we can
actually draw and comment on this
canvas. Like, I can just draw an arrow
directly to this crappy logo and then
either comment it or just add a new
prompt to fix it. Then 5 to 10 minutes
later, it's magically fixed. Well,
actually, wait a minute. It appears it
didn't fix it. It just changed the
background color a little bit. That's
too bad and I guess we'll have to wait
for Opus 4.8 to come out before we can
finally finish Horse Tender. But the one
thing we can continue working on is the
back end using awesome tools like Google
Cloud Run, the sponsor of today's video.
It's a fully managed serverless platform
that lets you run code on Google's
world-class infrastructure with zero
overhead. You can use any language or
framework to run front-end and back-end
services, batch jobs, or even host
fine-tuned LLMs with GPUs, then deploy
straight from your terminal or Cloud
Code with a single command or set up
continuous deployment from GitHub. You
can also use Google AI Studio as a
full-stack development environment where
you can vibe code a complete React or
Node.js app, then deploy to Cloud Run
with a single click. The best part is
that it scales to zero. So, idle
projects don't cost you anything and it
auto scales to handle traffic spikes
without any manual intervention. It also
gives you 2 million free requests per
month, so go try it out for free today
at cloud.run. This has been the Code
Report. Thanks for watching and I will
see you in the next one.