SpaceX IPO or initial public offering is
targeted for the middle of this year.
So, what this means is that the company
is selling its shares to the public for
the very first time at a valuation of
1.75 to 2 trillion dollars. That's the
biggest IPO in the history of the world.
Out of 100% of the shares being offered,
66% of the shares are what we call
primary shares or new shares, which
means the company will issue the new
shares and the money that you pay for
it, it will go into the company. So,
this 50 billion dollars will go into the
company. But, 33% of the shares that are
being offered are called vendor shares.
Vendor shares means that these are
shares owned by insiders, by employees.
So, in other words, when you buy these
shares, your money doesn't go to the
company, your money goes to the insiders
and shareholders that are getting out of
the business. So, 25 billion dollars
will go to insiders and management who
are getting out and 50 billion will go
to the company itself. Now, out of all
the shares being offered, about 22.5
billion of this amount will be reserved
for retail investors and not
institutional investors. And this is
three times higher than most major IPOs.
Because most major IPOs, they only offer
10% to retail investors. But for SpaceX,
they're offering a triple that amount.
So, is it because Elon Musk and the
management loves retail investors? They
want to give you a chance to own the
company? Or is it because they can't
find enough institutional investors to
buy, so they want to kind of like dump
it on the retail investors who are not
so sophisticated? Well, something to
think about.