Yesterday, I was looking at my GitHub
feed and realized it was 90% AI agents
reviewing other AI agents pull requests.
My for you page is just six rappers
around the same Claude API key, and all
the most starred repos are literally
just markdown files that tell you how to
talk to robots. I thought I had died and
went to hell, but I realized this can't
be hell because this is my terminal
emulator. It's 3D, it uses 300 megabytes
of RAM, it has a spinning rat for a
cursor, and it might be the most
important software released in 2026.
Underneath the AI sewage layer and below
the prompt bros and notion template
goblins, there are still real humans
building insane, beautiful, and deeply
unnecessary software. In today's video,
we'll look at 10 projects you've never
heard of built by people who absolutely
should not be allowed near a compiler,
and I mean that as the highest possible
compliment. It is May 26, 2026, and
you're watching The Code Report. The
first project I want to talk about is
Ratty. It's a new terminal emulator
built in Rust and inspired by TempleOS.
And as you can see here, the cursor is a
spinning 3D rat. It was created by
Warren Parmacksis, and unlike most
terminal emulators, it doesn't just
render text, but rather an entire
GPU-accelerated 3D scene using the Bevy
game engine. That means you can do
incredibly useless things like hit
control-alt-enter to physically tilt
your terminal in a 3D space like you're
flying through a PS2 game. And you can
even bring in your own crappy 3D models
from tools like Blender. The only catch
is that it eats 300 megabytes of RAM,
and RAM is not cheap these days. The
creator fully acknowledges that this is
insane by saying, "Quote, everything
comes at a cost, especially the spinning
rat cursor." But if 3D rats are not
enough, your terminal's about to get
even more awesomer thanks to a project
called Terminal Phone. Imagine this,
you're in the terminal, Vim open three
tmux panes deep, and instead of
unlocking your phone to take a call, you
just make the call from bash. The
Terminal Phone is an open-source
push-to-talk voice and text app that
runs entirely over Tor as a shell
script. There are no servers, no
accounts, no phone numbers. Instead, a
.onion address is your identity, which
means everything is ephemeral and
end-to-end encrypted. The developer
shipped this project in February with a
custom protocol built from scratch. This
is the project cypherpunks were
promising us in 1995, and now finally,
after 30 years, one psychopath finally
delivered it. But this next project
might even be more rebellious. Back in
1988, before the internet even existed,
John Carpenter made an awesome movie
where this dude puts on sun glasses and
suddenly every billboard, magazine, and
advertisement on Earth is revealed to be
what it truly is, alien mind control
propaganda telling us to obey, consume,
marry, and reproduce. Developer David
Lawrence realized that this is also the
most aesthetically correct way to
implement an ad blocker. He actually had
the idea all the way back in 2015, sat
on it for a decade, and then finally
shipped it recently as a fork of uBlock
Origin Light. Instead of just blocking
ads, it turns the entire experience of
surfing the World Wide Web into an 80s
sci-fi horror movie. But our next
project, CUDA Oxide, didn't come from
some basement hacker. It was quietly
dropped on GitHub by the five trillion
market cap Nvidia last week, and it
addresses an important problem. In order
to write CUDA kernels, code that runs on
a GPU, you need to carefully craft C++,
and pray the compiler doesn't segfault
because it only takes one wrong pointer
to turn your $40,000 GPU cluster into a
worthless paperweight. CUDA Oxide tries
to fix this by letting you write GPU
kernels in pure Rust. Just annotate a
function with kernel, and now you have
Rust code that can actually run on a
GPU, and it actually compiles straight
to PTX. There's no foreign functions
interface or C++ involved at all. But
all these awesome projects should have
their own theme songs, and that's where
Wario Synth comes in. This is a weird
project where you paste in a song and it
spits it back out as a Game Boy
chiptune.
Under the hood, it uses the Web audio
API to take two pulse waves, one wave
channel, and one noise channel to
resynthesize an entire song as something
that sounds like it's coming out of a
1989 Game Boy. And it can do all of this
in the browser with zero server-side
processing required. Enjoy it before
Nintendo's legal team nukes it and
memory holes it. But speaking of memory
holes, I completely forgot about the
Epstein files after the Iran war and UFO
disclosures. Luckily though, the files
are easier than ever to consume now
thanks to projects like J Mail, which
emulates Gmail as if you were Jeffrey
himself using it. But if you truly want
to go deep down this rabbit hole,
Epstein Exposed provides a searchable
database for the files and also this
awesome network graph that shows you how
deep the connections of the deep state
actually go. If that's a little too dark
for you though, you'll really like this
next project, Xpedia. Developer Lea
Rebain looked at the dumpster fire
that's modern social media and asked the
only sensible question, "What if
doomscrolling was actually good for
you?" And so she built Wikipedia as a
TikTok feed. You open up the web app,
pick a few categories, and it downloads
40 megabytes of simple Wikipedia in the
background, and then you have an
infinite feed you can scroll through
endlessly. This project is also open
source and runs its algorithm entirely
in the browser. But what if we could run
an entire computer in the browser? Well,
that's where Pyrite comes in. It's a
project you can self-host, or if you go
to pyrite.com, you'll be taken to a
desktop environment where you have a
taskbar, draggable windows, a file
manager, and a bunch of applications
like a notepad, code editor, terminal,
and so on. It's kind of like the dream
of Chrome OS, except it's actually free,
actually open, and actually fun. But now
it's time to learn about Honker. This
one's for the SQL Lite gang, and
honestly, it might be the single most
underrated project on this list. A SQL
Lite is an incredible database that can
handle even the most ambitious of failed
side projects. But if you end up needing
a feature like a job queue, things start
to get complicated. You might think you
need to spin up Redis, install Celery,
or run a message broker, but developer
Russell Romney says no. Honker is a
SQLite extension written in Rust that
adds Postgres-style notify listen
directly into your database file. You
get durable pub/sub, task queues, event
streams, and a cron scheduler. And all
of it lives inside the same .db file as
your business data. It's yet another
humble reminder that 99% of us don't
need Kubernetes
and would be perfectly fine running
SQLite in node on a $5 VPS. And that
brings us to number 10, Hyperagent, the
sponsor of today's video. Most agent
platforms only give you tool calls, but
Hyperagent lets you build and deploy
agents with their own browser, shell,
and file system, all running in an
isolated cloud sandbox. I used it to
build a research workflow for our Bytes
newsletter that studies past issues,
scouts Tech Twitter and Hacker News for
promising story topics, and saves them
to our team's airtable. Then I turn that
workflow into an agent we can invoke
from Telegram or Slack whenever we need
ideas. Right now, Hyperagent is giving
away $10 million to founders building
agent-first companies, and the first
thousand viewers to use the link below
will get $1,000 in free inference
credits. This has been The Code Report.
Thanks for watching, and I will see you
in the next one.