Earlier this week, Dario and the
Anthropic team pulled the ultimate trust
me bro power move when they announced
Mythos, a model so powerful, so capable,
so veiny that they claim the fallout for
economies, public safety, and national
security could be severe if it were to
be released to the general public. And
as you can imagine, this has everyone
losing their collective minds again.
>> Something very familiar about all this.
>> Some are saying Mythos may lead to the
entire cybersecurity industry collapsing
under the weight of our new god in a
box.
>> Because the security implications of a
model that is this capable are
terrifying.
>> While others are saying Anthropic is
just repeating the same model release
playbook we've seen countless times
before to scare the slop out of people,
then quietly release a model that can't
even code a spell five to do app. For us
in our parasocial relationship, it's
like a fun game of Russian roulette, but
instead of getting shot in the head, you
have to become a ranch hand and I have
to start teaching tutorials on how to
collect turkey semen so you can deploy
genetic payloads into production hens.
In today's video, we'll break down
Mythos and I'll show you my bulletproof
guide on how to update your software
fast enough that you not get zero dayed,
but slow enough to not get supply chain
attacked. It is April 10th, 2026 and
you're watching The Code Report. I'm
tired, boss, because every time a new
model comes out, it seems to bring on a
new form of mass psychosis. Midjourney
was going to make all human art
obsolete, but now nobody talks about it.
GPT-4o had an entire subreddit feeling
love for the first time. And now Mythos,
without even being publicly available,
has many feeling existential dread for
the first time. And the reason for that
feeling is that during Anthropic's
internal testing, they discovered that
Mythos is basically a zero-day vending
machine. It found a 16-year-old
vulnerability in FFmpeg, which allowed
an attacker to craft a malicious video
file that tricks the decoder into
writing a few bytes of data outside its
allowed memory, potentially crashing the
program and corrupting nearby data. It
was also able to find a 27-year-old bug
in OpenBSD, allowing a remote attacker
to trigger a null pointer write, which
instantly crashes any OpenBSD machine
reachable over TCP. In every major
browser, it was able to run a train on a
few JavaScript engine bugs that lets a
malicious webpage escape the browser
sandbox. In one case, that allowed it to
steal data across websites, and in
another, it was able to write directly
to the operating system's kernel, giving
an attacker full control over the device
the moment the victim opened the
webpage. And my personal favorite, it
found a bug in the Linux kernel which
let it flip a single bit in a
neighboring memory page, which turned
the password executable into a writable
file, which it then overwrote to gain
full root access to the system.
>> I found more bugs in the last
couple [music] of weeks than I found in
the rest of my life combined.
>> And just yesterday, US Treasury
Secretary Scott Bessent and Federal
Reserve Chair Jerome Money Printer
Powell has set up an urgent meeting with
bank CEOs to warn of the security
dangers posed by Mythos. So, it's no
wonder that Dario is pulling inspiration
from House Harkonnen and locking down
control of the spice with the
announcement of Project Glasswing, a new
initiative that brings together a
collection of companies that happen to
pay Anthropic a lot of money in an
effort to secure the world's most
critical software via access to Mythos.
The idea is that Mythos is too dangerous
for a default config NPC like you to
have, but perfectly safe in the hands of
a dozen trillion-dollar companies and a
bank. Anthropic's plan is that the
fellowship will quickly patch all of the
world's software before anyone else
builds a model this capable, which, if
it's up to Sinister Sam, now that Open
AI is no longer acting as the fluffer of
slop gen AI videos, will hopefully be
any day now. But, not everyone is
convinced that Mythos is that capable.
Anthropic has been using Mythos
internally since February 24th, and
since then, they leaked Claude code
source code, leaked documents revealing
the existence of Mythos, and have had a
very rough time even keeping their APIs
online. On top of that, the way Mythos
actually found these exploits is a
little sus. Like, the OpenBSD
vulnerability came out of 1000 parallel
agent runs across the code base at
costing nearly $20,000 in compute. If
you use the same process with Opus 4.6
or GPT 5.4 Pro, you'd probably find
plenty of issues as well. And the
Firefox numbers are doing something
similar. One of the claims is that
Mythos had an 84% success rate at
writing working exploits in Firefox,
which is a massive jump over Opus 4.6's
15%. But that number isn't against
actual Firefox. It's against a
SpiderMonkey shell with the process sand
box and other mitigations turned off. So
that begs the question, is Mythos going
to destroy the world? Well, in my expert
opinion, it almost certainly will not.
But is Mythos a real step up from
Anthropic's current flagship model Opus
4.6? Probably yes. Either way, we'll
just have to take their word for it
because
>> It's a big club
and you ain't in it.
>> But if you want to try an amazing tool
that you can actually use today, you
should check out BrowserBase, the
sponsor of today's video. It's a
complete platform for building and
deploying browser agents where a single
API key it gives your agent access to
cloud browsers, web search, and
everything else it needs to access the
web like a real human being. This lets
your agents perform more complex jobs
like filling out forms and extracting
unstructured data. And it's built in
tandem with StageHand, their popular
open-source SDK for browser agents. They
also partnered with Cloudflare on an
open-source protocol called WebBot Auth,
which lets your agents prove they're
legit so they can access any website
without pretending to be human. Teams at
Microsoft, Lovable, Ramp, and many
others are already using it to build
thousands of browser agents. And you can
try it out for free using the link
below. This has been the Code Report.
Thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next one.