Have you been waiting on the sidelines
with all your cash waiting for the next
big stock market crash that you've been
promised? Well, I got news for you. It's
already happened.
The US stock market is at an all-time
high again and it keeps going up despite
the ongoing war in Iran, despite
tariffs, despite inflation coming back,
despite the Federal Reserve not cutting
interest rates, despite higher oil. Why?
Why does it keep going up? For one very
simple reason. Earnings. Remember that
ultimately stocks are businesses and as
long as the businesses make more money,
they are worth more. Now, coming into
this earning season, analysts expected
that the S&P 500 companies collectively
would grow their earnings at 15%.
They were dead wrong. So far right now
for quarter one earning season, the
collective earnings of the S&P companies
are coming in at a 27.1%
growth rate. That is the main reason why
the market has rebounded so strongly and
a lot of people are in disbelief. How
can it be?
It be because of earnings and companies'
profit margins are at the 15-year high.
Simple reason. But here's the thing.
Every time the market makes new highs,
you always get the prophets of dooms
telling you that the next big crash is
coming. It's right around the corner,
all right? So just April this year,
you've got Harry Dent saying that how
the everything bubble will finally
burst. And then also in on the 2nd of
May a few days ago, top economist Gary
Shilling says a recession and a deep
stock market plunge are likely by the
end of the year. Oh, by the way, before
you listen to any of the prophets of
doom, please remember that they say this
almost every year. If you look at Harry
Dent, for example, these were all the
times he said the market was going to
collapse, you know, and he first said it
in 2008. By the way, he said it in 2008
and he said the crash was going to
happen
at the end of 2009.
But, by March 2009, the great financial
crisis bottomed and the S&P began one of
the longest bull runs in history. It was
like a 9-year bull run. And if you
listen to him, you would have missed on
a 9-year bull run. He said the market
would crash in 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014,
2015, 2016, 2017.
Every year, they say the big crash is
coming. And you know what? A broken
clock is right
twice a day. And sure enough, if you
look during this entire period, yeah,
did the market crash? Yeah, of course it
crashed, right? Crashed a couple of
times. It crashed here, it crashed here,
it crashed here, it crashed here, it
crashed here, it crashed here, it
crashed here.
But, if you stayed invested, it would
have compounded your wealth by 790%
over the last 16 years. You'd be well on
your way of retiring financially free.
But, the trouble with most retail
investors is that they listen to these
prophets of dooms and what do they do?
They get out of the market here or they
get out of the market here or they get
out of the market here or they stay out
of the market and they sit in cash and
they keep watching the market go higher
and higher and higher and higher and
they're sucking their thumb waiting for
the next crash to get in and they never
get in. And as a result, what happens to
them? As the market goes up through the
ups and downs, the value of their cash
depreciates because of inflation. And
10, 20, 30 years from now, when they
can't work anymore or they don't want to
work anymore, they cannot retire because
their wealth was not able to grow to
beat inflation. And that's why so many
people struggle financially, and the
rich get richer and the poor get poorer.
And they blame the market. They say the
market's rigged. No, the market's not
rigged. Well, in fact, yeah, sorry, the
market is rigged. The market is rigged
in your favor. The market is rigged to
always go up. Why? Because collectively
businesses will always grow their
earnings over time and their value will
always increase. But the trouble with
most people is what? They don't stay
invested or they don't stay in the
markets because they get scared out of
the markets by the prophets of doom.
Now, the bottom line is this, if you are
waiting for the next big crash, I'm here
to tell you that the crash has already
come and gone many times. In fact, if
you look at the last 10 years, in the
last 10 years we had more crashes in 10
years than we do in other 10-year
periods.
So, if you look at the last 10 years for
example, we had a bear market in 2020.
There was COVID-19. I know it sounds
like yesterday, but it was like 7 years
ago, COVID-19. There was a bear market,
there was a recession, the market
dropped 35%. That was a crash. It
happened. It's gone.
And then in 2022, just 2 years later, we
had another bear market where the market
crashed 27%.
And then, just last year in 2025, thanks
to Trump waging tariff war on everyone,
we had another almost bear market. Well,
actually it was a bear market on the
Nasdaq, but the market crashed 20%. So,
that's kind of like three bear markets
in 10 years. That's actually very rare.
Normally you get a bear market every 6
years, but we had close to three bear
markets in the last 10 years.
Now, again, if you had just stayed
invested through the ups and downs and
ignored the news, the prophets of doom,
today, despite these three major
crashes,
uh you would have gained
uh 311%
in terms of your wealth compounding.
Now, if you had added during the crashes
where you bought the dip, you would have
made even more. You have made 4, 5, 600,
700%
in the last 10 years. And for most
people, they would be very close to
financial freedom with that kind of
compounding. Now, the trouble with a lot
of people is that they don't feel
that the last three crashes were actual
crashes. So, I asked them, "Why?" They
said, "Because the last three crashes,
it happened too fast. It went down too
fast. It went up too fast. It's not
counted, right?" So, if you recall, for
example, during COVID, I mean, the
market dropped, but it bottomed within
like 2 months and then recovered within
another 2 months. It's like,
you know, before you knew it, it was
over. And same thing in the 2025
correction, the market dropped in a
month and less than a month, it's back
up again, you know? So, people when they
think of crashes, they're thinking of
Great Depression where it it it it takes
years for the market to crash and years
for it to recover. They're waiting for
that that big crash.
Now, I'm here to tell you that it could
happen, but it's very unlikely that
we're going to get those kind of bear
markets and crashes today because the
entire market structure today is totally
different from the market structure
back then. And let me explain why. So,
first of all, a bit of history.
Um,
So, a lot of people are always fearful
of another Great Depression because,
again, it took very long to recover. You
know, market went nowhere for for many,
many years. So, in 1929, we had, again,
the Great Depression.
And the market dropped
89% in
in total, okay?
Uh, and it took about 3 years for the
market to bottom and many more years to
get back up, you know? So, it's like I
think what, 7 8 years to finally
recover, something like that, you know?
And then in uh we had 2001, 2002, where
we had the dot com crash. The dot com
crash, the market dropped like 48%
and it also took about 2 and 1/2 years
for the market to finally bottom, and
again a couple more years to to get back
to the top. Again, another 5 6 years are
gone, you know? And then we had the
great financial crisis 2008, 2009.
Uh great financial crisis. So, the
market dropped about 57% for that one.
And but it was a bit faster, but still
quite long. It took about 1 and 1/2
years to bottom, and again another
couple of years to recover. Now, if
you're waiting for this, it may not
happen. Why? Because the markets today
are very different from the markets in
the past in terms of market structure.
Let me explain why. In the past, you
found that we had fewer bear markets,
but the bear markets lasted much longer.
But in today's world, we've got many
more bear markets. We've got many more
crashes, but they last very much
shorter. They come and go in months, not
years.
What's the reason? Well, there are a
couple of reasons. The first reason is
because
uh of the Federal Reserve,
the Fed.
So, back during the great financial
crisis, the Federal Reserve didn't have
the tools or they were not proactive to
take action when there was trouble
brewing.
But now you've got the Federal Reserve
that the moment they see, "Oh, the
market's getting in trouble or
something's going to happen." What does
the Fed do? They cut interest rates
aggressively, they buy bonds, they pump
liquidity into the markets, and that's
how they prevent the market from going
down too much. And that's how they get
the markets to recover so much faster.
And that's exactly what happened in
2020. People all thought we were going
through a prolonged depression. They
said that it's it's going to take years
to recover, but market recovered so fast
because the Fed intervened. The Fed
didn't do this in the Great Depression
because the Fed didn't have the tools
and the mandate to do that. During the
dot-com crash, the Fed did cut interest
rates, but they did it very, very
slowly, and they didn't have any
quantitative easing. They didn't
increase the money supply. That's why
the dot-com crash took, again, almost 3
years. Now, the Great Financial Crisis,
the Fed did cut interest rates, they did
do quantitative easing,
uh but they pumped in roughly about $1.2
trillion into the market. So, it still
took time to recover, but again, it was
shorter. But, during COVID,
they cut interest rates to zero within
just a few months, and they pumped in
something like $5 trillion
into the market. So, that's like five
times more than the Great Financial
Crisis, and that's how the market
recovered in just 2 months, all right?
So, in other words, cut a long story
short, today the Fed is your friend.
They will not allow the market to go
down as much as in the past, and do not
stay down for very long. Is it good for
us? Yeah, so the market's rigged
for us, okay? Who stay invested, who
take advantage of these crashes. Now,
that's only one reason. The second and
third reason are very, very important as
well. The second reason is because of
the speed
of information flow.
Okay? And the third, which is related to
the second, is because of high-frequency
trading.
Now, again, in the past, during the
Great Depression, when our parents were
young, information How did people get
information? There was no social media,
there was no internet. You read the
news. It took time for you to hear that
something was wrong with the market,
something wrong with the economy. So,
because information spread very slowly,
people took a long time to react. And
that's why the markets took a long time
to go down and long time to go up
because information was like a snail's
pace. But now, information, if something
happens in the Straits of Hormuz, we
know it 1 second on Twitter, on X, on on
on social media. So, we react instantly,
right? So, because we we can buy and
sell instantly, that's why the markets
move down and move up very fast, not
like the past. The third reason is a big
one. It's because of high-frequency
trading that markets move faster today.
Now, back in 1929, back in 2002, back in
2009,
majority of people who bought and sold
were human beings, not anymore.
Ever since 2011,
today, more than 70% of transactions of
buying and selling are not done by human
beings. They're done by high-frequency
[snorts]
trading robots that buy and sell in
milliseconds. So, these are the robots
that react to news in milliseconds. When
something happens, they sell. Something
happens, they buy. And there's no way
you can compete with these these
high-frequency robots because, you know,
it costs millions and millions of
computing power to run these robots. And
again, because of these robots, it
creates a lot more volatility today than
it did in the past. And that's why
again, when information happens, when
news happens, the market reacts in
milliseconds and recovers in
milliseconds. So, that's another reason
why again,
uh crashes happen more frequently today
and they recover a lot faster. Now, is
that is that good or bad? Well, to me,
it's good because it only means that
I've got a lot more opportunities. In
the old days, it would take a long time
for the bleeding market to crash. Now,
it can crash,
you know, very frequently. But at the
same time, I buy the dip on good
companies, of course, and I get rewarded
very fast as well. The bottom line is
that markets will crash. They crash all
the time. They've crashed many times in
the last 10 years. But if you're always
sitting on the sidelines in cash and you
get scared out of the markets, they'll
you'll lose more money than staying in
the markets. Okay, why? Now remember
that there are always two kinds of risk.
And many people they focus on the first
kind of risk. The first kind of risk is
the risk the risk of being invested.
But there's another risk that people
don't think about, which is the risk
of not being invested.
Which is a worst risk?
I'm here to tell you that this
is the worst risk. Why? Remember that as
investors, what's our ultimate goal? Our
ultimate goal is to compound our wealth
to reach financial freedom. The day
where we can choose not to work anymore.
So how much do you need to be
financially free? You take your annual
expenses multiplied by 25 as a general
rule. So for example, if your expenses
are 100,000 a year, you need 2.5 million
to be financially free. If you spend 200
grand a year, you need 5 billion to be
financially free. So our ultimate aim is
to compound our wealth to reach that
financial freedom number, whether it's
2.5 million or 5 million, right? Okay.
Now,
if you stay invested in the market, is
there a risk?
Yes, but it's a short-term risk.
Long-term, there's no risk if you buy
great companies or stay invested in
index. Why? Because let's say you
invested at the wrong time. Let's say
you were so unlucky that you you went in
there, right? You were invested there.
And after you went in, the market
crashed. OH MY GOD!
But guess what? If you stay invested,
over time your money will keep
compounding and you'll eventually reach
your 2.5 5 million financial freedom. So
short-term, yeah, is risky. Long-term,
you reach your your financial freedom.
Long-term, no risky, right? But, if you
are not invested because you're so
afraid of the crash, because you listen
to all the doomsday prophets of doom,
right? And then, you think, "Okay, the
crash is coming, crash is coming." And
let's say, you know, you get out of the
market here. You're out of the market.
What happens? You know, if you're out of
the market, yeah, the market can go even
lower as you see, "I'm so smart. I'm not
in the market. It goes even lower. Haha,
haha, haha." But, the next thing you
know, the market zooms past and keeps
going up, and you're sucking your thumb
in cash, losing value while the market
goes up. And over time, what's going to
happen? You're not going to reach your
financial freedom. You're going to be
stuck with cash that loses value, and in
the end, you find that you can't afford
anything
when you can't work anymore.
So, see what I'm saying?
The risk of being not invested is the
greatest risk of all. This risk of being
invested only lasts in the short-term.
Over time, that risk dissipates. Now, if
you've not seen this before, I think
this is a great table to explain the
core concept of staying invested. Now,
let's imagine that you invested $2,000
every year into the S&P 500 from your
annual savings, and you did this for 20
years.
And let's imagine that you were Tim. So,
Tim is the perfect market timer. He's
got a relationship with God, right? He's
he's the all-knowing, all-seeing. And
he's able to invest $2,000
every year right at the market bottom.
So, every year, he puts in two grand at
the bottom of the market every year for
20 years.
He ends up compounding the money to
$151,000.
Pretty good. Who Who doesn't want to be
Tim, right? Now, Aaron on the other
hand, cannot time the market. He's got
no idea when's the crash coming. So, he
just invest $2,000
at the start of every year on the first
day of the year. So, he invests
immediately, compounds the money after
20 years,
he winds up with 135 grand. Lower than
Tim, but still not too bad. Now, then
you've got Matt. Matt is someone who
takes the $2,000 a year
to put in the markets, divides it by 12,
and puts in $167
every month. So, that's called dollar
cost averaging, putting the same amount
every single month, doesn't time the
market, market and his wealth compounds
to 134 grand
by the end of 20 years. Pretty close to
Aaron.
Now, Bob is the most unlucky person in
the world, okay? Bob puts in $2,000
every year, but he buys at the market
top every year before the crash.
But at the end of 20 years of
compounding, despite buying at the top
and crash, top and crash, he ends up
with 121 grand. I mean, lower than the
rest, but still, at least, he's beating
inflation. He's compounding his wealth.
Now, Peter, on the other hand, listens
to the doomsday porn stars, and he's so
afraid to be in the market because what
if it crashes? And after the market goes
down, what if it goes even lower, right?
So, he never gets in. He always stays in
cash waiting for the next great
depression that doesn't come, and after
20 years, his 2,000 accumulates to 44
grand.
He keeps saying, "I will invest when it
gets lower."
So, what's the point? The point is that
even if you are the most most unlucky
person in the world, and you buy before
every crash, you will still end up
richer than people who stay out of the
markets.
People always like to ask me, "Adam,
when is the next crash coming?" I
honestly don't know. Could be this year,
could be next year, could be
10 years from now, I don't know. But
it's not important. Why is it It's
important? Because, like I keep saying,
the stock market is the greatest game
that is rigged in favor of you as the
investor. And the only thing you need to
know, the only thing you need to know
about the market going up and down
is this chart. That's the only thing you
need to know. So, this chart shows you
the history of the markets
that in the last 75 years
you had years the market went up, which
were which are all the green years, and
years the market went down, which were
all the red years. And you can see that
in the last 75 years, there were 59 up
years and 16 down years. So, 78% of the
time the market goes up in a year and
21% of the time the market goes down.
Now, let's imagine there's a game where
you can throw a ball into 75 of these
slots, and the ball's going to land in
one of these slots, right? Will you
throw the ball? Yeah, because if you
throw this ball
there's a 78% chance
you're going to have a gain and a 21%
chance you're going to have a loss. I
mean, if you had this game, you played
this game all the time, you get throwing
the ball
every single time. You will not stay out
of the game. People who stay out of the
game are the ones that lose. You stay in
the game, you win.
Now, of course, again, remember, when
people say that, "Hey, there's there's
going to be a big crash coming." Yeah,
it will happen, but what are the odds of
it happening? You always look in terms
of probability, okay?
If you look at the last 75 years
how many years did the market drop 10 to
20% and stay there by the end of the
year? It only happened four times in 75
years. So, the chance of that happening
is 5.3%.
Now, what are the odds of the market
going up 10 to 20% in a year?
Well, it happened a lot more times. In
fact, it happened 24% of the time. So,
it is 4.5 times more likely that this
year the market will go up 10 to 20%
than it will go down 10 to 20%. Now,
could the market drop 20 to 30% this
year like what the prophets of doom say?
No,
>> [laughter]
>> of course it's possible. But in 75
years, it happened only twice in 75
years. So, it's a 2.7% chance of it
happening this year.
But what's the chance that the market
will go up 20 to 30% this year? Well,
it's a 21%
chance of that happening. So, the odds
of this happening versus this is 7.8
times more likely.
So, bottom line, when people ask me,
"Adam, will the market be up or down
this year?"
My answer is most probably up.
By four to seven times more likely than
it being down. And I say this every
single year because these are the odds.
Okay, so take these odds and go and make
your fortune. And may the markets be
with you. If you want to catch my latest
videos, click on the subscribe button
right now. Click on the bell so you get
instant notifications once I upload my
latest video. If you want to check out
my online courses, go to
piranaprofits.com.
We're going to learn how to invest and
how to trade the financial markets and
create an income from all around the
world.
If you want to join my live wealth
academy program, go on to
wealthacademyglobal.com
and find out more about how you can
learn investing and trading live online.
This is Adam Khoo, and may the markets
be with you.