After eight years, we've got a new
Federal Reserve chairman, Kevin Walsh,
and he's been weaponizing AI to slash
interest rates aggressively. So, what
does this mean for the markets? What
does this mean for your portfolio? Let's
find out.
US stock markets continue to make new
highs almost every other week and the
S&P 500 is up over 8% year to date. My
portfolio is doing pretty well after
suffering a bit of a draw down early
part of the year. Uh my portfolio is up
16% year to date. In fact, in the last
month where they say sell in May and go
away, uh the portfolio's up 4.51%
just in the last one month. So what's
the reason markets have been surging?
Well, there are two main reasons. Number
one, corporate earnings. Earnings have
been much stronger than expected. The
second reason why markets are surging
higher is because of the new fat chair
that's just been sworn in, Kevin Walsh.
As you guys know, Chairman Powell has
been the Federal Reserve chairman since
2018 when uh Trump first appointed him
and he's been serving for the last eight
years. But in Trump's second term, as
you know, Trump has been constantly uh
berating him, insulting him, saying that
he's he's a too late. Powell is an
idiot. Why? Because Trump wants power or
wanted power to cut interest rates, but
Powell refused to cut interest rates
because his argument is that if you cut
interest rates, then inflation is going
to come back and we're all going to die.
Uh and that's why Trump has now
appointed Kevin Walsh to take over to do
his bidding. Although he just said, I
want to be independent. Yeah. Right.
Okay. Anyway, so is this a big deal for
markets? I think so. And let me explain
why. So, uh, before Walsh was sworn in,
he's been doing a lot of interviews on
TV and he has been setting up and
framing the public uh for aggressive
interest rate cuts and he has been
arguing for aggressive interest rate
cuts. Now, you may say, how can he cut
interest rates when inflation is still
very high, when the stock market's at
all-time high? Is is he is he crazy?
Well, well, let me explain uh his
argument. So we know that traditionally
uh the Fed policy goes according to when
there's high economic growth. High
growth could create inflation. So the
Fed needs to hold interest rates or
raise interest rates to cool inflation.
So that's the traditional economic
model. Now what Walsh is now saying is
that uh the rules have changed. We're
going to uh have a new policy shift in
the Fed. And his argument is that this
time is different because this time we
have got the AI
revolution, the AI productivity boom
where now companies can produce more
goods with less input with less
employees with less uh resources they
can produce more. So that increases
companies productivity
and that would reduce overheads
drastically for companies reduce
company's cost and hence companies can
eventually price their products lower.
So this would lead to a structural
deflation. He believes that in this new
world the economy can grow very strongly
without inflation and he expects a
structural decline in prices that's
going to come soon. So, might as well
preemptive preemptively cut interest
rates now before prices come down. But
the problem is currently prices have not
yet come down. Currently inflation is
still very sticky. The recent CPI, PPI
coming up uh coming in higher than
expected. But what he's saying is that
but all these inflation indicators are
looking at the past. They're all lagging
indicators. We need to be preemptive. We
need to cut interest rates right now
before prices start coming down. So, if
he really follows through on what he's
saying and he really starts cutting
interest rates really soon, what's going
to happen to the stock market, which
stocks are going to be winners and which
stocks are going to be losers? Well,
let's take a look at what could possibly
happen. So, first of all, who are the
winners? So, if he cuts interest rates
aggressively, growth stocks, especially
tech stocks, are going to be huge
winners, right? Because lower interest
rates plus surging AI profit margins
will be a massive tailwind for these
secular growth companies. So companies
like your usual suspects, right? Your
Nvidia, your Google, your Palanteer,
your Palo Alto, these will continue to
go up like crazy if he cuts interest
rates, but which would could be the
losing stocks. Now, if he cuts interest
rates, but inflation doesn't go down as
fast as he expects and inflation stays
high, then deep cyclical stocks would be
in the danger zone. Now what are deep
cyclical stocks? These are companies in
manufacturing, in logistics, in
transportation, like airlines, like
cruisers, uh consumer stable companies.
They would be in the higher risk
category. Why? Because these companies
might get squeezed by by current energy
and commodity cost. So these companies
have a lot of physical cost, commodity,
energy cost. So these costs go up
because of inflation.
But they are not able to benefit from
the AI productivity benefits as fast. So
their profit margins could be crushed.
So companies like Federal Express, UPS,
uh Delta Airlines, in fact, all the
airlines would be in big trouble, which
I'm wondering why uh Burkshshire
Heatherway just bought Delta Airlines.
Again, I can't understand why. uh Kroger
which is a supermarket chain, Dowo
Chemical, uh automobile manufacturers be
really hard hit especially like Ford and
General Motors the traditional car
makers um you know physical retail
outlets like Target and Carnival Cruise
Lines all this could be negatively
affected by surging inflation.
Now how about bonds? Um as we know
long-term bonds have continued to go
down. If you look at like the TLT which
is the long-term bond ETF, it's been
crashing. Now, if this happens, it's
going to get worse. Okay? So, this would
be actually very bearish for long-term
bonds, especially long-term treasury
bonds with long duration of 8 years or
more. Why? Because if the bond market
thinks that the Federal Reserve is
cutting interest rates too fast into an
energy crisis, into higher inflation,
then long-term yields will continue
spiking. So long-term yields go up mean
long-term bond prices will continue
going down like again TLT. This will
again be very bearish for long-term
bonds. But for short-term bonds and
medium-term bonds which are bonds with
duration of 5 years or less, it is
actually going to be bullish. Why?
Because they will be positioned to
capture the upside of the rate cuts.
Because remember the Fed
cannot control the long end of the
curve. the the Fed doesn't control the
long-term interest rates. The Fed only
controls the short-term interest rates,
the Fed funds rates. So shorter term
bonds like one-year bonds, two-year
bonds, 5year bonds, they are more in
sync with the Fed funds rates. So these
will be positioned to cut capture the
upside of the rate cuts. They will rise
in price, yields will fall uh without
being totally exposed to the longerterm
inflation traps. So as investors, what
does this mean for our portfolios? As we
know, there have been a lot of talk in
the markets that the market is
expensive. It's a bubble. We should stay
out of the market. And of course, we
know that Buffett, of course, he's
retired, but Bert Heatherway is sitting
on 400 billion in cash on the sidelines.
And many people are looking at that and
following that, you know, holding cash
on the sidelines, not daring to go into
the market or getting out of the market.
So in this new scenario with Wash coming
in, what does it mean for these people?
So I have to admit that yes, if you stay
in the market, there is risk. There's
always risk of staying in a market,
especially if you are in stocks that are
very overvalued. But again, like I said,
not all stocks are overvalued. In this
market of all-time highs, there are
stocks that are actually very very
undervalued. And of course, you can find
them easily by doing your research with
like stock oracle, which I use in less
than a few minutes. You can check the
intrinsic value. you can track uh all
these type of stocks and I'll run you
through some examples later on. Okay.
So, like I said, there is a risk of
staying invested in an all-time high
market. But if you ask me with wash
coming in, I think there's even bigger
risk of staying fully in cash. I think
there's an even bigger risk of not being
in the market. And that's why for me I I
stay in the markets. All right? Why? The
reason is now think about it. There are
two scenarios here. Scenario number one
is that Kevin Walsh is right about his
new uh theory, right? So, if he's right
and he comes in and he cuts interest
rates, what's going to happen? Stocks
will go to the moon and inflation will
also come down as he says. Okay. So, in
this scenario, who wins? Everybody wins
because consumers get lower prices. Yay.
the economy grows rapidly and investors
who invest in stocks will build massive
wealth. Everyone wins. That's the first
scenario. But scenario number two, what
if he's wrong? What if Kevin Walsh is
wrong and he cuts interest rates
aggressively but prematurely?
So interest rates come down
but because of the ongoing geopolitical
tensions in Iran because of the high oil
prices inflation
surges up like crazy. So in this
scenario stocks will still go up but
inflation will go up as well. So in this
case who will win? Asset owners. People
who own assets like you own stocks, you
own real estate, you will win because
you will see the asset values pump up
shielding your wealth from inflation
eroding cash. But in this scenario,
anyone sitting on the sidelines in cash
will suffer heavily because your
purchasing power will be wiped out.
So what I'm saying is that in this new
era whichever happens it pays to be an
asset owner. It pays to be invested in
the stock market. Now having said that
of course be careful in in the market.
There are stocks that are extremely
overpriced. There are stocks that are in
a freaking bubble right now. You know
and all people are chasing some of these
these these shiny new objects. You know,
if you're in them, you got to be careful
because once the market corrects, these
could drop significantly. But if you're
holding great companies that are still
undervalued or fairly valued, then
that's a safer way to play it. So, in
this all-time high market, are there
still stocks that are undervalued or
fairly priced? There are actually quite
a number and in fact, many of them are
very high quality compounders. Let me
give you a few examples and you can also
check very quickly on stock oracle. Oh,
by the way, in the next uh month or so,
we'll be launching the stock oracle uh
stock screener and the stock heat map
that will allow you to find stocks very
very quickly. And of course, by the end
of the year, we're also going to have
the Singapore listed and the China Hong
Kong listed stocks on stock oracle as
well. So, that's all uh going to be
rolled out really soon. Really excited
for that. Yeah. So, some examples,
Microsoft, such an obvious example.
Microsoft is right now actually very
very undervalued. If you take a look at
uh Microsoft, the intrinsic value
currently is $553
and it's currently selling at $418. So
yeah, you have got good companies that
are pretty cheap, right? On if you look
at PE ratio by itself, which is not
always meaningful, but the forward PE is
at 21 times when the company is growing
at uh 19% for the next 3 to 5 years. You
can see it's very ranked very high on
predictability, on profitability, on
growth, medium, very strong white
economic mode. Uh high financial
strength and pretty good valuation right
now. And if you look at the chart, all
right, it looks like, you know, very
nice wave up, wave down, wave up, wave
down. Looks like, you know, it's it
could be rebounding back up after a nice
uh double bottom pattern. Again, there's
no guarantees it's going to go up right
now. uh but the charts show a pretty
good probability and again this is not
financial advice for you to buy this
this just sharing with you uh what I own
and what I've been adding and what I see
from an educational perspective
platforms is another good example of a
company that announced solid earnings
but the share price has not search in
accordance with the the valuation so
Meta remains very undervalued uh
intrinsic value $95 currently selling at
$610 So very undervalued right now and
so these are the stocks that I continue
to hold. I continue to add to and if you
look at the charts you can see again
it's making a very nice retracement more
or less consolidating right now uh
before the eventual push up. Um now
beyond the MAX 7 are there also
companies that undervalued? Yeah. For
example, if you look at S&P Global,
which is a uh finance company, financial
analytics and ratings agency, and they
also own the S&P brand. So, every time
you look at anything with S&P 500, Dow
Jones, uh they own these brands. So,
they get royalties every time an ETF,
every time a fund uh uses their brands,
you know. So again, this has actually
been uh going through a bit of
retracement. It's been a bit sideways
recently, but the under uh underlying
fundamentals have been growing pretty
significantly. Um intrinsic value is
$515,
currently selling at $417.
And that's why again a lot of super
investors have actually been uh
purchasing this in their recent uh
filings, right? Another example is
Mastercard. Mastercard and Visa.
Although Visa is slightly overvalued,
Mastercard, which is actually growing
stronger than Visa, is actually quite
undervalued right now. Intrinsic value
is 561, currently selling at 498
and is growing at about 15%
uh projected growth for the next 3 to 5
years. So again, just to name a few. All
right. Now, how about stocks that you
own that are now overvalued? You know,
I've got students in my community asking
me, Adam, uh, some of the stocks are now
overvalued. Like I think Google is is a
bit overvalued right now. Google is one
of my biggest holdings. Let me just
double check. I don't remember
everything offhand, but yeah, Google is
uh slightly overvalued. You can see
intrinsic value is 298 currently selling
at 382. So, uh, 382 minus 298,
uh, is about
28%
overvalued. So, people have been asking
me, Adam, is about 30% overvalued. Uh,
should I sell? Well, it really depends
what's your objective. If you are a
short-term swing trader or you need the
money for something else, then yeah,
nothing wrong with selling right now. It
is overvalued. But for someone like me,
I'm not selling because I don't need the
money and I look at it uh where it's
going to be in the next 10 20 years and
no doubt it's going to keep compounding
in value. So um I don't sell it just
because it's slightly overvalued. You
know I would only consider selling a
great company only if it is grossly
overvalued. Grossly like if it's more
than 100% overvalued then yeah and start
to scale out. So in other words, if uh
Google today was at $600, which is more
than double the intrinsic value, then
yeah, I may start to sell a bit, right?
But 30% overvalued,
you know, I won't sell just because of
that because I want to hold it as a
long-term compounder. You know, another
example would be the cyber security
stocks that were actually left for dead
about a few weeks ago and then now
they've searched back when people
realize that hey, we need cyber
security, right? Duh. Of course. So, I
own Palo Alto, I own Foret, I own
Crowdstrike and recently the share price
has been like going up uh very very
steeply. So, if you look at Palo Alto
right now, I think Palo Alto is
currently overvalued already. Right.
Yeah, I'm right. So intrinsic value 199
is currently at 260. It is overvalued
and you can see the the PRICE ACTION
GOING UP right it's like you know going
up very steeply. So people say, "Adam,
it's like overextended, overbought,
overvalued. Should I sell?" And I said,
"It depends. If you need the money,
nothing wrong with selling here, right?
If you need the money to reinvest in
something else, you need the money for
your personal expenses, you need to
raise cash, nothing wrong. But for me,
Palo Alto is one of my uh bigger
holdings. I ain't selling shit." Okay?
Why? Because I don't need the money. Uh
and if I sell it, I have to find another
equally good company, you know? So I I
keep holding it. Even if it goes down
temporarily because it's overextended
over price in the short term, I'm fine
because I know in the long run the
intrinsic value at 199 will continue to
grow over the long run, you know. So
that's why I keep saying that, you know,
I never give advice to people. I never
advise people to buy. I never advise
people to sell. And you should never
listen to other people's advice. Why?
Because we all have different
objectives. Some of you are long-term
like me. I look where my portfolio will
be in 10 20 years. Some of you are more
shortterm. Um you know so we all have
different objectives. So one size cannot
fit all. You may need the cash so you
sell. I don't need the cash. I'm not
selling. Um that's why I never give
advice. You know the only thing I do is
I share with my students what I'm doing,
why I'm doing it. I share my research,
but then I say the decision to buy and
sell is your decision based on your
unique circumstances. All right? Just
because I sell something or I buy
something doesn't mean that you should
follow me. All right? But I'll explain
why I'm doing it. And if you're in the
same situation, then yeah, sell or or
whatever it is. Yeah. Okay. So, that's
it. That's what I want to share in this
video. I hope it's been useful. And like
I said, it's important to stay invested
in the right companies. Time in the
markets is more important than trying to
time the markets. You know, people who
attempted to time the markets early this
year uh in in the early part of the year
when the markets drop and they panic and
they sold and they're staying in cash
are sucking their thumb looking at the
markets going up every day like and
they're holding cash, their cash is
losing value. and worse, people who
shorted the market listening to the
profits of doom have been
getting slaughtered, right? So, we don't
want to do that. We want to grow our
wealth in a lowrisk, stress-free way.
Okay, so thank you for listening.
Subscribe if you have not already done
so, and I'll see you in the next video.
If you want to catch my latest videos,
click on the subscribe button right now.
Click on the bell so you get instant
notifications once I upload my latest
video. If you want to check out my
online courses, go on to
piranhaprofits.com
where you're going to learn how to
invest and how to trade the financial
markets and create an income from all
around the world. If you want to join my
live Wealth Academy program, go on to
wealthacademy global.com and find out
more about how you can learn investing
and trading live online. This is Adam
Coup and may the markets be with