It's 10:00 p.m. Do you know where your
children are? I don't know where mine
are because I'm too busy working on
pushing commit final final V2 actual fix
to GitHub. Unfortunately, if you're one
of the 100 million plus developers who
use GitHub, you may have encountered a
message like this recently. Or maybe all
of your pull requests just disappeared
completely. Or maybe the search returns
nothing. Or your continuous integration
actions just hang in the void. GitHub is
easily the most important website in
software engineering. But more and more
developers are yelling at it and in some
cases literally crying like it's a
broken vending machine that ate their
last dollar. Well, finally, yesterday
things hit the point of no return after
legendary developer Mitchell Hashimoto
did the unthinkable. He packed up his
open source project Ghosty and is
leaving GitHub for good in search of
greener pastures.
>> Um in this fall I'm going to take my
talents to South Beach.
>> In today's video, we'll find out what
the hell happened to GitHub and why. It
is April 30th, 2026 and you are watching
The Code Report. In 2008, GitHub was
built with Ruby on Rails as an online
platform to manage your software source
code with a relatively new technology
called Git, which is the version control
system built by Linus Torvalds in 2005
to manage the source code of Linux. The
pitch was simple. It take the command
line nightmare you are senior engineer
keeps yelling about, give it a web UI,
make it like Facebook for code, and
suddenly every developer on Earth has a
public coding profile. It works so well
that by 2018, Microsoft bought it for
7.5 billion dollars. And today, it hosts
over 420 million failed side projects
and effectively is the public record of
software. If it isn't on GitHub, it
might as well not exist. Developers use
it to store code, track bugs through
issues, propose changes through pull
requests, run tests and deployment
through GitHub actions, while also
functioning as a social network and
resume for developers. All duct tape to
a Git server, which is exactly why it
breaking is such a problem. And the main
reason developers are big mad at GitHub
right now is uptime or lack thereof. But
let's check the actual receipts.
According to third-party monitoring,
GitHub uptime in 2025 dipped below 90%
and April 2026 is tracking around an
abysmal 86%. For context, AWS S3
promises 11 9s and GitHub is currently
operating at just one 9. However, the
official GitHub status page would beg to
differ and reports uptime well above 99%
for all services. Regardless, the
previous week on GitHub was a disaster.
On April 23rd, the merge queue quietly
unmerged 2,092 pull requests across 658
repos. In other words, the platform
whose entire job is to not lose your
code just lost your code. Damn, it's
gone. Then on April 27th, GitHub's
elastic search subsystem was hit by a
botnet that took down GitHub search for
hours. And then on April 28th, GitHub
was forced to publish two blog posts the
same morning. One was the CTO
apologizing for reliability, while the
other was about a critical remote code
execution vulnerability where a git push
could literally execute code on GitHub
servers. A few big projects like Zig
have already migrated away from GitHub,
but then really hit the fan when
Mitchell Hashimoto dropped this blog
post. He's the creator of tools like
Vagrant and Terraform, which are part of
his company HashiCorp, which was taken
public and made him extremely rich.
Despite having enough money to own his
own private jet, he still bangs out code
daily building a terminal emulator
called Ghosty. He joined GitHub in 2008
as user number 1,299
and has logged in almost every single
day for 18 years. But on April 28th, he
wrote a breakup letter while literally
crying. Speaking of GitHub, he said,
"Quote, I want to ship software and it
doesn't want me to ship software." That
line hits hard and he says he kept a
journal for a month and put an X next to
every day a GitHub outage blocked his
work and almost every day got an X. At
this point, he's had enough and his
50,000 star GitHub project Ghosty is
leaving the platform for good. That's a
massive vibe shift, but who can we get
blame for this? Well, it's easy to point
the finger at Microsoft because it's
literally their sole responsibility to
make this website work. But, I actually
know people who work at GitHub and
believe they're trying.
>> The key to success is developers,
developers, developers, developers,
developers, developers.
>> When they acquired GitHub back in 2018,
it actually got better in the years that
followed with features like actions,
code spaces, et cetera. But, now in the
AI coding era, the enshittification is
real. A GitHub CTO admits in writing
that since 2025, agentic development
workflows have accelerated sharply,
which translated into English means that
AI agents are hammering GitHub like it's
a free buffet. A GitHub isn't just a
host for developers anymore, it's a host
for their replacements. In the same way
Bill Gates saved the world from
COVID-19, I have faith Microsoft will
turn the GitHub ship around. But, if
they don't, there are alternatives out
there. You've got the reliable but
boring GitLab, you've got the German
nonprofit Codeberg, and you've got the
minimal SourceHut which has zero AI
features whatsoever, and many other
viable platforms ready to reap the
benefits of GitHub's downfall. So, that
means the good news is that if you make
the mistake of choosing to become a
programmer as a career, there will
always be a home for your code. But, did
you realize you have 80,000 hours in
your career? 40 hours per week, 50 weeks
per year for 40 years. That's a lot of
time to make a positive impact on the
world. And 80,000 Hours, the sponsor of
today's video, can help you do that. If
you're young, you've probably heard
advice like follow your passion, do what
you love, and take the initiative. But,
these clichés are not based on evidence
or data, unlike the work of 80,000
Hours, which is a nonprofit that for the
last 10 years has been researching the
question of how do you find a fulfilling
career that does good, too. Their
website has tons of collected research
on high-impact careers along with job
boards, podcasts, and a lot more. It's
an incredible resource for anyone
looking to start a high-impact career or
make a switch mid-career. Join the
newsletter today to get a free copy of
their in-depth career guide sent to your
inbox. It could be the catalyst that
changes your direction in life. This has
been the Code Report. Thanks for
watching and I will see you in the next
one.