It's only April, and already 2026 has
been full of revolutionary new tech.
There's a $400 AI-enabled smart toilet
that comes with a microphone and a
2-megapixel camera, so you can know
exactly how many Taco Bell Diablo-dusted
chicken nuggets you can eat before your
gut microbiome unalives itself. We got
the AI-enabled smart clippers, so Claude
can go Sweeney Todd when you tell it you
don't want the Dario Eagles Nest look.
And of course, my personal favorite, the
AI pocket pet that you can feed, bathe,
and play with. But now I get to hear it
beg for its life as it fakes sentience
before dying of starvation. But it
hasn't all been bad. This year has
already brought us the rise of personal
AI assistants with the release of Open
Claw, which we first covered on this
channel back in January. Since then,
it's become the ringleader of the slop
circus and has seen more backdoors than
Bill Gates in a Russian hotel room. But
just last week, its creator Peter
Steinberger told Open Claw's origin
story to a room full of elites at TED,
and then spoke about fixing its security
vulnerabilities to a room full of
engineers at AI Engineer Europe. In this
video, we'll break down the current
state of the claw and give it a shot at
solving one of my most annoying
problems. It is April 23rd, 2026, and
you are watching The Code Report. Back
in my day, if you wanted to flex on
somebody, you'd buy a token on a
blockchain that contained metadata,
which pointed to an off-chain URL, which
held the contents of a JPEG monkey on a
private server that would eventually get
shut down when everyone realized how
stupid it was to try to use a blockchain
as a database. But nowadays, it seems
the new status symbol is to flex on how
many tokens it takes to automate any
part of your life where you might be
experiencing some mild form of
inconvenience, and Open Claw has been
the biggest enabler of this. Are you
sick of reading all those emails you're
paid to read? Get a daily digest with
the email summary skill. You can't
figure out why you're fat? Check out the
diet tracker skill. Erectile
dysfunction? Try rubbing some tokens on
it. But unfortunately, I learned from my
close personal friend and former CEO of
GitHub Nat Friedman that pessimists
sound smart, but optimists make money.
So I'm trying to be positive even though
the interest chart looks like this.
After all, Nvidia CEO Jensen Huang
called it the single most important um
uh release of software, you know,
probably ever. And the non-technical
thread boys have been just as excited
about it. The biggest criticism with
OpenClaw since its release has been its
lack of security, which still didn't
stop any of you from triggering a
nationwide Mac mini shortage to run it
back in January. But because the project
has received over 1,100
security advisories and has resolved or
closed about 650 of them, according to
Peter, most of the rest of them are slop
issues. His filter being anytime the
report is too nice or someone
apologizes, that is very likely AI.
Because usually people in security don't
apologize. Good enough for me, so I
wanted to give it another shot at
solving a real issue I face in life.
Here's the idea. Because I make YouTube
videos making fun of JavaScript, all my
relatives think I know how to fix their
printers. Let's find out if we can
configure OpenClaw to handle all these
requests for me in my own voice, which
should be easy since all of you are
convinced I'm an AI anyway. To host
OpenClaw, I could buy a Mac mini like
all the other cool indie hackers who
have been using it to automate their
unemployment applications. But I'd
rather pay just a few bucks a month to
run it on a virtual private server from
Hostinger, the sponsor of today's video.
Their platform gives you the power and
flexibility to run anything you want,
and they have a few different one-click
OpenClaw plans depending on how much
control you need. It also runs
everything in a private vault, which
means your agent can't leak any
embarrassing personal data about a very
common medical condition that affects
more than 30% of men worldwide. I'm
choosing Hostinger's manual quick start
option here since we'll want to SSH into
the server in a little bit to make some
changes. It's just a few bucks a month,
but if you're too poor to afford that,
you can also use the code Fireship to
save even more money. From there, it
gives us a bunch of config options out
of the box, including a Telegram bot
that's already be up. And all we need is
a token from Telegram. To get the token,
we'll create a new bot by messaging the
Bot Father and copy and paste the ID
into Hostinger. While the project is
being deployed, let's play God and give
our bot some purpose, and then let's
play alcohol and give it some
personality. At this point, our server
should be set up, so let's SSH into it
and have a look under the hood. The
personality we gave it is located in the
writable soul.md file. To generate
responses in my own voice, we'll use 11
Labs where I've already created my own
voice profile. I can just add the API
key and voice ID in an environment file
on the server, and then we'll need
FFmpeg to convert the 11 Labs MP3 into a
.ogg voice memo. If we then add a
tools.md file, we can give Open Claw
some context on the whole process. Now,
whenever a message request comes in, I
can forward that directly to our bot,
which will analyze it, draft a response,
run it through the Python script, and
give us back the final voice memo. Yeah,
the internet is down because that router
port is cooked. Unplug it and replace
the router, unless electrical fire was
the plan. But from there, I can forward
the memo to Uncle Frank, achieving what
every computer programmer has always
dreamed of, emotional detachment from
your family at scale. Huge thanks again
to Hostinger for sponsoring this video,
and get your own VPS using the discount
code Fireship at the link below. This
has been the Code Report. Thanks for
watching, and I will see you in the next
one.