In this section, we're building one of
the most fundamental patterns in
blockchain development, an escrow
program. An escrow is a neutral third
party that holds assets until certain
conditions are met. In traditional
finance, this might be a bank or a
lawyer, but on the blockchain, we
replace that trusted middleman with
code, so a smart contract that enforces
the rules automatically. Escrows are
everywhere in Web3. DEXs use the escrow
logic for token swaps. NFT marketplaces
use it to hold assets until payments
clear.
>> [music]
>> Freelance platforms use it to protect
both clients and contractors. Once you
understand the escrow pattern, you'll
recognize it in almost every DeFi
protocol you interact with. So, in this
program, we'll have three instructions:
make, which allows someone to create an
escrow, deposit their tokens into a
vault, and specify what they want in
return. Take lets another party accept
those terms. They send the requested
tokens and receive what's in the vault.
The whole swap happens automatically,
and refund lets the original creator
cancel and reclaim their tokens if they
change their mind. Beyond the escrow
logic, we'll learn how to test Anchor
programs using Light SVM, which is a
fast, lightweight alternative to running
a local validator. By the end, you'll
have a reusable pattern that you can
apply to countless blockchain
applications. [music] Now, let's get
started.
So, I'm going to link a repo of the
code, and we're going to go over just
the concepts and code snippets rather
than code from scratch line by line.
Just to save more engaging and avoid a
lot of repetitive code. Now, we already
talked about how most things in DeFi are
an escrow, but let's chat about why. So,
let's say I'm making a $1,000 bet on the
Super Bowl with my friend, and I'm
betting on the Eagles and he's betting
on the Chiefs. But, how do we know the
winner is actually going to get paid?
Well, in traditional finance, either I'd
have to trust my friend that he'd
actually pay me when the Eagles win, but
this is an emotional time, and I don't
know if he will. So, we could hire a
third party to hold our money and give
it to the correct person once the bet is
over, but again, this involves a lot of
trust. So, blockchain fixes this. It
creates a fully trustless third party
because this third party is just code.
And that's what we're going [music] to
write today. And it's an escrow. So, it
holds funds and releases them to the
correct person when the specified
conditions are met. So, if we made a bet
on chain instead, [music] the code would
query the outcome of the Super Bowl at
the specified time and immediately
release the funds to the correct person.
And it's as simple [music] as that. So,
how do we get started? Well, whenever
I'm writing smart contracts, I always
like to start with the state. And
[music]
as we now know, Solana programs are
stateless. So, when we want custom data
stored, we're going to need to create an
account in the smart contract. So, let's
start with where we're going to define
that account. So,
>> [snorts]
>> first, let's
open up the code. If I go to GitHub, um
I'm going to link this repo. We're going
to copy this GitHub CLI command, open up
our terminal.
And I'll just zoom in a bit so you can
see. I'll paste in the clone command,
and we're going to first CD into the
directory of the project that we just
cloned.
And then, we're going to take the code
that was already written for us, and
we're just going to go through it.
So, first,
we said we're starting with the state.
Now, let's see where that actually is.
If I go into programs, Anchor escrow
source, and then there's a file called
state.rs, and this is where you're going
to define every account that you create,
the custom state for that account. So,
accounts are where all of your data is
stored. Here, we're just going to have
one account, and that's going to be our
escrow account. So,
you can see here, we have this struct
that is our escrow, and it's going to
have all the fields of the data that I
want to store for my escrow. And here,
all I'm storing is the seed, the maker.
The maker is going to be the person who
makes a new escrow contract, a new bet,
a new whatever logic that they want to
have.
Um and then, we have these two mint
public keys, and that is going to be
allowing for two different tokens. So,
if I want a mint account for one and a
mint account for another token. And
then, the receive is going to be the
taker, whoever is going to receive the
funds that the maker is locking into
this vault of the escrow. And then, we
store our bump. So, for best practice
when you're writing Anchor programs, you
always want to store the bump, and that
is just going to make things more
efficient. We'll go through exactly why
once we get a little deeper into the
code.
Um but, there you have it. You have your
custom data structure with all of the
information that you want stored. Now,
you can see that there's these two
macros, and we talked about before how
Anchor
simplifies a lot of smart contract
design. And they do that with these
macros that are created. So, here you
can see this derive init space, and what
this does is it automatically calculates
the space needed to store the struct on
chain. So, Anchor adds up all of the
byte sizes of all of the fields that
you've stated here in your struct, and
then it calculates how much space it's
going to store, so you don't have to do
that manually.
Now, there's also this other
macro, and that is defining what the
discriminator is. So, this is setting a
custom discriminator that is a one-byte
discriminator. Normally, Anchor uses the
first eight bytes of the SHA-256
as the discriminator. Um this overrides
that with just a simple one. So, the
discriminator is written at the start of
the account data to identify a specific
account type.
So,
everything for your state is good to go.
But, all this is doing is defining what
is in your state. So, how do we actually
create the account that's going to hold
this state? Well,
let's go to these instructions. You have
a folder of three different
instructions, our make, refund, and
take. And we know that the
escrow starts at the make instruction.
You're having a maker create a new
escrow.
If you go to the lib.rs, you're going to
see this program macro. The program
macro is part of Anchor defining exactly
all of the instructions that are going
to exist within the smart contract that
you're writing. So, you can see we have
those three instructions that were
defined in this instruction folder. And
we're going to start with make. So, make
is where you're actually initializing a
new escrow account, and we're just going
to click into this make context. So,
if you're familiar with Anchor, this is
a very familiar format that you'll see.
Um it always starts with this context as
your first parameter. And the reason why
is this is where all of the accounts for
the accounts that you need to handle for
the instruction is going to be given.
So, if I click into this, it's going to
take me over to the make.rs file.
Now,
here you can see
this derive accounts macro and a data
structure inside of it. So, this derive
accounts macro, what it does is it tells
all of the accounts that are needed to
be able to
process the instruction that you're
writing, and it's going to tell you
everything that needs to be done to the
account. So, what does that mean? Well,
for example, let's start with the escrow
account. So, we already defined what the
state looks like. But,
here you can see there's a lot of
constraints that were written within
this account macro. So, what does that
mean? Well, first, we have this init
constraint, and what that's doing is
saying this account doesn't exist yet,
and I need to create it. So, instead of
writing all of the logic for how to
create an accounts on Solana, in Anchor,
all you have to do is specify the init
constraint when you are writing out your
derive accounts macro.
>> [snorts]
>> So,
here you have the escrow. If I click
into this escrow
type, it's going to go back to the data
that we've already defined. Now, let's
go back over,
and you can see we already talked about
init, payer. The reason we need a payer
here is because we're initializing a new
accounts. And accounts need to pay rent
on chain, so this is how data is
actually paid for. You're going to have
um
the amount of space that is needed on
chain calculated, and then you're going
to pay
for that space. So, someone has to pay
for that. So, here we're going to define
that the maker is paying for the space
on chain.
Now, this is, once the account is
closed, able to go back to the maker.
So, it's not a sunk cost, but kind of
just holding their spot as they're using
space on chain.
Here, this is just calculating the space
because we need to know how much to pay.
But, this is where the actual
escrow logic comes in. So, you can see
this specific constraint defined as
seeds, and then there's a lot that
happens after. So, what this actually is
is defining a PDA. So, a PDA is a
program derived address, and what that
is is it is a public key that falls off
the ED25519 curve, and it's generated by
having this input of seeds plus a bump,
and it runs through the SHA-256 hash and
generates a public key.
>> [snorts]
>> If that public key does land on the
ED25519 curve, that means it has a
corresponding private key, and it's not
valid as a PDA. So, it's going to
regenerate the bump. The bump always
starts at 255. Um it will decrement by
one every iteration until it actually
lands off the ED25519 curve. And when
that happens,
it's
now a public key that does not have a
corresponding private key. And the
reason that that's important is you're
only going to be able to sign for the
transaction
with the signer seeds through a program.
So, now no one can find your private key
and be able to sign for you. So, all
trust lies within this code. And the
program itself has to sign with the
signer seeds. So, what are those seeds?
Well, they're exactly what you define
here. So, here you can have any type of
seeds that you want. All that
I'm doing specifically for this program
is writing out escrow,
having the maker, who is going to take
the
public key of the signer, store that as
part of the input seeds for the PDA, and
then also this seed parameter. So, this
is just an example to show that if you
want to have part of your seeds as
something
that doesn't exist within the struct,
how that works is you're able to take it
as an input parameter for the
instruction. So, you can see here
there's this instruction macro.
And
what that's saying is, "Hey, I'm using
this variable seeds and I'm using it
within my account, but I don't have
access to it. So, how do I get it? I'm
going to get it as an input parameter."
So, if I go back to the lib.rs where the
function is defined, you can see that
seed is taken in as a parameter for the
function. So, going back here, just to
show exactly what I mean, if I remove
this macro
where I'm not saying this comes as an
input parameter of the function, now you
can see seeds is no longer recognized.
And if I save this, I should be getting
an error.
Um but
yeah, you can see seeds doesn't exist.
Cannot find the value. So, if I go back
and put the instruction macro back,
um give this a second to rerun the Rust
analyzer, and now seeds can be found
again.
So, this is just an example of if you
want to have part of your um seeds for
your PDA as a value that's not defined
somewhere within the struct, you can
just pass it as a parameter in the
instruction.
Okay.
So, that's kind of high-level overview
of having a PDA as your account. And
we'll go through exactly how to sign uh
later on when we're going through the
code. But, let's just go over the rest
of the accounts that are passed through.
When I'm creating this make function, I
not only have the escrow, but I'm going
to have to define all the other accounts
that are going to need to be interacted
with in order to actually execute this
instruction. So,
you can see I have this mint A, mint B.
This is allowing for two different
tokens to be interacted with um when
you're actually executing the make
function, and you can define what that
mint [clears throat] account is. So, if
I wanted to put USDC, I would define
that mint account here when I'm creating
the instruction
and any other account that you want.
Now, you have this maker ATA. So, what
is that? That's an associated token
account. So, the mint account, which
we've gone over a few times um within
other projects in this boot camp, but
the mint account is kind of the global
information of the token, and the token
account is what actually holds tokens.
So, if I want the maker to be able to
send tokens to the vaults to be stored
for this escrow program, it's going to
have to have a token account associated
with the instruction to be able to send
those tokens. So, this is just having
whatever the token account for the maker
is of the token they're sending into the
vaults.
And now, the very last section here
uh is going to be the vault itself. So,
we did define the escrow, but all this
account does is store data. It doesn't
actually store tokens. So, I want to
have an account associated with this
escrow that's going to actually hold the
tokens, so then they can be correctly
released when the logic has been
executed. So,
let's see.
This is initializing a new token account
that's associated with this escrow
program, and it's defining the payer for
the token account is going to be the
maker,
and it's saying what this token account
is. So, every token account is going to
have an associated mint account because
that is defining the global information
of what token you're actually storing
into that token account.
And now, you can see this is kind of the
key line.
We have associated token, the authority
of the account is going to be the
escrow.
So, as we talked about over here, the
escrow is not a typical public key with
a private key that can be signed for.
It's a PDA that needs signer seeds for
the program to be able to execute the
transaction. So, what actually has
authority over this vault to be able to
release funds is the program itself.
And that's what's making this
one line, the authority being the
escrow, this is what's making everything
here trustless.
And then, the very last three lines are
very typical whenever you're defining
all of the accounts for instruction.
It's going to have your associated token
program that's needed whenever you're
creating an ATA account, your token
program because we're interacting with
tokens, and then the system program is
needed because we're initializing new
accounts on chain. So, this is just
accessing other program information to
be able to
execute all the commands that we want
for this instruction.
Now,
that's how your derived account struct
works. All of the accounts that need to
be accessed to be able to execute the
logic in the instruction that you want.
So, that defines everything we need for
make.
And now, let's go back over to the
actual instruction.
If I go to lib.rs, you can see that this
has been organized with a handler. And
if I click into this, it's going to take
us back to the make page,
and this handler is executing two
functions. Populate the escrow and
deposit tokens. Because if I'm the
maker, all I'm doing is creating a new
escrow, defining what information needs
to be in that escrow, and then I'm going
to deposit tokens into the vault that I
just initialized.
So, let's look at what the logic
actually is.
When you're populating the escrow, all
you're doing is defining all of the
information that needs to be stored in
the escrow account. It's just the data.
So, if we go back to state here, you see
all of the data that's specified that is
the same data that has been defined for
our populate escrow instruction.
Now, the other function that's being ran
here is deposit tokens. And this is
where we're introducing a new concept,
and that is our CPI. So, CPI is a
cross-program
invocation.
And what that is is you are calling an
instruction from one program
for another program. So, we're writing
our escrow program, but when we're
calling a CPI, we're actually calling a
transfer instruction from another
program on chain.
Now, when you see the CPI,
there are specific accounts that are
interacted with here. So, this transfer
checked instruction is what we're
calling, and that is transferring a
token from one account to another. So,
you can see our from account is the
maker's ATA,
and we're using the mint of the token
that we've specified, and it's going to
the vault itself, and the authority is
going to be the maker in this case
because the maker is signing from their
own wallet and depositing it into the
vaults. So, in this case, the maker's
wallet is a public key that does have an
associated private key, so it does fall
on that ED25519 curve. It's essentially
going to be the wallet of the user
that's going to be signing the
transaction here.
So, we don't have to worry about the PDA
signer seeds, but we'll get into that
later. So, this is just a very basic CPI
for transferring a token from one
account to another. And in this case,
the account that's going to be
transferred into is going to be the
vault account of the escrow program, so
the escrow is now holding this token.
Okay. So, that's everything for make.
And now, the reason we're not actually
writing this line by line is it does get
pretty repetitive, and you'll see here
when I open the take file. Actually, I'm
just going to lay these side by side so
you can see how similar they look.
We're creating our derived accounts.
We're specifying a new data structure of
all the accounts that need to be
interacted with for this
function to be able to execute. You can
see they're pretty much the same
accounts. You have your maker.
In this case, we're now introducing
another
um account, which is the taker, who's
going to be taking those funds.
Um
and then we still have the escrow. It's
going to be defined pretty similarly. Um
here, the only thing that changes is
it's already been initialized, so I
don't have to worry about initializing
it as a constraint, but I do have to add
this mute constraint. And the reason I
have to add it is because
variables in Rust are immutable by
default, and here I'm going to be
changing the data in the escrow account,
so I have to define it as mutable
because something's going to change. So,
I'm just saying, "Hey, I am changing
this
um and I'm just going to let you know
that's going to happen."
Now,
here we have a few additional
constraints that have been added. And
what these are just kind of some
security checks. So, it's defining that
the maker is the correct public key, the
mint A and mint B for the mint accounts
are also the correct public keys. So,
this is just additional security checks
to make sure the correct accounts are
interacting with this instruction. And
if
it is an incorrect account trying to
interact with the instruction, it's
going to return an error and say
you don't have access, this is an
invalid account.
Um otherwise, everything else looks
pretty much the same. You're defining
all of the accounts that need to be
interacted with, but now we're just
adding the taker into this equation.
And now, the one thing that is different
here is how the CPI is actually
executed. And the reason is
that we now are going to execute using
our PDA.
So, for the taker to be able to now take
the funds, they're going to be taking
the funds from the vault.
And the vault has to
be able to sign for that instruction.
And because we now know that the vault
is a PDA, it's going to have to be
signed from the program with the signer
seeds. So, we can just compare what this
looks like. We're still transferring a
token, so we're making a CPI call to the
token program
calling the transfer checked function.
>> [snorts]
>> And
that's still all the same.
And you can see here, we're defining
once again the token program, the
transfer checked function, and it has
all of the same parameters. However,
when we're calling this CPI context,
instead of just saying new, we're saying
new assigner. And the reason why is
we're going to have to sign with signer
seeds. So, there's an additional field
added here, which is your signer seeds.
And what these seeds are, we're going to
have to specify
and they're going to be the seeds of the
PDA that you defined. So, you can see
here, we've defined what the signer
seeds are, and we can make sure they're
correct by going back to our make
instruction
when we actually
initialized the escrow program and
defined what the seeds were for the PDA.
And you can see here
we have our escrow
as our first seed.
We have our maker as our second, and
then we have the escrow seed as the
last. And then all we're doing after is
just defining the bump. And the reason
you're defining the bump is to just
make it easier to actually find what the
PDA is. So, we're saving the bump of the
PDA when we initialize it. You can see
here, we're saving the bump.
And
um the bump is that 255 that's being
added
when you're actually generating the PDA.
So, just to recap
when you're creating a PDA, it has these
input seeds plus a bump starting at 255,
and then every iteration it decrements
by one.
And those values are going to be ran
through the SHA-256 hash and output a
public key.
That public key is either going to fall
on the ED25519 curve or it's not. If it
doesn't, it's a valid PDA address. If it
does, it's invalid and it's going to
have to run again, but now it's going to
run your input seeds with 254 and so on.
So, if I save the bump and I know what
it is, when I'm recalculating my PDA,
it's going to know immediately by just
pulling that bump that I saved.
If I don't save it, it's going to run
through that cycle continuously until it
finds the correct address. So, now we're
saving like CU cycles and um
making the contract more efficient by
saving it and just being able to
directly call that value.
Okay. So
that shows the difference between just
signing with your
regular CPI and signing with a PDA. And
that's how we know that this is more
secure of a program because the PDA is
the authority here for the vaults.
Okay.
So, that goes over pretty much
everything that you need for writing an
escrow program.
So, now that we've gone over the whole
program, all that we have left is to
build it and then test it. So, how we're
going to build it is we're going to open
up our terminal
and just type in anchor build. So,
anchor build, it's using the anchor CLI
to compile all of your rust code and
then create this target folder here. So,
we're going to let this run and let
everything compile.
And here you can see it finished and
compiled successfully. If you're
following along, it's going to take a
little bit more time for you because I
pre-compiled this for this video.
Um so
just wait until it completely finishes.
Once that's done, you can open your
target directory, go to IDL, and what
we're going to do is copy this IDL file
into this IDLs directory up here. And
the reason is so our latest VM test can
access it. Um
so
now that it's compiled, we're going to
be able to test. I will just copy this
over. So, we'll go to IDL, anchor
escrow.json
and then paste it into the IDLs folder.
Now that that is good to go
I'll be able to run cargo test. And what
that's going to do is run our latest VM
test, and I'll go over how those are
working.
So, we'll do cargo test. It's going to
compile and then run the tests.
And you can see here, I'll just zoom in
a bit so you can see it better.
We have running one test, test the
escrow make and take has passed. So,
let's see what that test looks like.
I'll
zoom out, go into the test folder.
And it's showing an error just because
my rust analyzer is a little behind. Um
it's just waiting to be able to read
this IDL file.
Once it fully reloads, that error error
will go away. But for now, let's just go
over what these tests look like. So,
this test demonstrates a complete escrow
flow using latest VM. And what latest VM
is, it's a fast lightweight Solana
virtual machine that's used for testing.
So
here you can see we're importing a
couple crates. So, one is our anchor
latest VM crate and our latest VM utils
crate. And what that is doing is
using latest VM, but adding some
additional helpers to be able to make it
a little bit more compatible with the
anchor program that you're writing. So,
you can see here, we have this anchor
lang
declare program
for the anchor escrow. And what this
does is it generates all the client
modules for the program. So, it's kind
of like this magic line that helps you
keep all of your code type safe, and
it's referencing this IDL that we pasted
over here. So, by using this, you don't
need any manual serialization. Now,
we're going to just go through the test.
All it's doing is
setting up your latest VM environment.
So, you can see right here where it has
anchor latest VM build with program, and
it is referencing your program ID and
the program bytes to your .so file. This
is where it's able to actually read the
program and test against it. And it's
using this, running it against the
Solana virtual machine that latest VM is
running, and then being able to test as
if it's running in a real blockchain
environment. Which is why you're able to
create test accounts and create token
mints and fund those token accounts to
be able to fully like emulate what you
want your environment to look like. So,
we have everything set up here for our
environment.
We're also creating token accounts to be
able to interact with our escrow
program. And then once all of that is
created, you're going to be able to
actually call the
here we're calling the make instruction
and we're passing through all of the
accounts that are needed for that
instruction. So, if you remember when we
were writing the program, we have that
derived account struct where you're
specifying
all of the accounts that the instruction
is going to need to interact with. And
here you're going to specify them once
again when you're testing out the
program. So, we're calling the make
instruction, defining every account that
it interacts with that you can verify in
your derived account struct that you
wrote in the program.
And then you're specifying all of the
arguments that need to be passed
through. And then once you unwrap that
function, you're able to execute the
instruction on your latest VM virtual
machine.
And then we're just asserting to make
sure that everything
resolves how we want once that once the
instruction is executed. And then we're
able to now test the take instruction as
well. And this follows the entire escrow
flow. We're able to make an escrow, have
the logic be defined, and then once it
is met, we're able to have the take
instruction called to be able to
finalize that interaction between the
maker and the taker. So
there's your escrow program. You have
your tests. You can see the test passed
down here, and you're good to go. So,
that was
your escrow anchor project for the
bootcamp, and stay tuned for what's
next.