Eight months ago, some galaxy brain
hacker quietly penetrated the back door
of more than 30 WordPress plugins, and
no one noticed until now. As somehow,
this massive collection of different
WordPress plugins for silly UI updates
was instantly turned into malware with a
crazy supply chain attack. That means
one minute, your countdown timer
ultimate plugin is converting sales on
your website, and then the next minute,
it becomes a remote control demon on
your server that steals all your data
and leaks photos of your wife's
boyfriend to the Kiwi Farms. WordPress
remains the most popular website builder
in the world, but many people have
argued that WordPress's plugin
architecture is fundamentally insecure,
and a brand new slot work has emerged to
replace it. In today's video, we'll find
out how the latest brutal exploit
occurred and take a look at this new
project from Cloudflare that hopes to
terminate WordPress from the timeline.
It is April 16th, 2026, and you are
watching The Code Report. I actually
love WordPress and have built many
failed side projects with it, but the
WordPress ecosystem has experienced a
wild couple years. Its founder, Matt
Mullenweg, sperged out on private equity
last year because the Silver Lake-owned
WP Engine was drinking his milkshake by
making money hosting WordPress. So,
naturally, he demanded that they pay him
8% of their revenue for using his logo.
Now, as you all know, I'm a huge fan of
private equity because they make every
product better, like Hooters, for
example, but WP Engine refused to pay
the king his royalty. That made
Mullenweg sperg out even harder, and he
said a bunch of stuff that eventually
led to WP Engine filing a defamation
lawsuit against him. They're still
fighting each other in court to this
day, and the lore goes way deeper, but
the bigger problem for WordPress is that
it's been experiencing a wave of new
vulnerabilities, and 96% of those are a
direct result of its plugin system. The
core problem is that a WordPress plugin
is basically just a PHP script that
plugs straight into your site and starts
running with full privileges. There's no
sandbox or isolation. It can touch your
database, your files, and your private
parts. And when you install a plugin,
you're basically just hoping a stranger
knows how to handle every edge case,
exploit, and bad input perfectly. What's
crazy though, is that this most recent
attack on 31 WordPress plugins was
actually not the result of bad code.
>> It's not your fault.
>> It was something far scarier. In this
case, the attacker didn't exploit a
vulnerability. Instead, they
legitimately acquired and took control
of a portfolio of plugins by simply
purchasing them for money from the
original developer on Flippa in a deal
with a sales price estimated to be in
the mid six figures. After the original
developer was bought out, the new buyer
had control of the code and they
inserted a back door about eight months
ago and it's just been sitting there
dormant in production waiting for the
right moment. Then, when the moment was
right, the malicious logic activated
which reached out to a remote server,
pulled down additional payloads, and in
some cases modified core files like
wp-config.php
which includes sensitive data like your
database connection and security keys.
And apparently, the command and control
domain was resolved through an Ethereum
smart contract. So, once the exploit
became known, the attacker could quickly
update the smart contract to point to a
new domain at any time. That's pretty
clever, but the core issue here is that
everything was delivered through a
normal plugin update from a trusted
source. So, it bypassed the usual
suspicion of a normal fishing attack.
Now, WordPress did step in and remove
the plugins, but damage is already done
inside the system and turning what
looked like routine maintenance into a
full-blown supply chain compromise.
Luckily though, if you're considering
using WordPress today, Cloudflare
recently created a new project called m-
which takes all that old crappy PHP code
and turns it into something even
crappier, AI written JavaScript code.
This project actually doesn't use any
original WordPress code and is MIT
licensed, but it's designed to be fully
compatible with the original WordPress
APIs. And under the hood, it's based on
the awesome Astro project for its
content management system. What makes
this project special though, is that it
doesn't let plugins run wild with full
access. m- locks each plugin down in its
own sandbox with a dynamic worker. The
framework itself doesn't hand over your
data directly. Instead, the plugin only
gets access to specific capabilities
through bindings and only if it
explicitly asks for them in the
manifest. It's kind of like telling the
plugin, "No, no, don't touch me there.
This is my no-no square." Pretty cool,
but will M dash actually kill WordPress
once and for all? The answer is probably
not and definitely not anytime soon.
But, the craziest thing to me is how
quickly developers can roll out complete
replacements for frameworks that have
been around for forever. And that's made
possible by modern AI coding tools like
Warp, the sponsor of today's video. If
you're vibe maxing with Claude Code,
Codex, Gemini CLI, and open code at the
same time, but keep losing track of all
your agents, you need to check out
Warp's new universal agent support,
which turns your terminal into an agent
command center. Vertical tabs let you
group your agent sessions together and
quickly see useful metadata like Git
branch, work tree, and pull request
status, which means your terminal
finally has object permanence. And the
tab configs let you save your ideal
setup and reopen it instantly in the
future. The best part though is that you
can get notifications from your coding
agents in Warp and on your desktop
whenever they need attention. Instead of
checking on them every 30 seconds like a
helicopter parent. So, if you already
have an agent you like or you want to
try running multiple agents at once, I'd
highly recommend checking out Warp for
free at the link below. This has been
the Code Report. Thanks for watching and
I will see you in the next one.