Hey everyone, it's Bree and today we're
going to talk about trading. In a
previous video, I got to sit down with
Anatoly, one of the Solana founders, to
understand what motivated him to build a
global state machine. And one of his
biggest motivators was actually his
frustration trading in traditional
markets. He wanted to create [music]
fairness and give the edge back into the
hands of individual traders. So,
traditional markets, they haven't kept
up with technology and honestly, they're
starting to show their age. Moving
markets onto a blockchain introduces
something they've never had, which is
transparency and a true level playing
field anywhere in the world. So, today
we'll be diving into the vision of a
decentralized on-chain Nasdaq and we'll
talk about where Solana stands right now
and the benefits of on-chain trading.
>> [music]
>> So, yeah, traditional finance does have
electronic markets, but the access is
layered. You have brokers, exchanges,
custodians, market makers, clearing
systems and well, a lot of hidden
plumbing between your order and your
final fill.
>> [music]
>> But on Solana, more of that stack is
exposed as open rails. And what I mean
by this is you have execution, routing,
collateral, custody, and settlement that
can all happen in the same environment
>> [music]
>> with software native access and much
more viable market data. Now, that
doesn't mean every fill is perfect.
There's still fragmentation and there's
still competition, but the market
structure is open enough that traders
can participate more directly. And that
matters because in traditional markets,
the best data, the best tooling, and the
best execution quality lives inside
large firms. On Solana, more of that
market is public, composable, and
actually accessible to anyone anywhere
in the [music] world. Now, that doesn't
eliminate edge, it just changes where
edge comes from. And a cool thing about
Solana is it's not actually limited
[music] to only crypto native assets
anymore. You have tokenized equities,
commodities, and ETFs that now exist on
chain. And I think that's a signal worth
paying attention to.
>> [music]
>> It shows where on-chain markets are
actually heading. You now have more
programmable access and more of the
trading stack moving onto public [music]
infrastructure. So, the lines between
crypto markets and traditional markets
are starting to blur. And Solana is
where a lot of that convergence is
happening. Now, let's talk about speed.
Yes, Solana is fast, but that's not
really the point here.
Speed matters because it changes what
kind of market can actually exist on
chain. Solana processes thousands of
transactions per second on the live
network and has demonstrated over 1
million TPS in test [music]
environments. But, that exact number
doesn't really matter. What matters is
what it unlocks. Because that level of
throughput is what makes order book
style trading and high-frequency
interaction actually possible on chain
in the first place.
There's also a deeper point here around
Solana's architecture. Solana is built
for parallel execution. And what I mean
by that is many transactions can be
processed simultaneously instead of
everything competing through one narrow
lane. So, that reduces congestion and
makes fast market interaction a lot more
realistic. Because here's the thing, if
you want real trading to happen on
chain, the chain itself has to be fast
enough that the market can actually feel
tradeable. When a system's too slow, the
gap between quote and execution gets
worse.
>> [music]
>> And that gap is where your edge dies.
So, a slow chain can host finance, but a
fast chain can host markets. Now, we
know speed gets a lot of attention, but
cost matters, too. And Solana's base
network fee is really small. Like, I'm
talking 5,000 lamports per signature,
which makes the raw settlement cost of a
simple transaction
>> [music]
>> less than a penny.
And once raw settlement is cheap enough,
things that [music] weren't economically
viable before start to actually make
sense. You can do things like
microtransactions or frequent
rebalancing or complex multi-instruction
flows. Now, yeah, that's not your all-in
execution cost. You still have things
like LP fees and slippage, but [music]
here's what's different. More of that
cost is actually visible.
In traditional markets, a lot of traders
focus on explicit commissions and
overlook the hidden cost like speed
capture, payment for order flow, dark
routing, queue positioning. And all
these costs are real, but they're
buried.
On Solana, you can inspect the route,
[music] estimate slippage, compare
venues, and look directly at the pools
or order books that are involved in your
transaction. And the cost is still
there, but now you can actually see it,
and that changes how you think about
execution entirely. [music]
Now, let's talk about liquidity. Solana
is already one of the largest on-chain
trading venues by spot volume, and that
volume isn't concentrated in one place.
It's spread across AMMs, concentrated
liquidity pools, order books,
aggregators, and perps venues. [music]
And yeah, that's fragmentation, but in
this case, fragmentation isn't actually
a bad thing.
>> [music]
>> Yes, it adds complexity, but it also
adds opportunity because the best price
isn't always sitting in one place.
And that's exactly why routing matters.
If you understand execution,
fragmentation becomes part of your edge.
Traditional markets are fragmented, too.
You have liquidity spread across
exchanges, dark venues, wholesalers, and
routing destinations. So, edge always
came from knowing where the liquidity
actually is and how your order gets
there. The difference on Solana is that
more of that structure is visible. You
get fragmentation plus transparency, and
that's something that you can actually
model as an individual trader. So, that
brings us to where aggregators come in.
>> [music]
>> Think of Jupiter as a part smart order
router, part liquidity map, and part
[music] execution layer.
It doesn't remove fragmentation. It
actually [music] makes fragmented
liquidity usable. And that's one of the
reasons Solana works so well as a
trading ecosystem. The chain is fast
enough, costs are low enough, and the
routing layer is good enough that
fragmented liquidity still feels
tradeable. And then there's
composability, which is one of the most
misunderstood ideas in crypto, in my
opinion. For a trader, it means that
your entire stack can work together
inside one programmable environment. You
have spot position, hedge, collateral,
settlement, automation, and it doesn't
all have to live in separate systems.
You can buy spot, hedge somewhere else,
route to another aggregator, settle, and
then move into the next trade without
having to wait on broker rails, or
banking rails, or a separate clearing
workflow.
You can hold a tokenized asset, post it
as collateral in something like Kamino,
[music]
borrow USDC, and then redeploy. All
without leaving the ecosystem.
So, you have more flexibility, faster
capital movement, [music] more room to
build strategy directly on top of the
market. So, overall, why trade on
Solana? Well, [music] I think it
combines five things that rarely show up
together. Speed, low settlement cost,
transparent market structure, fragmented
liquidity that creates an opportunity,
and composability that lets the stack
work as one.
So, the real edge on Solana comes from
understanding the plumbing. How
liquidity is structured, how routing
works, how fees affect inclusion, and
how market design shapes execution
quality. So, this is the introduction
[music] to a Solana trading series,
which will include conceptual videos for
general trading knowledge that are each
paired with hands-on coding tutorials.
So, stay tuned, and drop any questions
in the comments. I'll see you in the
next one.